<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Rachel Thomas, PhD</title>
<link>https://rachel.fast.ai/index.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://rachel.fast.ai/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>an AI researcher going back to school for immunology</description>
<image>
<url>https://rachel.fast.ai/images/thomas-card.jpg</url>
<title>Rachel Thomas, PhD</title>
<link>https://rachel.fast.ai/index.html</link>
</image>
<generator>quarto-1.3.450</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 14:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Deep learning gets the glory, deep fact checking gets ignored</title>
  <dc:creator>Rachel Thomas</dc:creator>
  <link>https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2025-06-04-enzyme-ml-fails/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Deep learning is glamorous and highly rewarded. If you train and evaluate a Transformer (a state-of-the-art language model) on a dataset of 22 million enzymes and then use it to predict the function of 450 unknown enzymes, you can publish your results in Nature Communications (a very well-regarded publication). Your paper will be viewed 22,000 times and will be in the top 5% of all research outputs scored by Altmetric (a rating of how much attention online articles receive).</p>
<p>However, if you do the painstaking work of combing through someone else’s published work, and discovering that they are riddled with serious errors, including hundreds of incorrect predictions, you can post a pre-print to bioRxiv that will not receive even a fraction of the citations or views of the original. In fact, this is exactly what happened in the case of these two papers:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-023-43216-z">Functional annotation of enzyme-encoding genes using deep learning with transformer layers | Nature Communications</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2024.07.01.601547v2.full">Limitations of Current Machine-Learning Models in Predicting Enzymatic Functions for Uncharacterized Proteins | bioRxiv</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2025-06-04-enzyme-ml-fails/altmetric.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:70.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">A Tale of two Altmetric Scores</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>This pair of papers on enzyme function prediction make for a fascinating case study on the limits of AI in biology and the harms of current publishing incentives. I will walk through some of the details below, although I encourage you to read the papers for yourself. This contrast is a stark reminder of how hard it can be to evaluate the legitimacy of AI results without deep domain expertise.</p>
<section id="the-problem-of-determining-enzyme-function" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-problem-of-determining-enzyme-function">The Problem of Determining Enzyme Function</h2>
<p>Enzymes are what catalyze reactions, so they are crucial for making things happen in living organisms. Enzyme Commission (EC) numbers provide a hierarchical classification system for thousands of different functions. Given a sequence of amino acids (the building blocks of all proteins, including enzymes), can you predict what the EC number (and thus, the function) is? This seems like a problem that is custom-made for machine learning, with clearly defined inputs and outputs. Moreover, there is a rich dataset available, with over 22 million enzymes and their EC numbers listed in the online database UniProt.</p>
</section>
<section id="an-approach-with-transformers-ai-model" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="an-approach-with-transformers-ai-model">An Approach with Transformers (AI model)</h2>
<p>A research paper used a transformer deep learning model to predict the functions of enzymes with previously unknown functions. It seemed like a good paper! The authors used a reasonable, well-regarded neural network architecture (two transformer encoders, two convolutional layers, and a linear layer) that had been adopted from BERT. They looked at regions with high attention to confirm that these were biologically significant, which suggests that the model had learned underlying meaning and provided interpretability. They used a standard training, validation, and test split on a dataset with millions of entries. The researchers then applied the model to a dataset where no “ground truth” was known to make ~450 novel predictions. For these novel predictions, they randomly selected three to test <em>in vitro</em> and confirmed that the predictions were accurate.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2025-06-04-enzyme-ml-fails/kim-fig1a-4.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:75.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">A transformer model, shown on the left, was used to predict Enzyme Commission numbers for uncharacterized enzymes in E. coli. Three of these were tested in vitro (Fig 1a and Fig 4 from Kim, et al.)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="the-errors" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-errors">The Errors</h2>
<p>The Transformer model in the Nature paper made hundreds of “novel” predictions that are almost certainly erroneous. The paper had followed a standard methodology of evaluating performance on a held-out test set, and did quite well on that (although later investigation suggests there may have been <a href="https://www.kaggle.com/code/alexisbcook/data-leakage">data leakage</a>). The results claimed for enzymes where no ground truth is known were full of errors.</p>
<p>For instance, the gene E. coli YjhQ was predicted to be a mycothiol synthase, but mycothiol is not synthesized by E. coli at all! The gene yciO, which evolved from the gene TsaC, had already been shown a decade earlier <em>in vivo</em> to not have the same function as TsaC, yet the Nature paper concluded it did have the same function.</p>
<p>Of the 450 “novel” results given in the Nature paper, 135 of these results were not novel at all; they were already listed in the online database UniProt. Another 148 showed unreasonably high levels of repetition, with the same very specific enzyme functions reappearing up to 12 times for genes of <em>E. coli</em>, which biologically implausible.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2025-06-04-enzyme-ml-fails/de-crecy-fig5.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:75.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Most of the “novel” results from the transformer paper were either not novel, unusually repetitious, or incorrect paralogs (Fig 5 from de Crecy, et al.)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="the-microbiology-detective" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-microbiology-detective">The Microbiology Detective</h2>
<p>How did these errors come to light? After the model had been trained, validated, and evaluated on a dataset involving millions of entries, it was used to make ~450 novel predictions, and three of these were tested in vitro. It just so happens that one of the enzymes selected for in vitro testing, yciO, had already been studied extensively over a decade earlier by Dr.&nbsp;de Crécy-Lagard. When Dr.&nbsp;de Crécy-Lagard read that deep learning had predicted that yciO had the same function of another gene, TsaC, she knew from her long years in the lab that this was incorrect. Her previous research had shown that the TsaC gene is essential in <em>E. coli</em> even if yciO is present in the same genome and even when yciO gene is overexpressed. Moreover, the yciO activity reported by Kim et al.&nbsp;is more than four orders of magnitude (i.e.&nbsp;10,000 times) weaker than that of TsaC. All this suggests that yciO does NOT serve the same key function as TsaC.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2025-06-04-enzyme-ml-fails/de-crecy-fig7.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:80.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Two enzymes with a common evolutionary ancestor, but different functions (Fig 7 from de Crecy, et al.)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>YciO and TsaC do have structural similarities, and YciO evolved from an ancestor of TsaC. Decades of research on protein and enzyme evolution have shown that new functions often evolve via duplication of an existing gene, followed by diversification of its function. This poses a common pitfall in determining enzyme function, because the genes will have many similarities with the ones they duplicated and then diversified from.</p>
<p>Thus, looking at structural similarities is only one type of evidence for considering enzyme function. It is also crucial to look at other types of evidence, such as neighborhood context of the genes, substrate docking, gene co-occurrence in metabolic pathways, and other features of the enzymes.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2025-06-04-enzyme-ml-fails/de-crecy-fig2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:80.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">It is important to look at multiple types of evidence when classifying enzyme function (Fig 2 from de Crecy, et al.)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="hundreds-of-likely-erroneous-results" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="hundreds-of-likely-erroneous-results">Hundreds of Likely Erroneous Results</h2>
<p>Spotting this one error inspired de Crécy-Lagard and her co-authors to take a closer look at all of the enzymes found to have novel results in the Kim, et al, paper. They found that 135 of these results were already listed in the online database used to build the training set and thus not actually novel. An additional 148 of the results contained a very high level of repetition, with the same highly specific functions reappearing up to 12 times. Biases, data imbalance, lack of relevant features, architectural limitations, or poor uncertainty calibration can all lead models to “force” the most common labels from the training data.</p>
<p>Other examples were proven wrong via biological context or a literature search. For instance, the gene YjhQ was predicted to be a mycothiol synthase but mycothiol is not synthesized by <em>E. coli</em>. YrhB was predicted to synthesize a particular compound, which was already predicted to be synthesized by the enzyme QueD. A form of <em>E. coli</em> with a QueD mutant was unable to synthesize the compound, showing that this is not in fact the function of YrhB.</p>
</section>
<section id="rethinking-enzyme-classification-and-true-unknowns" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="rethinking-enzyme-classification-and-true-unknowns">Rethinking Enzyme Classification and “True Unknowns”</h2>
<p>Identifying enzyme function actually consists of two quite different problems which are commonly conflated:</p>
<ul>
<li>propagating known function labels to enzymes in the same functional family</li>
<li>discovering truly unknown functions</li>
</ul>
<p>The authors of the second paper observe, “By design, supervised ML-models cannot be used to predict the function of true unknowns.” While machine learning can be useful for propagating known functions to additional enzymes, there are many types of errors that can occur: including failing to propagate labels when they should, propagating labels when they should not, curation mistakes, and experimental mistakes. Unfortunately, erroneous functions are being entered into key online databases such as UniProt, and this incorrect data may be further propagated if it is used to train prediction models. This is a problem that increases over time.</p>
</section>
<section id="need-for-domain-expertise" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="need-for-domain-expertise">Need for Domain Expertise</h2>
<p>It is not news that AI work will be more highly rewarded and supported than work that closely inspects the underlying data and integrates deep domain knowledge. The aptly titled <a href="https://research.google/pubs/everyone-wants-to-do-the-model-work-not-the-data-work-data-cascades-in-high-stakes-ai/">“Everyone Wants to do the Model Work, not the Data Work”</a> paper involving dozens of machine learning practitioners working on high-stakes AI projects and found that inadequate-application domain expertise was one of a few key causes of catastrophic failures.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2025-06-04-enzyme-ml-fails/sambasivan-square.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:70.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Sources of cascading failures in machine learning systems (Fig 1 from Sambasivan, et al.)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>These papers also serve as a reminder of how challenging (or even impossible) it can be to evaluate AI claims in work outside our own area of expertise. I am not a domain expert in the enzyme functions of <em>E. coli</em>. And for most deep learning papers I read, domain experts have not gone through the results with a fine-tooth comb inspecting the quality of the output. How many other seemingly-impressive papers would not stand up to scrutiny? The work of checking hundreds of enzyme predictions is less glamorous than the work of building the AI model that generated them, yet it is even more important. How can we better incentivize this type of error-checking research?</p>
<p>At a time when funding is being slashed, I believe we should be doing the opposite and investing even more into a range of scientific and biomedical research, from a variety of angles. And we need to push back on an incentive system that is disproportionately focused on flashy AI solutions at the expense of quality results.</p>
</section>
<section id="related-reading" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="related-reading">Related Reading:</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-09-10-gaps-risks-science/">Gaps and Risks of AI in the Life Sciences</a></li>
<li><a href="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-11-20-ai-immunology/">AI and Immunology</a></li>
<li><a href="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-02-20-ai-medicine/">“AI will cure cancer” misunderstands both AI and medicine</a></li>
</ul>
<p><br></p>
<p>You can subscribe to be notified of new blog posts by submitting your email below:</p>
<script type="text/javascript" src="https://campaigns.zoho.com.au/js/zc.iframe.js"></script>
<iframe scrolling="no" frameborder="0" id="iframewin" width="100%" height="100%" src="https://zcmp-pd.maillist-manage.com.au/ua/Optin?od=11d0c075b7ed49&amp;zx=11a17553b1&amp;tD=156971d471c7b09&amp;sD=156971d471c7cb3">
</iframe>


</section>

<p><br><br><i>I look forward to reading your responses. Create a free GitHub account to comment below.</i></p> ]]></description>
  <category>machine learning</category>
  <category>science</category>
  <guid>https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2025-06-04-enzyme-ml-fails/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jun 2025 14:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2025-06-04-enzyme-ml-fails/tsac-ycio.jpeg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Will gene sequencing finally prove its worth?</title>
  <dc:creator>Rachel Thomas</dc:creator>
  <link>https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2025-05-13-spatial-omics/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="dna-sequencing-hasnt-lived-up-to-the-hype" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="dna-sequencing-hasnt-lived-up-to-the-hype">DNA sequencing hasn’t lived up to the hype</h2>
<p>Twenty to thirty years ago, <a href="https://theconversation.com/why-sequencing-the-human-genome-failed-to-produce-big-breakthroughs-in-disease-130568">politicians, scientific leaders, journalists, and even Nobel laureates</a> predicted that sequencing the human genome would revolutionize how we treat disease. And while the advances in DNA sequencing that have occurred since then have improved recognition and treatment for some cancers and rare diseases, on the whole the field has not lived up to earlier hype.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2025-05-13-spatial-omics/time-94-99.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:60.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Time Magazine covers from 1994 and 1999 about genetics</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>In an article titled <a href="https://theconversation.com/why-sequencing-the-human-genome-failed-to-produce-big-breakthroughs-in-disease-130568">“Why sequencing the human genome failed to produce big breakthroughs in disease”</a>, a biology professor highlights that most common diseases are not caused by a single gene. In fact, common diseases are often linked to <a href="https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC6391102/">hundreds of gene variants</a>, and even collectively, these variants still account for only a small fraction of disease variance. Here, I want to focus on two other key limitations of DNA sequencing, and how they are now being addressed with new approaches.</p>
</section>
<section id="what-dna-cant-tell-us" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-dna-cant-tell-us">What DNA can’t tell us</h2>
<p>First, DNA can’t answer many questions about how cells and organisms work in practice. A neuron in the brain has the same DNA as a liver cell, yet the two have completely different functions. This is because different segments of DNA are turned off or on in different cells. To understand how cells are actually working, you need to know about proteins and RNA (RNA is the intermediary which translates DNA into protein). Proteins are what build the structure of cells, catalyze chemical reactions within the cell, and allow communication between cells. Healthy and unhealthy cells in the same organism will usually have the same DNA. For instance, if some regions of the intestines are experiencing an IBD (irritable bowel disease) flare and others aren’t, they would all have the same DNA, yet likely different RNA and protein levels.</p>
<p>A second big problem is that many key sequencing techniques destroy spatial information. You essentially may have to put tissue or cells into a blender in order to get rich information about DNA or RNA sequences. While this data is informative, it turns out that locations of cells within a piece of tissue, and locations of regions within a cell, are also very important! Again, considering the case in which some regions of the <a href="https://www.mypathologyreport.ca/pathology-dictionary/cryptitis/">intestine are inflamed due to IBD</a>, yet others aren’t, mixing them all together in a blender will lose or distort useful information. Look at the difference between crypts in a healthy segment of the colon (on the left) compared to inflamed crypts (on the right).</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2025-05-13-spatial-omics/cryptitis.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:80.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Differences between a healthy bowel (on the left) and an inflamed bowel (on the right). Source: mypathologyreport.ca</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Recently, we have seen a rise in breakthroughs that allow us to obtain data about location. Spatial techniques are a necessary and exciting step beyond DNA sequencing. The power of spatial information showed up as a major theme at a <a href="https://www.multiomics2024.org/">conference I attended last year</a>, and spatial techniques have been recognized by Nature Methods as “<a href="https://www.nature.com/collections/dbifijbacd">Method of the year</a>” <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41592-020-01033-y">twice</a> in the last 5 years.</p>
</section>
<section id="a-few-major-areas-of-innovation" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-few-major-areas-of-innovation">A Few Major Areas of Innovation</h2>
<p>What is genetic sequencing anyway? There are a number of different types of sequencing that have been invented in the last 30 years. Walking through a brief history will illustrate what these technologies are, and what they can and cannot do. To make it concrete, let’s look at the example of how they have been applied to cancer treatment.</p>
<p><strong>Sanger Sequencing</strong>: This is an older technology dating back to the 1970s, and which was the main way of sequencing DNA up until 2005. Sanger sequencing was one of the methods used in the mid-90s to identify the genes BRCA1 and BRCA2 as key genetic risk factors for breast cancer. The process of discovering BRCA1/BRCA2 involved scientists slowly zeroing in on their chromosomal locations over a period of years. Several other cancer genes were discovered during this time period as well. While Sanger sequencing is effective on smaller amounts of DNA, it can be quite slow to deal with larger volumes. It took over 10 years to sequence the first copy of the human genome using Sanger Sequencing. It is still used today as a simple and reliable way to test for known mutations (such as BRCA1/BRCA2) or for smaller tasks.</p>
<p><strong>High-Throughput Sequencing</strong>: New technology released in the mid-2000s allowed DNA to be cut into lots of short pieces and for millions of pieces to be sequenced in parallel at once. This approach, called high-throughput sequencing, was significantly faster than Sanger sequencing. High-throughput sequencing has many applications, including to cancer treatment, by making it cheaper and faster to sequence DNA to identify particular mutations which can influence treatment decisions. Method of the Year | Nature Methods</p>
<p><strong>Long-read sequencing</strong>: High-throughput sequencing has the advantage of high accuracy, but the downside of short sequence lengths. In the 2010s, technologies were released with the opposite set of strengths and weaknesses. Long-read sequencing provides the advantage of long sequence lengths, although the downside of lower accuracy. To compare, high-throughput sequencing uses DNA strands that are a few hundred base pairs long, whereas long-read sequencing uses DNA strands that are tens of thousands base pairs long. Both technologies have different strengths and are widely used today.</p>
<p><strong>Single-Cell Sequencing</strong>: High-throughput sequencing involves sequencing the DNA of many cells at once, but sometimes it is useful to sequence individual cells. In a tumor, different cells can have different mutations. It is possible that a small subset of the mutations may drive metastasis (the spread of cancer to other areas) or resistance to treatment. Identifying these driver mutations can guide treatment decisions, since particular driver mutations can predict the effectiveness of various drugs. Key mutations may be drowned out in the average if you sequence the entire tumor. This is one reason why it is useful to be able to sequence single cells, and not just obtain the average of many cells. Single-cell sequencing was selected as Nature Methods method of the year in 2013.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2025-05-13-spatial-omics/legos.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:80.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">A Lego interpretation of bulk RNA-seq; single-cell RNA-seq; spatial transcriptomics; and the original organ. Source: Bo Xia, <span class="citation" data-cites="BoXia7">@BoXia7</span></figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p><strong>Multi-Omics</strong>: The study of DNA is genomics. DNA alone gives us an incomplete picture of an organism. Epigenomics can provide information about which regions of DNA are active or silenced. To understand how different cells function, as well as cells in different states of disease or health, you also need to know about their RNA and proteins. This data is contained in the field of transcriptomics (transcripts are strands of RNA transcribed from DNA) and proteomics (the proteins in a cell). Metabolomics looks at small molecules (such as sugars, amino acids, and vitamins) within the body and exposomics includes all sorts of environmental exposures. Collectively, these fields are known as -omics or multi-omics. It is valuable to combine multiple types of -omics together for richer sources of information, since each has different strengths, limitations, and insights to offer. Multi-Omics is an exciting area that draws on lots of data, with applications to cancer, infectious disease and immunology.</p>
<p><strong>Spatial</strong>: Spatial information lets us see all the variation within a section of the body– such as a segment of the intestines, the liver, or a cancerous tumor. This variation can often be significant for understanding disease and treatment prognosis. To better understand why spatial techniques are useful, let us dive into some background about cancer.</p>
</section>
<section id="tumors-arent-just-lumps-of-bad-cells" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="tumors-arent-just-lumps-of-bad-cells">Tumors aren’t just lumps of bad cells</h2>
<p>Cancer is defined as excess cell division. I used to think that tumors were just clumps of “bad cells”, where “good” and “bad” were binary states. This is incorrect. Tumors are not uniform, and within the category of “bad” there is a great deal of variation and heterogeneity. Different cells within a tumor may have different mutations from one another. And our immune systems sometimes build <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41568-024-00728-0">complex defense structures</a> within tumors in attempts to more effectively fight them. How close a cancerous cell is to one of these immune structures impacts how likely the body is to destroy the cancerous cell.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2025-05-13-spatial-omics/tls.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:70.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Notice all the variation within this tumor!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Immunologist <a href="https://www.multiomics2024.org/angela-ferguson">Dr.&nbsp;Angela Ferguson</a>, who studies head and neck cancers, describes tumors as having a “physical landscape”. She has shown how the organization and structure within a <a href="https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2024.04.18.590189v1.full">tumor can predict and guide treatment outcomes</a>. Her work found that cancer progression is “landscape-dependent”, where landscape refers to the locations of immune cells and structures within a tumor. It is not enough to study cancer cells in isolation. We need to understand their layout. Methods that effectively put tumor cells into a blender in order to sequence them, disrupting their spatial information, are insufficient on their own. Mapping that spatial information can hold the keys for more effective treatment.</p>
<p>Single cell sequencing approaches allow a greater number of genes to be measured, whereas spatial approaches measure fewer genes but also provide location information. Combining these two approaches can prove powerful.</p>
</section>
<section id="programming-libraries-applied-to-spatial--omics" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="programming-libraries-applied-to-spatial--omics">Programming Libraries Applied to Spatial -Omics</h2>
<p>We are living at a time when multi-omics, spatial information, and user-friendly programming libraries are converging for easier exploration and discovery. For instance, below is an image I created using the common Python programming libraries pandas and matplotlib of data the NIH has shared about a rare liver disease. The image shows a slice of liver tissue, with gene expression overlaid in a color scale ranging from purple (low expression) to yellow (highest expression).</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2025-05-13-spatial-omics/liver-alb.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:80.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Using Matplotlib to display a cross-section of liver with gene expression</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The NIH dataset contain images of slices of liver and expression of many different genes, from both healthy patients and those with a rare liver disease. https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE240429. The plot shows expression of albumin, a protein which helps transport other molecules around the body, overlaid on top of the liver, illustrating which regions produce more or less of this protein. Data science tools are invaluable for transforming and plotting such data.</p>
<p>In addition to being able to use standard Python libraries (such as Pandas and Matplotlib) for visualing this data, there are many specialist libraries as well. The <a href="https://scverse.org/">Scverse</a> (Sc = single cell) includes a number of Python libraries focused on single cell analysis.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2025-05-13-spatial-omics/sc-verse.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:70.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">The SC Verse includes libaries for single cell sequencing analysis</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>There are also popular R libraries for single cell analysis and multi-omics, such as <a href="https://portals.broadinstitute.org/harmony/index.html">Harmony</a>, <a href="https://satijalab.org/seurat/">Seurat</a>, and <a href="https://mixomics.org/">mixOmics</a>.</p>
<p>With all of these tools and technologies, it is an exciting time to be working at the intersection of data science and microbiology. The causes of most diseases are complex and multi-factorial, although new approaches of spatial multi-omics provide unprecedented types of useful information.</p>
</section>
<section id="related-reading" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="related-reading">Related Reading:</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2025-01-16-cpath-foundation/">What AI can tell us about microscope slides</a></li>
<li><a href="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-09-10-gaps-risks-science/">Gaps and Risks of AI in the Life Sciences</a></li>
<li><a href="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-11-20-ai-immunology/">AI and Immunology</a></li>
</ul>
<p>You can subscribe to be notified of new blog posts by submitting your email below:</p>
<script type="text/javascript" src="https://campaigns.zoho.com.au/js/zc.iframe.js"></script>
<iframe scrolling="no" frameborder="0" id="iframewin" width="100%" height="100%" src="https://zcmp-pd.maillist-manage.com.au/ua/Optin?od=11d0c075b7ed49&amp;zx=11a17553b1&amp;tD=156971d471c7b09&amp;sD=156971d471c7cb3">
</iframe>


</section>

<p><br><br><i>I look forward to reading your responses. Create a free GitHub account to comment below.</i></p> ]]></description>
  <category>science</category>
  <guid>https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2025-05-13-spatial-omics/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 12 May 2025 14:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2025-05-13-spatial-omics/time-94-99.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Missing Medical Data Holding Back AI</title>
  <dc:creator>Rachel Thomas</dc:creator>
  <link>https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2025-01-24-missing-data/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Amidst the barrage of executive orders and announcements Trump made during his first week in office are two which highlight common misunderstandings and obfuscations about the relationship between <a href="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2023-05-16-ai-centralizes-power/">data, AI, and power</a>. These announcements contradict each other:</p>
<ul>
<li>He announced a <a href="https://apnews.com/article/trump-health-communications-cdc-hhs-fda-1eeca64c1ccc324b31b779a86d3999a4">freeze on communications</a> from scientific and health agencies, stopping them from sharing health data with the public, including infectious disease data about the emerging H5N1 bird flu outbreak. The CDC was unable to send out its <a href="https://www.medpagetoday.com/infectiousdisease/generalinfectiousdisease/113905">weekly MMWR report</a> for the first time in 60 years. Without data, it can be nearly impossible to understand, much less respond, to growing threats.</li>
<li>He announced a <a href="https://apnews.com/article/trump-ai-openai-oracle-softbank-son-altman-ellison-be261f8a8ee07a0623d4170397348c41">large investment in AI</a>, including promises to use AI to analyze health records, help doctors care for patients, and treat cancer.</li>
</ul>
<p>Hiding health-related data from the public does not improve the lives of patients, particularly since those with cancer are vulnerable to infection. As I wrote in a <a href="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-02-20-ai-medicine/">previous post</a>, claims that AI will cure cancer are often used as superficial marketing, ignoring the ways that AI could further disempower patients (whose knowledge and experiences are already disregarded by the medical system).</p>
<p>The orders for scientific agencies to pause communications are a particularly vivid and drastic example of the <a href="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2021-10-12-medicine-political/">political nature of data</a>. However, choices about what data is collected and who it is made available to have been shaped by social influences, financial factors, and power disparities long before this past week.</p>
<section id="missing-data-sets" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="missing-data-sets">Missing Data Sets</h2>
<p>A decade ago, Mimi Onuoha coined the concept of <a href="https://github.com/MimiOnuoha/missing-datasets">Missing Data Sets</a>. She uses this term specifically to refer to “<em>blank spots that exist in spaces that are otherwise data-saturated</em>.” So it’s not just that this data does not exist, but that it ought to exist.</p>
<p>Originally writing in 2016, Onuoha gives the example of how “<em>traditionally there has been little history of standardized and rigorous data collected about police brutality… The group who would make the most sense to monitor this issue—the law enforcement agents who create the data set in the first place—have no incentive to actually gather such data, which could prove incriminating</em>.”</p>
<p>Missing Datasets are not just a USA-based phenomenon. In early 2024, the <a href="https://theconversation.com/the-uk-government-aims-to-stop-publishing-stats-on-homeless-peoples-deaths-heres-why-thats-a-problem-223879">UK government announced</a> that it would stop collecting and publishing statistics about homeless people’s deaths, even as rising evictions and a housing shortage were making the issue more urgent than ever. Public outcry led the government to reconsider.</p>
<p>As another example, <a href="https://thesicktimes.org/2024/02/06/how-we-track-covid-19-with-wastewater-and-other-data-sources/">wastewater data provides</a> a reliable indicator of covid rates, even in the absence of testing. The health department in my home state (Queensland, Australia) used to monitor covid wastewater data, but <a href="https://www.data.qld.gov.au/dataset/queensland-wastewater-surveillance-for-sars-cov-2">stopped doing so in 2022</a>, even as several other states in Australia have continued to collect and share such data. This was a political decision. The lack of this data for Queensland from late 2022 onwards registers as a blank space compared to <a href="https://www.cdc.gov/nwss/rv/COVID19-nationaltrend.html">other countries</a> and <a href="https://www.health.wa.gov.au/articles/a_e/coronavirus/covid19-wastewater-surveillance">other</a> <a href="https://www.health.nsw.gov.au/Infectious/covid-19/Pages/sewage-surveillance.aspx">Australian states</a>, and compared to Queensland’s own record in 2020-2022. There have been multiple covid waves since 2022. This is missing data.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2025-01-24-missing-data/covid-wastewater.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:70.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">This graph from San Jose, California shows how closely wastewater data (in red) tracked with covid positive tests (green) up until most people stopped testing in mid-2022. In Queensland, we do not have access to this data.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Onuoha explains several reasons that <a href="https://github.com/MimiOnuoha/missing-datasets">data may be missing</a>. Those who could collect it lack incentives to do so, or in some cases may even want to hide or obscure it. Another possible reason is that the data in question may be of a type that resists straight-forward quantification or doesn’t fit with our current modes of collection. Her work also reminds us that data won’t solve all problems, and that in some cases missing data can function as protection for disadvantaged groups.</p>
</section>
<section id="decades-of-work-not-instant-magic" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="decades-of-work-not-instant-magic">Decades of work, not instant magic</h2>
<p>Some people mistakenly believe AI can just be sprinkled on a problem to achieve a magic solution, without understanding the many necessary underlying ingredients. The example of AlphaFold, whose creators won a Nobel Prize in Chemistry for their work, disproves these misconceptions. AlphaFold can predict the 3D structures of proteins with unprecedented accuracy. While clever algorithmic innovations were pivotal to AlphaFold, its success would not have been possible without a large, high-quality dataset that thousands of researchers contributed to for decades.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2025-01-24-missing-data/insulin-2ways.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:70.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">AlphaFold takes a string of amino acids (on the left) and converts it into a 3D structure (on the right)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The construction of the dataset that made AlphaFold possible began a full 50 years earlier. The Protein Data Bank (PDB) was <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/newbio233223b0">announced in 1971</a> as a database to store information about the 3D structures of proteins. The files were originally shared and distributed using magnetic tape data storage. Initially, just a handful of entries were added to the database each year. By 1980, there were a total of 69 entries present in the database. However, that number <a href="https://www.rcsb.org/stats/growth/growth-released-structures">grew exponentially</a>, reaching nearly 200,000 entries by 2022. Access to the data was updated from magnetic tapes to the world wide web. In the mid-1990s, a <a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/prot.340230303">bi-annual competition</a> was created, encouraging teams to write computer program to predict 3D protein structures. The existence and quality of the database and competition are what led to the record-shattering creation of AlphaFold.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2025-01-24-missing-data/PDB-per-year.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:70.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">The number of proteins stored in PDB grew exponentially with time</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>AlphaFold wouldn’t have been possible without the rich data of the PDB. Machine learning engineer <a href="https://www.owlposting.com/p/wet-lab-innovations-will-lead-the">Abhishaike Mahajan writes</a>, “<em>In my opinion, what Alphafold2 pulled off — applying a clever model to a large body of pre-existing data to revolutionize a field — is something that will be extremely hard to replicate. Why? Because we’re almost out of that pre-existing data. If we had enough, sure, throw ML at it and call it a day, just as Alphafold2 did. But we don’t have that luxury anymore</em>.”</p>
<p>Mahajan argues that <a href="https://www.owlposting.com/p/wet-lab-innovations-will-lead-the">“<em>We are running out of data</em>,”</a> and that the next big innovations of AI applied to biology will require new wet-lab techniques to collect larger quantities of different biological data types than currently possible.</p>
</section>
<section id="ai-projects-begin-at-the-wrong-starting-point" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="ai-projects-begin-at-the-wrong-starting-point">AI projects begin at the wrong starting point</h2>
<p>Many machine learning projects begin with an existing dataset, and ask “what can we do with this data?” However, this ignores all the data that we don’t have and ends up overlooking many important questions. The harder question is, “what are the biggest questions in your area, and what data would be useful to answering them?”</p>
<p>In some cases, technical limitations prevent the collection of more, better, or different data. In the case of PDB and CASP, creating those datasets required large teams working for decades to produce, curate, and organize data.</p>
<p>One thing that is holding back the application of AI to medicine is lack of the <strong>right</strong> data. It is not just that medical data may be scattered or hard to access; in many cases, the most interesting variables aren’t being measured or collected at all. Scores of useful and high impact data are not being gathered. For example, widespread medical biases often lead doctors to incorrectly dismiss the pain or physiological symptoms of patients as “anxiety” or “drug-seeking” behavior. In these cases, doctors may fail to record relevant observations or run tests that could gather valuable data. Promises about what AI can achieve with electronic health records must be tempered with the awareness that the data within is too often biased, incorrect, or missing.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2025-01-24-missing-data/med-bias-research.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:85.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">An AI analysis of electronic health records will be shaped by all the above biases in diagnosis delays, pain mismanagement, and misdiagnoses</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>As another example, many people have observed that an infection was the trigger for onset of Type 1 Diabetes in themselves or their children, yet they often don’t know which type of virus caused that infection. Determining causality around this requires large longitudinal studies, which are expensive and difficult to run.</p>
<p>AI is great at finding patterns in existing data. However, AI will not be able to solve this problem of missing and erroneous underlying data.</p>
</section>
<section id="asking-the-right-questions" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="asking-the-right-questions">Asking the right questions</h2>
<p>The most fundamental machine learning question, prior to the questions I mentioned above, is “what type of society do we want to live in?”</p>
<p>When <a href="https://archive.is/OdM2b">school districts implemented a computer program</a> to automatically fire supposedly low-performing teachers, there were numerous issues with the underlying algorithm and data. One key type of data used as input was student test scores, which had often been altered due to cheating scandals by school administrators. The algorithms were also based on the dubious assumption that changes in standardized test scores were a reasonable proxy for teacher quality.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2025-01-24-missing-data/teacher-fired.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:70.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Washington Post headline about a teacher who was loved by students and parents, but fired by an algorithm</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Test scores don’t capture a teacher’s creativity, care for their students, or ingenuity. They don’t capture the challenges their particular students are facing, or how those students may grow and flourish apart from test scores.</p>
<p>This is an example of an algorithm where there was low quality data, the wrong data, and faulty assumptions. However, even if it had been implemented differently, the whole premise would still be a terrible idea. Many of us (myself included) find the idea of a society where we use computerized algorithms to fire teachers to be dystopian. The answer to “How can we best use AI to fire teachers?” is that we shouldn’t.</p>
</section>
<section id="negative-spaces" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="negative-spaces">Negative spaces</h2>
<p>The decisions around which, where, and how data is collected, and who it is shared with, all exert a strong but often overlooked influence on the shape of scientific research and algorithm creation. As I dive deeper into the intersection of microbiology and machine learning, I am seeking to understand not just the data that I’m shown, but also the factors shaping its collection and the negative spaces of what is missing.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2025-01-24-missing-data/negative-space.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:45.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Negative Space, image by Boris Thaser, Wikimedia Commons</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>We are in a disturbing era, in which relevant health and safety data that we previously had access to are actively being cut off. Issues of bias and politics that dismiss the viewpoints of marginalized groups were already bad and seem to be worsening.</p>
<p>While promises of AI improving healthcare may seem appealing, systems that ignore patient expertise risk building on faulty premises and causing more harm than good.</p>
</section>
<section id="further-reading" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="further-reading">Further Reading</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://dl.acm.org/doi/10.1145/3351095.3372829">Lessons from archives: strategies for collecting sociocultural data in machine learning</a> by Eun Seo Jo and Timnit Gebru, on lessons machine learning practitioners could learn from the library sciences</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/MimiOnuoha/missing-datasets">On Missing Data Sets</a> by Mimi Onuoha</li>
<li><a href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/258173934_The_end_of_forgetting_Strategic_agency_beyond_the_panopticon">The end of forgetting: Strategic agency beyond the panopticon</a> by Jonah Bossewitch and Aram Sinnreich, on how information flow relates to power dynamics</li>
<li><a href="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-02-20-ai-medicine/">“AI will cure cancer” misunderstands both AI and medicine</a> by Rachel Thomas</li>
<li><a href="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2021-11-04-data-disasters/">Avoiding Data Disasters</a> by Rachel Thomas</li>
</ul>
<p><br><br></p>
<p>You can subscribe to be notified of new blog posts by submitting your email below:</p>
<script type="text/javascript" src="https://campaigns.zoho.com.au/js/zc.iframe.js"></script>
<iframe scrolling="no" frameborder="0" id="iframewin" width="100%" height="100%" src="https://zcmp-pd.maillist-manage.com.au/ua/Optin?od=11d0c075b7ed49&amp;zx=11a17553b1&amp;tD=156971d471c7b09&amp;sD=156971d471c7cb3">
</iframe>


</section>

<p><br><br><i>I look forward to reading your responses. Create a free GitHub account to comment below.</i></p> ]]></description>
  <category>ethics</category>
  <category>machine learning</category>
  <category>science</category>
  <guid>https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2025-01-24-missing-data/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 14:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2025-01-24-missing-data/negative-space-header.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>What AI can tell us about microscope slides</title>
  <dc:creator>Rachel Thomas</dc:creator>
  <link>https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2025-01-16-cpath-foundation/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>The lavender images below show <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/31226662/">breast tissue</a>. There are many questions doctors could want to answer using these images: They could want to know whether there are tumors present or not. If there is a tumor, doctors would want to classify its stage, make predictions about how likely the patient is to respond to treatment, and to detect whether the tumor has spread from another organ.</p>
<p>All of these are questions which people are now tackling with machine learning. They fall within the area of <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41374-020-00514-0"><strong>computational pathology</strong></a>, often abbreviated <strong>CPath</strong>. In the past year, two CPath AI models were released which achieved state-of-the-art results. Here I will discuss an introduction to this field, what these models do, and what some key challenges are going forward.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2025-01-16-cpath-foundation/bach.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:90.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Breast tissue images from the BACH: Grand challenge on breast cancer histology</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<section id="cpath-foundation-models" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="cpath-foundation-models">CPath foundation models</h2>
<p>There is a powerful idea about how to make more accurate CPath models. Rather than train a model on a single type of tissue and a single task (e.g.&nbsp;identifying cancer in breast tissue), train a model on images of tissue from many different organs (breasts, lymph nodes, lungs, prostate, heart,…) and on multiple different tasks (recognizing cancer, determining the stage and subtype of the cancer, segmenting cells, and predicting treatment outcomes). Patterns learned from one dataset or one task are likely to generalize to others.</p>
<p>Such models are known as CPath <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Foundation_model"><strong>foundation models</strong></a>. In general, a <em>foundation model</em> is a machine learning model which is trained on a sufficiently diverse large dataset which can then be adapted for a range of downstream tasks. This idea is commonly used in the area of language models such as Chat-GPT and Claude.ai. Language foundation models are trained on many types of language tasks and intended to generalize across different corpuses of text (e.g.&nbsp;wikipedia, reddit posts, academic papers, online conversations, news articles, and more). ImageNet models trained to recognize a huge variety of different pictures often serve as foundation models for images. The success of foundation models within the areas of language and more general images is a key reason why we might expect pathology foundation models to be useful too.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2025-01-16-cpath-foundation/types-of-tissue.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:60.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Tissues are groups of cells with similar structure and function. Different types of tissue within the human body include nervous, muscle, connective, and epithelial tissue. Image: Wikimedia</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Two notable CPath foundation models were released in 2024: <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-024-07441-w">Prov-GigaPath</a> and <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41591-024-02857-3">UNI</a>. Both models achieved state-of-the-art performance on dozens of pathology tasks (although they were not directly compared to one another). Another <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.15217">relevant paper</a> (from Kaiko.ai) studied the impact of dataset size and model size on CPath model performance.</p>
</section>
<section id="learning-the-vocab" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="learning-the-vocab">Learning the Vocab</h2>
<p>Medicine is full of jargon and specialized vocabulary. Pathology refers to the study of disease. It is a broad field, and can include everything from dissecting dead bodies to analyzing blood samples. One key focus of <em>computational pathology</em> is analyzing and interpreting <em>whole slide images (WSIs)</em> and in some cases combined with accompanying meta-data about a patient. Whole slide images refers to the complete microscope slide, although in many cases the region of interest (such as particular cancerous or inflamed cells) may be much smaller, just occupying a subset of the slide.</p>
<p><em>Machine learning (ML)</em> is a subfield of Artificial intelligence (AI) which involves learning from past data, and is increasingly being used with great success in pathology. The focus of most computational pathology ML models is on images of tissue, on microscope slides. That is what we will focus on in this post as well.</p>
</section>
<section id="so-many-tasks" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="so-many-tasks">So Many Tasks!</h2>
<p>There are many different benchmarks that CPath models can be tested on. These involve numerous datasets: related to different areas of the body, with different sizes, and with different purposes. They also involve a variety of tasks, including binary classification, image segmentation, and outcome prediction. Prov-GigaPath attained state-of-the-art performance on 25 out of the 26 tasks it was evaluated on and UNI attained state-of-the-art performance on 34 different tasks. Here I will give examples of just 3 of these tasks.</p>
<section id="task-prostate-cancer-cell-grading" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="task-prostate-cancer-cell-grading">Task: prostate cancer cell grading</h3>
<p>In the 1960s, the pathologist Dr.&nbsp;Donald Gleason came up with a grading scale for rating cells as they progressed from normal to prostate cancer. The Gleason Grading system is still widely used and is considered a powerful predictor of how prostate cancer patients will fare. A major medical image conference (MICCAI) <a href="https://aggc22.grand-challenge.org/AGGC22/">held a competition in 2022</a> for researchers to create algorithms to determine the Gleason grades when given images of prostate tissue.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2025-01-16-cpath-foundation/gleason.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:70.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Examples of UNI predictions of Gleason grades for a section of prostate tissue. Figure 3b from the UNI paper</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The prostate tissue is shown in pink, and segments have been colored in blocks based on where they fall on the Gleason scale.</p>
</section>
<section id="task-identifying-early-signs-of-rejection-after-a-heart-transplant" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="task-identifying-early-signs-of-rejection-after-a-heart-transplant">Task: identifying early signs of rejection after a heart transplant</h3>
<p>Rejection is the main cause of mortality in patients who have received a heart transplant. Since the early stages of rejection can be asymptomatic, it is standard for patients to receive frequent biopsies for 1-2 years following a transplant. These are known as endomyocardial biopsies (EMB), since they remove a small sample of tissue from the inner lining (endo) of the heart (cardial) muscle (myo). Accurately interpreting the results of these biopsies is a key question. Underestimating the chance of rejection could lead to dangerous delays in treatment, but overestimating could lead to alarm and unnecessary follow-ups or treatment. Assessment of the sampled tissue by experienced pathologists has higher variability than many other tasks, such as cancer diagnosis. Deep learning is being used to tackle this task, in models such as <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41591-022-01709-2">Cardiac Rejection Assessment Neural Estimator (CRANE)</a> and the CPath foundation model UNI.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2025-01-16-cpath-foundation/cardiac-tissue-zoom.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:70.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Each row shows a different sample of cardiac tissue, with a different medical issue. On the far left are the whole slide images, then zoomed in at higher resolution on a key Region of Interest (ROI). On the far right is a heat map for the most zoomed in area showing which features the algorithm has identified as significant. Figure 3 from the CRANE paper.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="task-genetic-mutations-in-cancer" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="task-genetic-mutations-in-cancer">Task: Genetic Mutations in Cancer</h3>
<p>For several common genetic mutations in tumors, there are <a href="https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC9012285/">specific drugs known to target those mutations</a>. This has a direct application for clinical treatment. Since genetic mutations can change the form and function of cells, it is reasonable to expect that this information could be deduced from images of the cancer cells. Deep learning models have been built to identify genetic mutations from tissue slides. The benefits of using a computational approach are that it can be scaled as an increasing number of relevant genetic mutations and molecular biomarkers are being discovered. <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s43018-020-0087-6">Task-specific models</a> have been built for this, and this is one of the tasks that foundation models can be tested on.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2025-01-16-cpath-foundation/cancer-mutations.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:70.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Different types of cancer listed along the y-axis and 20 common genetic mutations listed on the y-axis. Figure 1D from Kather, 2020.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
</section>
<section id="we-need-more-data" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="we-need-more-data">We need more data</h2>
<p>One key challenge in the area of CPath foundation models is gathering enough training data. <a href="https://www.cancer.gov/ccg/research/genome-sequencing/tcga">The Cancer Genome Atlas (TCGA)</a> was an ambitious project launched in 2006 by the National Cancer Institute in the USA. Over a 12 year period, samples were collected from over 11,000 patients of 33 different cancer types, and all this data was made publicly available. While this is a rich dataset and a useful resource, all 3 papers we’ve looked at concluded that TCGA is not large enough for effective foundation models. In addition to limited data size, TCGA also has limited diversity, consisting mostly of slides from the primary site of cancer, but not metastasized cancers or different types of tissues.</p>
<p>Researchers at Kaiko.ai <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.15217">tested the impact of scaling</a> both the size of their model and the size of the training dataset. While they found limited need to scale model size beyond a certain point, they found that larger datasets continued to lead to increased performance. They concluded that TCGA was likely not large enough and shared their plans to build a larger training set, and are now partnering with cancer centers across Europe to create a dataset for their model.</p>
<p>The researchers behind two other CPath foundation models reached the same conclusion about data set size, and gathered massive datasets to train their models. This required partnering with healthcare centers. <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-024-07441-w">Prov-GigaPath</a>, a model created by Microsoft Research and Providence Genomics involved data from 30,000 patients across 28 cancer centers (which are part of Providence Healthcare company). <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41591-024-02857-3">UNI</a>, a cPath model created by a team at Harvard, MIT, and the Broad Institute, involved the creation of the Mass-100K: a dataset with over 100K whole slide images across 20 tissue types collected from Mass General Hospital, Brigham &amp; Women’s Hospital, and Genotype-Tissue Expression (GTEx) consortium.</p>
<p>These partnerships and curation of training datasets are currently a crucial component of building CPath foundation models. Curating datasets carefully poses many challenges as well. Combining data from different sources, which often use different protocols for how slides are sampled and prepared, can introduce significant biases.</p>
</section>
<section id="different-scales" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="different-scales">Different scales</h2>
<p>CPath foundation models face the difficulty of capturing both local patterns (that show up in a small tile within a slide) and global patterns across the whole slide. Many tiny tiles are found within a slide.</p>
<p>Some models, such as the <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2206.02647">Hierarchical Image Pyramid Transformer</a> (from several of the same authors as UNI), use hierarchical approaches to deal with these multiple scales.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2025-01-16-cpath-foundation/hierarchical.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:60.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Hierarchical Structure of Whole-Slide Images, Figure 1 from Chen, et al, 2020</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Other models, such as Prov-GigaPath, treat the tiles as tokens, encoding both the tiles and the slide as a whole as model inputs. Prov-GigaPath uses both a slide encoder and a tile encoder to take into account these two different scales.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2025-01-16-cpath-foundation/slides-prov-gigapath.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:60.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Treating slides as tokens, Figure 1a from the Prov-GigaPath paper</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>In pathology clinics, diagnosis and treatment decisions are often made at the patient level, whereas CPath models are often highly focused on regions of interest. Accommodating the multiple relevant scales (small tiles, whole slides, and patient-level) for pathology is a consideration that CPath models need to balance.</p>
</section>
<section id="going-forward" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="going-forward">Going Forward</h2>
<p>It is still early in the world of CPath and there are many growth opportunities, including the continued need for large and diverse datasets, ways to further optimize model training, tasks which have previously received less focus, and the difficulties of integrating models into clinical work. As the <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.15217">authors of the kaiko.ai paper</a> wrote, “<em>We are still at the very beginning of developing a truly foundational pathology foundation model.</em>” It is a hopeful sign that these models achieve state-of-the-art results on dozens of benchmarks, but it still remains to be seen when and how they will be used in clinical settings.</p>
</section>
<section id="related-reading" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="related-reading">Related Reading:</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-07-24-neural-nets/">The Most Common and Useful Neural Nets</a></li>
<li><a href="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-04-03-ai-antibiotics/">Using AI to Discover New Antibiotics</a></li>
<li><a href="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-11-20-ai-immunology/">AI and Immunology</a></li>
</ul>
<p>You can subscribe to be notified of new blog posts by submitting your email below:</p>
<script type="text/javascript" src="https://campaigns.zoho.com.au/js/zc.iframe.js"></script>
<iframe scrolling="no" frameborder="0" id="iframewin" width="100%" height="100%" src="https://zcmp-pd.maillist-manage.com.au/ua/Optin?od=11d0c075b7ed49&amp;zx=11a17553b1&amp;tD=156971d471c7b09&amp;sD=156971d471c7cb3">
</iframe>


</section>

<p><br><br><i>I look forward to reading your responses. Create a free GitHub account to comment below.</i></p> ]]></description>
  <category>machine learning</category>
  <category>science</category>
  <guid>https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2025-01-16-cpath-foundation/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 14:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2025-01-16-cpath-foundation/gleason.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>AI and Immunology</title>
  <dc:creator>Rachel Thomas</dc:creator>
  <link>https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-11-20-ai-immunology/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>I spent close to 20 years focused on mathematics and data science, including cofounding the research lab fast.ai, which focused on the powerful family of AI algorithms known as deep learning. A few years ago, I decided to make a big pivot and <a href="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2023-02-07-school-immunology/">return to school</a> for immunology. What motivated my sudden change amidst a successful career? We are now living in <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/science/archive/2022/04/how-climate-change-impacts-pandemics/629699/">a pandemicene</a>, a period with increasingly likely pandemics. Climate change and habitat destruction are crowding species into closer and closer contact with humans. <a href="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-08-13-crowds-vs-friends/">Frequent global travel and mega-cities</a> allow unprecedented opportunities for viruses to spread and mutate. Antibiotic resistance is rising rapidly.</p>
<p>At the same time, we have been learning more and more about the <a href="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2023-03-07-viruses1/">long-term consequences of infections</a>– seemingly mild infections can contribute to long-term <a href="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2023-03-22-viruses2/">autoimmune diseases, neurodegenerative diseases</a>, and cancer. The human immune system is incredibly complex and there is much we don’t know about it. Immunology is a crucial area to study. In this post, I want to gather some of my writing and talks on how AI is being applied to immunology.</p>
<center>
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/I3q5-cBebKA?si=MFcccYwqKdSTGth0" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen="">
</iframe>
<br> <em>My 30 minute presentation on key areas where deep learning is being applied to immunology</em>
</center>
<section id="using-ai-to-predict-what-t-cells-will-bind-to" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="using-ai-to-predict-what-t-cells-will-bind-to">Using AI to predict what T cells will bind to</h3>
<p>T cells are one of the most important cell types of our immune systems. Figuring out how to predict what a T cell will bind to (meaning what cells it can recognize as bad and coordinate attacks against) would be a vital medical breakthrough.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-07-09-t-cells/">Decoding T cells with AI</a></li>
<li><a href="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-07-24-neural-nets/">The Most Common and Useful Neural Nets</a></li>
<li><a href="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-08-01-ai-t-cells/">AI’s Quest to Predict T Cell Binding– The Holy Grail of Immunology</a></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="mapping-immune-cell-communication-networks" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="mapping-immune-cell-communication-networks">Mapping immune cell communication networks</h3>
<p>Immune cells talk to each other through complex networks. NLP, math, and immunology are useful in studying these networks.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-01-23-cytokines1/">Applying AI to Immune Cell Networks</a></li>
<li><a href="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-02-06-cytokines2/">How Immune Cells Communicate</a></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="discovering-new-antibiotics" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="discovering-new-antibiotics">Discovering new antibiotics</h3>
<p>Bacterial resistance to existing antibiotics is an urgent threat. AI is being used to search for new antibiotics.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-04-03-ai-antibiotics/">Using AI to Discover New Antibiotics</a></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="ethical-risks-of-ai-applied-to-immunology" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="ethical-risks-of-ai-applied-to-immunology">Ethical risks of AI applied to immunology</h3>
<p>The enthusiasm about AI in medicine is failing to grapple with realities of the system. Recognizing gaps in how AI is applied to scientific research can prevent potential shortcomings and risks.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-09-10-gaps-risks-science/">Gaps and Risks of AI in the Life Sciences</a></li>
<li><a href="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-02-20-ai-medicine/">“AI will cure cancer” misunderstands both AI and medicine</a></li>
</ul>
<p>You can subscribe to be notified of new blog posts by submitting your email below:</p>
<script type="text/javascript" src="https://campaigns.zoho.com.au/js/zc.iframe.js"></script>
<iframe scrolling="no" frameborder="0" id="iframewin" width="100%" height="100%" src="https://zcmp-pd.maillist-manage.com.au/ua/Optin?od=11d0c075b7ed49&amp;zx=11a17553b1&amp;tD=156971d471c7b09&amp;sD=156971d471c7cb3">
</iframe>


</section>

<p><br><br><i>I look forward to reading your responses. Create a free GitHub account to comment below.</i></p> ]]></description>
  <category>machine learning</category>
  <category>science</category>
  <guid>https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-11-20-ai-immunology/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 19 Nov 2024 14:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-11-20-ai-immunology/thumbnail.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>5 Devious Tricks Pathogens Use Against Us</title>
  <dc:creator>Rachel Thomas</dc:creator>
  <link>https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-11-12-devious-tricks/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>“The human immune system is amazing, with an impressive range of techniques to protect against invaders.”</p>
<p>I see this sentiment expressed frequently by everyone from doctors quoted in newspaper articles to online commentators in parenting groups. And I share it– I loved learning about the intricate processes our bodies deploy against invaders when I took graduate immunology.</p>
<p>However, the point that has struck me again and again as I complete my MS in Microbiology-Immunology is that pathogens (virues, bacteria, fungi, and parasites that cause disease) have a fierce and varied range of techniques to overcome our immune defenses, and even to turn our cells’ own defenses against us. Seeing the ingenuous lengths pathogens are capable of illustrates that it is often preferable to avoid getting infected in the first place.</p>
<p>There is hubris in exalting only the human immune system, without also recognizing the capacity of viruses and bacteria to wreak havoc in clever ways. In this post, I will cover 5 different ways that pathogens subvert our defenses.</p>
<section id="commandeering-the-cells-own-machinery" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="commandeering-the-cells-own-machinery">1. Commandeering the cell’s own machinery</h2>
<p>The year is 2063. An insect-like robot with a swinging gait and clamp-like feet marches along a beam in a space colony, transporting the large cargo suspended behind it.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-11-12-devious-tricks/motor-protein-short.gif" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:70.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">A motor protein moving cargo along a microtubule</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Ooops– what I meant to say is that a microscopic motor protein in one of our cells moves a bag of proteins along the cytoskeleton, away from or towards the nucleus. This is not a metaphor; we actually have <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=y-uuk4Pr2i8">motor proteins that are moving complexes</a> within our cells. The above gif is scientifically accurate, not a fantastical invention.</p>
<p>I used to think that cells were just sacks of liquid, with various items such as the mitochondria or nucleus floating haphazardly around inside. I couldn’t have been more wrong. Just as beams, drywall, and supporting columns are necessary to organize and support the architecture of a building, so too do our cells have an intricate organization arranged by various filaments and microtubules.</p>
<p>Tiny motor proteins that look like robots are used to transport items around. But just like the space colony mentioned above, these robots can be commandeered by enemy invaders. Unfortunately, the virus which plays a role in Alzheimer’s Disease is able to use these motor proteins for its own goals.</p>
<p>Alert! Alert! Herpes Simplex Virus-1 (HSV-1) has breached the cell! When HSV-1 invades a human cell, it <a href="https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC2132479/">commandeers our motor proteins</a> to transport the viral capsids (packets containing the viral DNA) to the nucleus. The sooner the viral capsids arrive at the nucleus, the sooner the virus can begin replicating, printing copies of itself to invade the neighboring space colonies, err, I mean neighboring cells. HSV-1 has turned our cell’s own machinery against us to improve its speed and efficiency in infection.</p>
<p>HSV-1 is a virus responsible for causing fever blisters on the mouth. It can live latently in neurons, activating or reactivating after decades. A growing body of research is linking HSV-1 with a <a href="https://www.ox.ac.uk/news/2022-08-02-viral-role-alzheimers-disease-discovered">major role in Alzheimer’s Disease</a>. The ability of HSV-1 to use human motor proteins to speed its path to the nucleus for replication is just one of the many devious tricks that different viruses and bacteria have developed.</p>
</section>
<section id="blocking-signals-from-t-cells" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="blocking-signals-from-t-cells">2. Blocking signals from T cells</h2>
<p>T cells are a keystone of the human immune system. T cells can rearrange their genes, allowing for the potential recognition of billions of different invaders. And yet they are outmatched by a single-celled organism (<em>T. cruzi</em>) carried in the feces of so-called “kissing bugs” (triatomine bugs). A kissing bug bites you in your sleep. In many cases, you may not even notice, and experience no symptoms in the coming weeks. <em>T. cruzi</em> is a species of trypanasome, a tiny one-celled parasite, and causes Chagas disease. They live in the feces of the bugs can enter the bite wound and travel through your bloodstream. They have a preference for making a home inside the muscles of your heart, the lining of your digestive tract, or the nervous system. <em>T. cruzi</em> can hang out patiently for 10-30 years, but are then ready to wreak havoc. Up to one third of patients experience heart problems caused by destruction of cardiac tissues. One in 10 experience neurological and digestive problems. Some die sudden deaths.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-11-12-devious-tricks/chagas-cdc.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:60.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">T. cruzi parasites are stained as purple squiggles against the red blobs of human blood cells</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Why haven’t your T cells protected you? One of <em>T. cruzi</em>’s devious tricks is that it is able to block the key signal which coordinates the T cell response (a messenger known as IL-2). IL-2 is crucial for activating T cells. With its messaging blocked by these tiny parasites, T cells don’t activate and respond to the threat, and <em>T. cruzi</em> is able to survive in humans, later causing great destruction. While there is medication available that will work if addressed early, remember, most people have no symptoms initially. The best protection against <em>T. cruzi</em> is to avoid it in the first place, which typically requires access to a home that keeps out insects.</p>
</section>
<section id="making-a-home-in-b-cells" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="making-a-home-in-b-cells">3. Making a home in B cells</h2>
<p>In addition to T cells, the other type of adaptive immune cells that can rearrange their genes are B cells. B cells produce antibodies, small proteins that bind to a target, marking it for destruction by other immune cells. Through a process of hypermutation, B cells are able to create carefully custom-tuned antibodies to target any enemy they want. The flexibility and nearly infinite customizability of this defense are powerful.</p>
<p>Given the powers of B cells, you might expect that invaders would want to stay away from B cells. Yet Epstein-Barr Virus (EBV) and measles virus actively seek out B cells. EBV is able to set up a life-long home in memory B cells, hanging out for decades. While EBV is best known for causing mono, it can also <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41579-022-00770-5">cause multiple sclerosis</a> and cancer. In multiple sclerosis, the immune system attacks the nervous system, damaging neurons and causing plaques in the brain. If the viral antigens present in EBV look similar to neurons, this could confuse the immune system and lead to autoimmune attack.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-11-12-devious-tricks/EBV.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:65.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Epstein-Barr Virus can cause a lot of trouble</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Another virus, measles, plays an amnesia trick on memory B cells, causing them to forget their memories of other invaders that the B cells had previously learned to recognize. This <a href="https://www.bbc.com/future/article/20211112-the-people-with-immune-amnesia">immune amnesia</a> is why children who have been infected with measles are significantly more likely to die of other illnesses later, compared to children who have never had measles. The measles vaccine drastically <a href="https://www.bmj.com/content/311/7003/481">reduces the risk of non-measles related deaths</a> by letting the immune system retain the information it has learned.</p>
</section>
<section id="thriving-in-acid" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="thriving-in-acid">4. Thriving in acid</h2>
<p>T cells and B cells aren’t the only immune cells targeted by particular pathogens. Macrophage literally means “big eater”. These large cells are a useful component of the immune system, because they are ready to eat your enemies. Macrophages contain bags of acid to acidify and ingest invaders. They share the digested remnants of their foes with other immune cells to activate them and coordinate the immune response. Sounds fierce, right? And yet a number of bacteria have developed strategies to survive inside them.</p>
<p>“No! No! Don’t dump me in acid!” cries the bacteria <em>C. burnetii</em> insincerely, “Anything but that!” In fact, that is exactly what <em>C. burnetii</em> (the bacteria that causes Q fever) wants. It thrives in acid. Acidic environments are where it can replicate, making more and more copies of itself. <em>C. burnetii</em> prospers inside the the acidic pouches in macrophages.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-11-12-devious-tricks/Coxiella-burnetii-NIH.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:65.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">C. burnetii (shown in green) replicating inside of a vacuole, a location in macrophages where invaders are supposed to be killed</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p><em>C. burnetii</em> is not the only type of bacteria that has figured out strategies for living inside the “Big Eaters” that are meant to protect us. Tuberculosis is a bacteria that spreads when infected people cough, talk, or even just breathe. Approximately <a href="https://www.who.int/teams/global-tuberculosis-programme/tb-reports/global-tuberculosis-report-2021/disease-burden/mortality">1.2 million people die each year of tuberculosis</a>, almost double the number of people who die of HIV. Tuberculosis that is resistant to multiple antibiotics is an urgently growing problem. And unfortunately, our macrophages are unable to eliminate it. When macrophages take a big bite of an invader, this leads to the invader initially being inside a pouch called a phagosome, within the macrophage. Usually, the next step is for the phagosome (containing the invader) to merge with a pouch of acid (called the lysosome). However, tuberculosis is able to prevent that next step from happening. Tuberculosis loves to just kick back and relax within the phagosome. It can remain latent for years or even decades, but can reactivate if the immune system becomes suppressed.</p>
</section>
<section id="when-we-put-the-brakes-on-translation-viruses-cut-the-brake-lines" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="when-we-put-the-brakes-on-translation-viruses-cut-the-brake-lines">5. When we put the brakes on translation, viruses cut the brake lines</h2>
<p>Pathogens don’t just target immune cells, but also more general processes found in all our cells. A central action is the process by which DNA is transcribed into RNA, which is then translated into proteins. Proteins are the building blocks for all sorts of important materials within our cells, and proteins allow communication throughout the body. The process of producing protein from RNA is known as “translation”. Viruses love to take over our protein translation machinery for their own purposes.</p>
<p>In my molecular cell biology course, the professor recently taught about a method our cells have for halting protein translation when they have been infected by a virus (for my fellow immunology nerds, we were learning about <a href="https://www.frontiersin.org/journals/microbiology/articles/10.3389/fmicb.2021.757238/full">PKR phosphorylation of eIF2α</a>– but you don’t need to know any details of it for this blog post). It is a bit like our cells stepping on the brakes to stop protein translation.</p>
<p>That is encouraging that we can block those pesky viruses from producing proteins! Good job, human cells!</p>
<p>Then, on the following slide, the professor <a href="https://www.frontiersin.org/journals/microbiology/articles/10.3389/fmicb.2021.757238/full">shared a paper</a> that covers 31 different viruses that sabotage this safety mechanism (via 9 categories of actions) so that they can use the cells’ machinery to produce their own viral proteins regardless. Viruses have effectively cut the brake lines, so they can continue barreling along. And so it goes. Each time I learn about an intricate and ingenuous aspect of the human immune system, the following page seems to contain a clever way that pathogens circumvent or subvert it.</p>
</section>
<section id="viewing-pathogens-with-appropriate-respect-gives-us-a-path-forward" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="viewing-pathogens-with-appropriate-respect-gives-us-a-path-forward">Viewing pathogens with appropriate respect gives us a path forward</h2>
<p>There is hubris in focusing solely on the impressive coordination of the human immune system, without considering the methods that pathogens have developed for counterattacks. This information is not just an academic point; it has practical impact. Unthinking repetition of the soundbite “the immune system is amazing” can lull people into a false sense of confidence that disease prevention is unnecessary. While it can be discouraging to think about the methods bacteria and viruses have for causing harm and the surprising long-term consequences of some infections, the good news is that many infections are preventable.</p>
<p>Mosquito nets, houses that keep out insects, <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/society/2007/jan/19/health.medicineandhealth3">sewage systems, clean drinking water</a>, <a href="https://www.abc.net.au/news/2024-09-24/covid-safety-schools-course-sick-days-teachers-long-covid/104319032">air purifiers</a>, <a href="https://theconversation.com/masks-work-our-comprehensive-review-has-found-229658">N95s in public indoor spaces</a>, and <a href="https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.abg2025">good ventilation</a> are all effective at reducing risks of infection. In particular, research from the past few years has illustrated that <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/society/2007/jan/19/health.medicineandhealth3">cleaning up indoor air quality</a> would likely stop transmission of numerous pathogens.</p>
<p>I still marvel at the intricacy of the human immune system, but alongside that marvel, I keep a commensurate respect for the serious deviousness of many pathogens.</p>
</section>
<section id="related-reading" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="related-reading">Related Reading:</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-08-13-crowds-vs-friends/">Our immune systems evolved for a different world (that didn’t involve 100,000 global flights per day)</a></li>
<li><a href="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-04-25-microbiome-1/">Surprises of the Microbiome</a></li>
<li><a href="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2023-03-22-viruses2/">Viruses: The Silent Triggers of Autoimmune and Neurodegenerative Diseases</a></li>
</ul>


</section>

<p><br><br><i>I look forward to reading your responses. Create a free GitHub account to comment below.</i></p> ]]></description>
  <category>science</category>
  <guid>https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-11-12-devious-tricks/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 11 Nov 2024 14:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-11-12-devious-tricks/Coxiella-burnetii-NIH-thumbnail.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>In defense of screen time</title>
  <dc:creator>Rachel Thomas</dc:creator>
  <link>https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-10-29-screen-time/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>My daughter is constantly creating– her passions include making art, writing fiction, coding interactive games, and composing music. Yet, I regularly see news articles and media pundits suggesting that my husband and I are doing things all wrong. The reason for these claims? My daughter uses screen-based tools, at least partially, and in some cases, entirely, to pursue the interests I listed in my first sentence. To give more detail on how she pursues her passions:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Art</strong>: She creates digital art in <a href="https://www.sketchbook.com/">Sketchbook Pro</a>, both on her own and in lessons. She also takes in-person art courses that involve a mix of acrylic painting, water colors, and sculpture.</li>
<li><strong>Coding</strong>: She loves coding in <a href="https://scratch.mit.edu/">Scratch</a> and <a href="https://p5js.org/">P5.js</a> to design and build interactive games.</li>
<li><strong>Creative writing</strong>: While her handwriting is on target for her age, she prefers typing, as it lets her write faster and express more complex ideas– we taught her touch typing when she was 5. She writes fiction both individually and collaboratively with friends.</li>
<li><strong>Music</strong>: She plays the piano, takes group singing lessons online, and enjoys composing music. There is a composition component to her piano lessons (which happen over zoom) and she composes music online through <a href="https://musiclab.chromeexperiments.com/">Chrome MusicLab</a> and <a href="https://flat.io/">Flat.io</a>.</li>
</ul>
<p>My daughter is not unique. Our family knows many other children with similar creativity levels who are excelling in their passions beyond what is often believed possible for their age groups.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-10-29-screen-time/music-lab.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:60.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Visual from Chrome Music Lab</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Parenting approaches are personal and often polarizing, so I normally don’t write on this topic. However, I am concerned by how several (in my view, false) points are being increasingly repeated by politicians and pundits: that screentime is very harmful for children, that it is essential for children’s well-being to attend in-person school every day (<a href="https://apnews.com/article/covid-flu-school-attendance-4845073e737db87f786e1d8c815a48f7">even</a> <a href="https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2023-08-12/got-a-cold-runny-nose-the-sniffles-no-worries-come-to-school-lausd-says">when</a> <a href="https://www.1news.co.nz/2024/09/26/govt-reveals-new-plan-for-getting-kids-to-school-heres-how-it-will-work/">sick</a>), and that it is important for workers to return to the office (even when their jobs can be done remotely).</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-10-29-screen-time/school-attendance.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:70.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">There has been a rise in policies requiring children to attend school while sick</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The above points are interlocking, since getting workers commuting to in-person offices requires children being at in-person school. And overemphasizing in-person school attendance overlooks a number of children whose needs aren’t being met by in-person school. It also overlooks a number of online and screen-based options opportunities to build skills, express creativity, and form friendships. Here I want to focus on some innovative ways that we can encourage children’s flourishing, whether that is as a supplement to in-person school, or instead of.</p>
<section id="a-false-binary" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-false-binary">A False Binary</h2>
<p>I often hear statements such as, “I’d rather kids played outside than on a computer.” But these choices aren’t binary! You don’t have to pick just one. My daughter plays outside AND on a computer. She plays in-person sports regularly AND has online hobbies. This year we threw her 2 birthday parties: an in-person one for her local friends AND an online one for her long-distance friends.</p>
<p>The term “screen time” is so broad as to be meaningless, clumping together many disparate activities. A child sitting next to a parent playing a math game together on the computer is screen time. Calling your grandparents on skype is screen time. Collaboratively composing music with your best friend in another country is screen time. Yet, when many people refer to screen time, they often seem to be referring to a child passively watching TV on their own (something which my husband and I almost never let our daughter do, and that she doesn’t seem interested in). With any screen-based activity, it is useful to consider:</p>
<ul>
<li>Is it social or solitary?</li>
<li>Does it involve creating content or consuming content?</li>
<li>Is it educational or not?</li>
</ul>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-10-29-screen-time/venn-diagram.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:70.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">A Venn Diagram showing how we think about screentime. We avoid the outside (white) region and mostly stick to the intersections.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>It is not that some of these options are always good or always bad, but rather that we need to have a nuanced view on different combinations of these factors and how much time you may want to spend on each.</p>
<p>Screens are a crucial tool and outlet for her expressing her creativity, and it saddens me to hear an increasing media narrative vilifying screen time for kids.</p>
<p>Two of my daughter’s best friends are kids she has never met in person (because they live in a different state and in a different country), yet she talks with each of them several times per week. She also has local friends that we get together with regularly in-person. The fact that she has several close long-distance friends isn’t surprising, because my husband and I have many close online / long-distance friendships as well. Our friendships aren’t any less real because they are over screens. Opening up the possibility for long-distance friendships has given us the option of finding additional friends we are particularly compatible with.</p>
</section>
<section id="increased-options" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="increased-options">Increased options</h2>
<p>Screen-based learning options make homeschooling more feasible for a wider range of families. Online resources (games, classes, and clubs) can offer opportunities that may not be available locally, can fill in gaps parents may not be qualified to cover, and offer an exciting variety of options. For instance, online courses have allowed my daughter to do the following (which are not available locally for us):</p>
<ul>
<li>have tutors/teachers based in 5 different countries, providing diverse experiences</li>
<li>take science courses including: particle physics for kids, biochem for kids (she has been with the same group of kids for 3 years), and a biology class where a small group of students could share images from their digital microscopes over zoom</li>
<li>participate in clubs for creating collaborative narratives, fanart, and fanfiction around two of her favorite series of books</li>
<li>complete mastery-based math games at her own pace, which allowed her and a few friends to end up many years above their grade levels</li>
</ul>
<p>As I wrote about in a previous post, <a href="https://www.fast.ai/posts/2022-09-06-homeschooling.html">we homeschool</a>, and this leaves our daughter with far more time for hobbies and socializing than in-person school gave us.</p>
</section>
<section id="in-person-school-does-not-work-for-everyone" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="in-person-school-does-not-work-for-everyone">In-person school does not work for everyone</h2>
<p>There are several categories of kids whose needs are often not met in traditional schools and frequently benefit from online options:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2020/08/10/opinion/coronavirus-school-closures.html">Neurodivergent kids</a>, who may deal with overstimulating, distracting, or painful sensory experiences in traditional schools</li>
<li>Gifted kids, who are not intellectually challenged in traditional schools</li>
<li><a href="https://www.wired.com/story/pandemic-homeschoolers-who-are-not-going-back/">Kids from marginalized cultures</a>, whose cultural heritage may not be reflected at school, or who may experience discrimination</li>
<li>Kids who are being bullied</li>
<li>Kids who have particular passions they would like to hyper-focus on (which are either not included in their school’s curriculum, or which they don’t get adequate time for)</li>
<li>Medically complex kids, including those who may be getting sick so often that they can’t attend school regularly, those for whom an illness could result in hospitalization, or whose health issues make it difficult to attend school in-person</li>
</ul>
<p>It is an injustice that schools are not inclusive of all children. While individuals pulling their children out of school does not address this injustice (and we should continue to work for <a href="https://www.abc.net.au/news/2024-09-24/covid-safety-schools-course-sick-days-teachers-long-covid/104319032">safer</a> and more inclusive schools), many families have found it necessary to leave systems that are harming their kids.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-10-29-screen-time/homeschool-headlines.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:60.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">We were not alone in discovering that homeschooling worked better for our child</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="dont-judge-screentime-by-a-few-bad-examples" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="dont-judge-screentime-by-a-few-bad-examples">Don’t judge screentime by a few bad examples</h2>
<p>I would caution against writing off screen time or online learning based on a low quality or poorly designed experience. Maybe your child’s school went online in 2020 with no notice and no support, and they were stuck in a zoom with 25 other kids (this is not a good set-up for anyone!). We have found that with small group online tutoring, my daughter is able to be more social and talkative than she was in a large class at in-person school, and she masters more material in less time. However, even amongst small online groups, occasionally she’ll try a teacher or club that isn’t a good match for her, and in those cases, we discontinue it.</p>
<p>Since screentime is often equated with a way to occupy kids while parents do something else, there are often unrealistic expectations, particularly for the most rewarding screen-based tools (which tend to involve a learning curve and require support from a trusted adult). In many cases handing your child a new educational app and then leaving them alone can lead to frustration. Sitting with them and working through the app together can be relationship-building, prevent them from getting overly discouraged, and help them build confidence as you figure it out together. With age and experience, kids will likely be able to do more on their own.</p>
</section>
<section id="inclusion-and-accessibility" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="inclusion-and-accessibility">Inclusion and accessibility</h2>
<p>Countries around the world, including the <a href="https://www.ippr.org/articles/our-greatest-asset">USA</a>, <a href="https://news.sky.com/story/parents-of-children-with-complex-needs-worried-they-could-be-unfairly-fined-under-new-school-absence-rules-13213524">UK</a>, <a href="https://www.educationtoday.com.au/news-detail/Half-of-Australia-6155">Australia</a>, <a href="https://www.rnz.co.nz/news/political/513250/sickness-related-school-absences-to-be-targeted-under-government-plan">New Zealand</a>, <a href="https://english.kyodonews.net/news/2023/10/d8cd090637bd-japan-school-absenteeism-at-record-high-of-nearly-300000-in-fy-2022.html">Japan</a>, <a href="https://www.brusselstimes.com/1053759/number-of-absences-and-suspensions-among-pupils-in-belgium-on-the-rise">Belgium</a>, and <a href="https://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/school-absence-data-1.7156254">Canada</a> are seeing high levels of school absences. Factors for these record levels of absences include <a href="https://calgaryherald.com/opinion/columnists/opinion-we-dont-know-whats-causing-the-tsunami-of-sick-kids-but-wed-better-figure-it-out-fast">more frequent illnesses</a> (such as covid, RSV, and flu) and <a href="https://www.abc.net.au/news/2024-06-16/children-with-long-covid-dismissed-doctors-myth-virus-harmless/103959078">chronic health issues</a>. In mid-2024, many countries (including the USA and Australia) experienced a particularly high wave of the ongoing covid pandemic. Rates of disability are increasing, and people, <a href="https://www.scientificamerican.com/article/long-covid-is-harming-too-many-kids/">including children</a>, are continuing to develop new health conditions after viral infections.</p>
<p>A number of school districts are responding to these waves of illness by placing heightened emphasis on attendance to in-person school, in many cases pressuring or <a href="https://apnews.com/article/covid-flu-school-attendance-4845073e737db87f786e1d8c815a48f7">even</a> <a href="https://www.1news.co.nz/2024/09/26/govt-reveals-new-plan-for-getting-kids-to-school-heres-how-it-will-work/">requiring</a> <a href="https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2023-08-12/got-a-cold-runny-nose-the-sniffles-no-worries-come-to-school-lausd-says">children</a> and <a href="https://archive.md/T2oHI">teachers to attend school while sick</a>. In parts of the <a href="https://news.sky.com/story/parents-of-children-with-complex-needs-worried-they-could-be-unfairly-fined-under-new-school-absence-rules-13213524">UK</a>, <a href="https://www.indystar.com/story/news/education/2024/08/19/new-law-indiana-school-absences-juvenile-court-missing-school-ips-attendance-policy-criminal-charges/74818189007/">USA</a>, and <a href="https://www.rnz.co.nz/news/political/513250/sickness-related-school-absences-to-be-targeted-under-government-plan">New Zealand</a>, policies are being considered (or implemented) to charge parents fines if their children miss school too often. This is counterproductive, as it is hard to focus when unwell, attending school sick increases the likelihood of spreading illness to others, and <a href="https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2022-07-07/working-through-covid-sleep-rest-infection-test-positive">rest is a key way</a> to reduce risk of post-viral illness. None of these punitive attendance policies address root causes, such as <a href="https://www.abc.net.au/news/2024-09-24/covid-safety-schools-course-sick-days-teachers-long-covid/104319032">improving school air quality</a>, making sure parents have adequate paid leave to stay home with sick children, or decoupling school funding from attendance.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-10-29-screen-time/school-attendance.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:70.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Requiring kids to attend school while sick is only going to lead to more sick students and sick teachers</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>We are also seeing <a href="https://www.abs.gov.au/media-centre/media-releases/55-million-australians-have-disability">rising rates of disability</a> amongst <a href="https://x.com/Mike_Honey_/status/1842530019991769108?t=Cc8jUI2CayxAIBCpoZHiXw&amp;s=19">working age</a> adults. In the USA, there has been an <a href="https://www.ippr.org/articles/our-greatest-asset">increase in people with cognitive disabilities</a>. A <a href="https://www.bbc.com/news/business-68639144">BBC article</a> notes that in the UK sick people are leaving the workforce at record highs. Online access is a crucial part of accessibility and disability rights. For many disabled people, accessibility improved in 2020 with more remote options for work, medical appointments, conferences, and other events, and there is now a counter-reaction in which these options are being removed.</p>
<p>Every child is different, so what works for my family won’t work for everyone. I am not recommending that all families homeschool, or that nobody should attend in-person school. However, we need to consider innovative approaches to learning and communication, and that includes screen-based approaches.</p>
</section>
<section id="hopes-for-a-creative-and-inclusive-society" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="hopes-for-a-creative-and-inclusive-society">Hopes for a creative and inclusive society</h2>
<p>I want children to discover and develop passions that they enjoy (astronomy, writing, art, music, math, oceanography, chess, there are so many possibilities!) and to be able to connect with others who share their interests. Taking advantage of computer-based and online options opens up a world of possibility. I also want a society in which disabled people are included in events and opportunities, and in which people can rest when they’re sick or preferably avoid illness in the first place. Fewer people commuting to the office is better for the environment. Traditional school is failing a lot of kids. I hope we can consider a range of innovative educational and social approaches, and not exclude an entire category of valuable ways to communicate, create, and learn (e.g.&nbsp;screentime).</p>
</section>
<section id="related-posts" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="related-posts">Related Posts</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.fast.ai/posts/2022-09-06-homeschooling.html">My family’s unlikely homeschooling journey</a>: Prior to 2020, we never expected to homeschool, and now we have committed to it long-term.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.fast.ai/2022/03/15/math-person/">There’s No Such Thing as Not A Math Person</a>: based on a webinar I gave to parents addressing cultural myths about math and how to support your kids in their math education, even if you don’t see yourself as a “math person.”</li>
</ul>


</section>

<p><br><br><i>I look forward to reading your responses. Create a free GitHub account to comment below.</i></p> ]]></description>
  <category>education</category>
  <guid>https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-10-29-screen-time/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 14:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-10-29-screen-time/music-lab.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Gaps and Risks of AI in the Life Sciences</title>
  <dc:creator>Rachel Thomas</dc:creator>
  <link>https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-09-10-gaps-risks-science/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>AI is being used to tackle high-impact scientific problems, including <a href="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-04-03-ai-antibiotics/">searching for new antibiotics</a> to combat antibiotic-resistance and predicting <a href="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-08-01-ai-t-cells/">what foreign substances the immune system can recognize</a> as invaders. Amidst the excitement, it is important to keep in mind the gaps and risks of how AI is applied in science. Recognizing these risks opens up new opportunities and can prevent us from being caught off guard by shortcomings.</p>
<section id="missing-data" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="missing-data">Missing Data</h2>
<p>A recurring problem within data science is that often the data we would be most interested in does not exist or is too difficult to gather. In response, data scientists often instead use imperfect proxies (<a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC9122957/">Thomas and Uminsky 2022</a>), or alter their research questions to make use of the data they have (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1901.02547">Passi and Barocas 2019)</a>). While it is understandable for teams to work with what data is available, this can unduly influence the field to neglect areas where data is unavailable or more difficult to collect.</p>
<p>A research project titled “The library of missing data” (<a href="https://github.com/MimiOnuoha/missing-datasets">Mimi Onouha 2016</a>) inspected examples of datasets that are not collected and of information that we don’t have. What is not measured or recorded can be very revealing, yet it is harder to see an absence. It would be a valuable project to begin with the most important and high-impact open questions in various scientific fields, and then to determine which types of data would need to be collected, what experiments need to be run, and whether AI could prove useful.</p>
<p>While it is understandable that physical and financial constraints shape what types of data can be gathered, it is important to stay aware of how these influence research questions and findings. In some cases, a research area may be ignored due to lack of data. In other cases, results may be biased due to only cetain types of data being included. Missing data can be a type of representation bias, in which not all groups are adequately represented (<a href="https://dl.acm.org/doi/fullHtml/10.1145/3465416.3483305">Suresh and Guttag 2021</a>). For example, databases of <a href="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-07-09-t-cells/">T cell receptors</a> are highly biased towards particular genetic alleles and certain viral antigens. This data can still help us reach valuable conclusions, but it would be a mistake to overgeneralize those findings to alleles or antigen types that are not well-represented in the underlying data.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-09-10-gaps-risks-science/suresh-fig1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:75.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Sources of bias at different points throughout the process of creating machine learning models, Figure 1 from Suresh and Guttag, 2021</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="the-physical-world-is-complex-and-volatile" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-physical-world-is-complex-and-volatile">The physical world is complex and volatile</h2>
<p>In other fields, machine learning models have sometimes performed well in testing but failed to work as expected when deployed in the real world (<a href="https://research.google/pubs/everyone-wants-to-do-the-model-work-not-the-data-work-data-cascades-in-high-stakes-ai/">Sambasivan et al.&nbsp;2021</a>). Issues can arise when the context and quality of the training data is not fully understood (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1803.09010">Gebru et al.&nbsp;2021</a>). Biases and errors in datasets will propagate to downstream research. For example, The ImageNet Large Scale Visual Recognition Challenge (ILSVRC) dataset, often called ImageNet-1k, is widely used in image recognition research and has been cited 32,000 times. Over a quarter of the images in the dataset are of wild animals, yet researchers later found that over 12% of these wild animals are labeled incorrectly (<a href="https://ojs.aaai.org/index.php/AAAI/article/view/26682">Luccioni and Rolnick 2023</a>).</p>
<p>ML systems are trained in clearly defined environments, while the physical world often has complex and volatile underlying phenomena, which are not fully accounted for during training. This can create a brittleness to ML-generated solutions (<a href="https://research.google/pubs/everyone-wants-to-do-the-model-work-not-the-data-work-data-cascades-in-high-stakes-ai/">Sambasivan et al.&nbsp;2021</a>).</p>
</section>
<section id="neglecting-mechanistic-understanding" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="neglecting-mechanistic-understanding">Neglecting Mechanistic Understanding</h2>
<p>Language models are great at interpolating between underlying information, but not at creating things that are completely new (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.18654">Dziri et al.&nbsp;2023</a>). Brand new theories will still require human ingenuity. Upon receiving the Nobel Prize, biologist Sydney Brenner, warned that increased data does not necessarily lead to deeper understanding, saying “We’re drowning in an ocean, or a sea of data but we are starved of knowledge.” (<a href="https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/medicine/2002/brenner/interview/">Sylwan 2002</a>). Geneticist Paul Nurse, another Nobel Prize-winner, echoed these concerns. He wrote about the need for a renewed emphasis on new ideas and theory, alongside data. Nurse proposed that computer scientists need to be embedded alongside biologists to deeply understand the domain problems, “It is through deep familiarity with the biology — not simply a drive to collect more and more data — that important questions will be asked.” (<a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-021-02480-z">Nurse 2021</a>).</p>
<p>AI is a powerful tool, but it does not replace other ways of knowing about the world, including qualitative research and benchtop quantitative experiments. Machine learning and AI techniques are great at learning patterns in existing data.</p>
</section>
<section id="difficulty-of-cross-disciplinary-work" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="difficulty-of-cross-disciplinary-work">Difficulty of Cross-Disciplinary Work</h2>
<p>Interdisciplinary work is challenging, as it can be tough to remain on the cutting edge of two separate fields. At one extreme, you can have research based on sound immunology, but using deep learning techniques which are outdated or perhaps were never considered best practice. At the other extreme, you can have research using state-of-the-art deep learning, yet misunderstanding the core mechanisms of immunology or misconstruing the underlying context of datasets.</p>
<p>Meaningful collaboration between those with in-depth immunology knowledge and those with in-depth deep learning knowledge is necessary. Cross-disciplinary work is inherently difficult. Challenges can include differences of communication and work practices between practitioners with different backgrounds; insufficient expertise in one of the fields; and the difficulty of reconciling different approaches and priorities. Moreover, many academic institutions, journals, and other research centers often tend to value specific types of expertise over others. Deep learning and areas of the life sciences such as immunology are each highly complex, jargon-laden, and fast-moving fields. Finding researchers, or even teams, which can keep pace with both is challenging.</p>
<p>Deep learning practitioners often seek to automate systems without understanding what the greatest needs of domain experts are. When this automation leaves gaps, humans are often expected to fill these gaps in ways that are difficult, tedious, or impractical. In contrast, a more fruitful approach may be to take the strengths of both domain experts and deep learning into account from the start to leverage human strengths (<a href="https://slideslive.com/38917533/lessons-learned-from-helping-200000-nonml-experts-use-ml">Thomas 2019</a>).</p>
</section>
<section id="the-double-edged-sword-of-competitions" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-double-edged-sword-of-competitions">The Double-Edged Sword of Competitions</h2>
<p>Carefully structured competitions can play a valuable role in motivating research. Well-defined benchmarks make it clear how various approaches compare to one another. The winner of the 2012 ImageNet competition to identify objects in photographs, an algorithm called AlexNet, led to the mainstream popularization of neural networks and set off an avalanche of increased research into AI. The winner of the 2020 CASP challenge to take amino acid sequences as input and output the most likely 3D protein structure was a computer program called AlphaFold, which has revolutionized protein structure prediction. While these have been huge breakthroughs for their respective fields, over-focusing on competitions can lead to other research areas being neglected. In other cases, the models created for benchmark tasks may be inappropriately applied to other tasks for which they are less suited (<a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S2666389921001847">Paullada et al.&nbsp;2021</a>).</p>
<p>It takes effort to construct well-structured competitions. Data must be gathered and selected, often through benchtop laboratory experiments, while being cognizant of biases and overall representation within the dataset. It is also crucial to have appropriate splits between the training set and a held-out test set. When data leakage occurs, clues from the test set can be found in the training set, artificially inflating the performance of models (<a href="https://www.spiedigitallibrary.org/conference-proceedings-of-spie/11314/1131416/Hazards-of-data-leakage-in-machine-learning--a-study/10.1117/12.2549313.short#_=_">Samala et al.&nbsp;2020</a>).</p>
</section>
<section id="undervaluing-data-work" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="undervaluing-data-work">Undervaluing data work</h2>
<p>Too often the arduous task of curating quality datasets has been neglected, undervalued, and not given the same currency for career advancement as algorithmic work (<a href="https://dl.acm.org/doi/10.1145/3351095.3372829">Jo and Gebru 2020</a>). A research paper which interviewed over 60 machine learning practitioners was titled “Everyone wants to do the model work, not the data work”, drawing on a representative quote from one of the interviewees. The researchers found that data work was systematically devalued, leading to issues which impacted model performance, sometimes with disastrous consequences (<a href="https://research.google/pubs/everyone-wants-to-do-the-model-work-not-the-data-work-data-cascades-in-high-stakes-ai/">Sambasivan et al.&nbsp;2021</a>)).</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-09-10-gaps-risks-science/sambasivan-square.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:75.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Physical world brittleness, inadequate domain expertise, and other factors can have compounding negative impacts on the process of building AI models. Figure 1 from Sambasivan, et al, 2021</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Many areas within science lack consistent benchmark datasets. This can result in models that are not consistently reproducible and makes it tough to compare performance across different papers. Organizers of the largest academic AI conference, Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS), recognized that there were too few incentives for researchers to work on datasets and benchmarks. In 2021, they opened a new track of the conference, on equal standing with the original track, to better support and incentivize research on datasets and benchmarks (<a href="https://blog.neurips.cc/2021/04/07/announcing-the-neurips-2021-datasets-and-benchmarks-track/">Vanschoren and Yeung 2021</a>). This is an encouraging model, and I hope to see more efforts to prioritize data curation.</p>
</section>
<section id="opportunities-for-ai-in-science" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="opportunities-for-ai-in-science">Opportunities for AI in Science</h2>
<p>The flip side of these risks and gaps is that they offer opportunities for how we can work to improve the application of AI to science and to aim to avoid potential pitfalls. To ensure that we are making the most of AI possibilities in the life sciences, it would be a good idea to:</p>
<ul>
<li>Embed scientists and AI practitioners on closely integrated teams</li>
<li>Survey the biggest open problems in immunology and determine whether AI could help, and if so, what data is needed (as opposed to always just starting with the data we already have)</li>
<li>Reward dataset collection, through conference tracks and journal issues focused on it, similar to the model adopted by NeurIPS</li>
<li>Invest in research that is:
<ul>
<li>Focused on underlying causal mechanisms</li>
<li>Values multiple ways of generating knowledge</li>
<li>Gathering new types of data</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Develop benchmark datasets and structured competitions where relevant</li>
</ul>
<p>By keeping a broader perspective on different types of expertise, different methods of research, and the need for interdisciplinary work, we can prevent a myopic application of AI to science that risks neglecting important questions.</p>
<p><em>Thank you to Jeremy Howard for feedback on earlier drafts of this post.</em></p>
<p>You can subscribe to be notified of new blog posts by submitting your email below:</p>
<script type="text/javascript" src="https://campaigns.zoho.com.au/js/zc.iframe.js"></script>
<iframe scrolling="no" frameborder="0" id="iframewin" width="100%" height="100%" src="https://zcmp-pd.maillist-manage.com.au/ua/Optin?od=11d0c075b7ed49&amp;zx=11a17553b1&amp;tD=156971d471c7b09&amp;sD=156971d471c7cb3">
</iframe>


</section>

<p><br><br><i>I look forward to reading your responses. Create a free GitHub account to comment below.</i></p> ]]></description>
  <category>ethics</category>
  <category>machine learning</category>
  <category>science</category>
  <guid>https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-09-10-gaps-risks-science/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 09 Sep 2024 14:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-09-10-gaps-risks-science/liquid-drops.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Your Immune System is Not a Muscle</title>
  <dc:creator>Rachel Thomas</dc:creator>
  <link>https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-08-13-crowds-vs-friends/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="that-which-doesnt-kill-you" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="that-which-doesnt-kill-you">That which doesn’t kill you…</h2>
<p>Some people compare the immune system to a muscle, suggesting that the more you use it, the stronger it gets. Who doesn’t love an analogy? But is this one accurate?</p>
<p>We can see that not all obstacles make you stronger. Destroy the cartilage in your knee, and it may never fully recover, since cartilage doesn’t grow back. Some bacterial infections can permanently scar the lining of the brain and leave <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC5570486/">survivors with lower IQs</a>. More and more evidence is linking viruses to a range of diseases including <a href="https://theconversation.com/link-between-epstein-barr-virus-and-multiple-sclerosis-is-a-crucial-discovery-for-people-living-with-ms-175908">multiple sclerosis</a>, <a href="https://theconversation.com/my-work-investigating-the-links-between-viruses-and-alzheimers-disease-was-dismissed-for-years-but-now-the-evidence-is-building-184201">Alzheimer’s disease</a>, <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/36669485/">dementia</a>, <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41591-019-0667-0">type 1 diabetes</a>, and certain types of <a href="https://www.mdanderson.org/publications/focused-on-health/7-viruses-that-cause-cancer.h17-1592202.html">cancer</a>. When does illness make you stronger, and when does it cause permanent harm or leave you with chronic health conditions?</p>
<p>Our immune systems are amazing, and amazingly complex. Certain cells, called memory B cells and memory T cells, are able to “remember” invaders that they have seen before. They can rearrange their genes to create billions of possible memories and to respond more quickly to a future infection with the same pathogen. Is this an example of infection making you stronger? It depends. You can only catch the measles virus once, because you will form memory cells for it. But <a href="https://asm.org/articles/2019/may/measles-and-immune-amnesia">measles also destroys your pre-existing memory cells</a>, meaning that you can now re-catch a bunch of other illnesses that you had already built immunity to. Also, a very small percentage of people (unvaccinated babies may have more risk) will seem to fully recover from measles, and then 6 to 15 years later develop <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK560673/">brain inflammation that often leads to death</a>.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-08-13-crowds-vs-friends/virus-headlines.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:75.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Viruses have been linked to multiple sclerosis, Alzheimer’s, strokes, and other diseases</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Chickenpox is another disease that people typically only have once. However, the virus does not fully go away, but rather lies latent in the nervous system and can reactivate as shingles decades later. When the virus reactivates as shingles, it also leads to the <a href="https://theconversation.com/chickenpox-and-shingles-virus-lying-dormant-in-your-neurons-can-reactivate-and-increase-your-risk-of-stroke-new-research-identified-a-potential-culprit-194627">formation of blood clots</a> that raise the risk of stroke for months afterwards. So while you have “immunity” against getting chickenpox again, it has come with <a href="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2023-03-07-viruses1/">long-term risk</a>. While chickenpox and measles are examples of viruses, bacteria can also lie latent for a long time after an infection. For instance, the bacteria types that cause epidemic typhus, brucellosis, and tuberculosis can all activate/reactivate long after initial infection.</p>
<p>Another informative example is Dengue virus, a <a href="https://theconversation.com/dengue-why-is-this-sometimes-fatal-disease-increasing-around-the-world-215008">potentially fatal mosquito-borne disease</a> that affects millions of people annually. It has 4 different, but related types. This is a problem, because the memory your immune system forms to a given type will actually harm you if you get <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC10062565/">infected with a different type later</a>. As a result, a person’s second dengue infection is more severe than their first. Having no memory of dengue is better than remembering the wrong version!</p>
<p>There is a lot of confusion on germs and illness. It is good to play in the dirt and to be exposed to microbes, but you should also wash your hands after using the toilet and avoid raw sewage. When is hygiene good and when is it bad? Recently, a recurring question in newspaper articles and parents groups is whether it was harmful to children’s immune systems that they stayed home in 2020 and caught fewer illnesses. Is there a correct amount or type of “training” that the immune system needs? To explore these questions, we first need to inspect a widely misunderstood idea, often referred to as the <em>Hygiene Hypothesis</em>.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-hygiene-hypothesis" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-hygiene-hypothesis">The Hygiene Hypothesis</h2>
<p><em>Allergies</em> are a misfiring of the immune system– when it attacks what should be harmless environmental substances, such as pollen or dust. <em>Autoimmunity</em> is a different type of misfiring of the immune system– when it attacks our own cells, whether those are your neurons (multiple sclerosis), your joints (arthritis), your thyroid (Hashimoto’s disease), or your insulin-producing cells (type 1 diabetes). Both allergies and <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC9918670/">autoimmune diseases</a> have risen dramatically in recent decades.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-08-13-crowds-vs-friends/miller-autoimmune.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:65.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">A drastic rise in autoimmune disease: All the diseases listed on this graph are autoimmune diseases (Miller, 2022).</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>First proposed in 1989, the Hygiene Hypothesis offers an explanation for this dramatic rise. Certain types of microbes can help <em>modulate</em> our immune systems. By creating a low level of immune activity, they prevent our immune systems from getting bored and confused, which could lead them to attack the wrong target. <strong>Four main categories of pathogens that humans deal with are viruses, bacteria, fungi, and parasites.</strong> The evidence for pathogens that may be beneficial to the immune system is almost entirely for <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4396177/">parasitic worms and friendly (commensal) bacteria</a>. In contrast, many viruses can even trigger the onset of autoimmune diseases or allergies.</p>
<p>The reason for this makes sense: humans co-evolved with parasites and commensal bacteria, going back to when people lived in small hunter-gatherer tribes. For <a href="https://www.google.com.au/books/edition/The_Cambridge_Encyclopedia_of_Hunters_an/5eEASHGLg3MC?hl=en&amp;gbpv=1&amp;dq=The+Cambridge+Encyclopedia+of+Hunters+%26+Gatherers&amp;printsec=frontcover">over 90% of human history</a>, we lived as hunter-gatherers, and were exposed to very different types of microbes than we are now in crowded cities or poorly ventilated office buildings. Researchers have pointed out that the moniker Hygiene Hypothesis is misleading, and have proposed a more accurate alternative. <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4089149/">The “Old Friends” mechanism</a> describes which microbes we co-evolved with for 300,000 years.</p>
</section>
<section id="our-old-friends" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="our-old-friends">Our old friends</h2>
<p>Our bodies are full of <a href="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-04-25-microbiome-1/">peaceful (commensal) bacteria</a>, which can help synthesize vitamins we need, regulate dopamine, and even protect us from infection. Most famously our guts, but also the skin, throat, and bladder, all have distinct microbiomes. Disruption due to antibiotic use, Western diets, and cesarean births has changed our microbiomes, contributing to the rise of autoimmunity and allergies. Not all bacteria are the same– the positive microbes transmitted in a vaginal birth are quite different from harmful bacteria like anthrax or tuberculosis.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-08-13-crowds-vs-friends/parasites-square.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:50.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Our “old friends” parasitic worms may seem gross, but crowd infections can be even grosser</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Surprisingly, there are a number of studies showing that <a href="https://elifesciences.org/articles/65180">infections with helminths (parasitic worms)</a> can be <strong>beneficial</strong> in treating allergies and autoimmune disease, including for <a href="https://sci-hub.se/https://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007/7854_2014_361">multiple sclerosis</a>. A proposed mechanism is that parasites provide a low-level of background activation for the immune system, which prevents excess activation. This in turn can prevent inflammatory and autoimmune disorders. However, helminth infections can also be harmful and are not something you should try at home! Researchers are developing therapies based on <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4374592/">proteins derived from helminths</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="crowd-infections-are-new-in-human-history" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="crowd-infections-are-new-in-human-history">“Crowd infections” are new in human history</h2>
<p>Our “old friends” are organisms we co-evolved with for &gt; 50,000 years. By evolving together, our bodies learned to take advantage of these organisms. <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4089149/">Old friends can be contrasted with “crowd infections”</a> which only developed much more recently, since 10,000 BCE, after people began to live in more densely populated townships.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-08-13-crowds-vs-friends/busiest-flights-2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:75.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Our immune systems did not evolve for this!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>A crowd infection is one that would not last in sparsely distributed, small hunter-gatherer groups, because it either kills people, or offers enough immunity until the small tribe has been infected and there is nowhere else to spread. For instance, if a small tribe of hunter-gatherers caught a strain of influenza, the virus would die out once they had all caught it in short order, with no more hosts to spread to. The ability to circulate through megacities or crisscross the globe through international travel in our current world offers influenza far more opportunities to infect and time to mutate. It is able to continue infecting and reinfecting, decade after decade. Even viruses that don’t mutate much, such as measles, are able to continue infecting, due to dense populations and an ongoing supply of new people being born.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-08-13-crowds-vs-friends/old-friends.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:70.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Not all infections are the same! Figure from Rook, et al, 2014</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Homo Sapiens first evolved some 300,000 years ago, yet crowd infections are believed to have only developed in the last 12,000 years, a small blip in human history. Humans living in dense cities is a relatively recent development. An even more recent development is that of sealed indoor spaces and frequent international air travel. Many crowd infections, such as measles, mumps, chickenpox, colds, and flu, are airborne, spreading when humans talk and breathe in close contact, with poor ventilation. These infections could not widely spread until the last few hundred years of human history.</p>
<p>When I began studying immunology, something that surprised me is how much of the immune system is focused on fighting parasites. There is an entire branch, including several cell types, devoted to this. It seems like such a mismatch to the modern, industrialized world. <em>“Can I have a few more immune cell types focused on viruses or intracellular bacteria?”</em> I thought, <em>“in exchange for some of these parasite-focused cells that I’m not using??”</em> Our “old friends” are quite different from the crowd infections that plague us now– it would be bizarre to assume that research based on one of these categories will apply to the other!</p>
</section>
<section id="old-friends-hypothesis-is-more-descriptive-than-the-hygiene-hypothesis" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="old-friends-hypothesis-is-more-descriptive-than-the-hygiene-hypothesis">Old Friends Hypothesis is more descriptive than the Hygiene Hypothesis</h2>
<p>Our “old friends” parasitic worms and beneficial microbes are associated with a reduced risk of allergies and autoimmune diseases. No such relationship exists for crowd diseases. In fact, the opposite is true. Crowd diseases contribute to <a href="https://erj.ersjournals.com/content/19/2/341">allergies</a> and <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC10051805/">autoimmune diseases</a>. Comparing the immune system to a muscle that gets stronger with use is overly simplistic and, in many cases, inaccurate. There is huge variety in how various pathogens impact us. Being precise in considering different types of microbes and infections will allow us to better understand human health.</p>
</section>
<section id="related-reading" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="related-reading">Related reading:</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://elifesciences.org/articles/65180">Gross ways to live long: Parasitic worms as an anti-inflammaging therapy?</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4089149/">Microbial ‘old friends’, immunoregulation and socioeconomic status</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4396177/">Unraveling the Hygiene Hypothesis of helminthes and autoimmunity</a></li>
<li><a href="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-04-25-microbiome-1/">Surprises of the Microbiome</a></li>
<li><a href="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2023-03-22-viruses2/">Viruses: The Silent Triggers of Autoimmune and Neurodegenerative Diseases</a></li>
</ul>


</section>

<p><br><br><i>I look forward to reading your responses. Create a free GitHub account to comment below.</i></p> ]]></description>
  <category>science</category>
  <guid>https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-08-13-crowds-vs-friends/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 12 Aug 2024 14:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-08-13-crowds-vs-friends/flights.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>AI’s Quest to Predict T Cell Binding– The Holy Grail of Immunology</title>
  <dc:creator>Rachel Thomas</dc:creator>
  <link>https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-08-01-ai-t-cells/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><em>This post is part 3 in a series on using AI to predict T cell binding. Here are <a href="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-07-09-t-cells/">part 1</a> and <a href="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-07-24-neural-nets/">part 2</a>.</em></p>
<p>Better understanding what T cells bind to is a crucial question; some researchers even call it <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41577-023-00835-3">“a holy grail of systems immunology”</a>. While AI is already being used towards solutions, there is still much work to be done in this area!</p>
<p>In <a href="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-07-09-t-cells/">part 1 of this series</a>, we discussed the importance of determining what a T cell, that multi-purpose hero of the adaptive immune system, can bind to. New research papers on this topic are published each month. Almost all of them use neural networks, and in <a href="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-07-24-neural-nets/">part 2</a>, we discussed different types of neural networks. Now we will see how different types of neural networks are being applied to T cell binding.</p>
<section id="when-t-cell-binding-makes-a-big-difference" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="when-t-cell-binding-makes-a-big-difference">When T Cell Binding Makes a Big Difference</h2>
<p>T cells play a role in <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6BYocBxOfsU&amp;list=PLtmWHNX-gukLirebdPH8lla41SS78kjLD&amp;index=1&amp;t=172s">autoimmune diseases like Type 1 diabetes</a> (where T cells mistakenly destroy insulin-producing cells in the pancreas) and psoriasis (where T cells attack our own skin). T cells are also crucial to a healthy response to cancer. In cancer, something has gone amiss: cells undergo uncontrolled growth. T cells should put a stop to this, but in many cases T cells have been misleadingly soothed into exhaustion.</p>
<p>An increasing number of cancer therapies are based on T cells, and predicting which T cells are the most promising cancer-fighting candidates is crucial. When all is in harmony, our T cells should keep cancer from starting in the first place by quickly identifying and killing any cells which have gone rogue. T cells do this by recognizing small pieces of protein, called peptides, held out to them on special molecules called MHC. If those proteins are the sign of a good cell gone bad, the T cell can destroy the miscreant cell.</p>
<p>We can help the immune system by hanging up WANTED posters with the faces of outlaw proteins on them. This can let the immune system know who to look out for.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-08-01-ai-t-cells/wanted.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:65.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">WANTED poster for Cancer/testis antigen family 45 member A1</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>In practice, this is done by pairing a cancer peptide (called a “neoantigen”) together with a danger signal, and injecting them into a patient in order to sound the alarm and spur T cells into action. We need to identify which rogue cancer proteins are the most promising candidates for such a therapy. Neural networks are being used for this task!</p>
<p>One key question is <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/29403468/">which peptides are the best</a> candidates to use in these therapies. A key criteria is that T cells need to be able to recognize the peptide, which means that MHC molecules need to be able to bind to it. Everyone has different T cells and MHC molecules, since these are created by the most diverse genes in the human genome! The answer must be <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s42256-020-00260-4">personalized</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="applying-neural-networks" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="applying-neural-networks">Applying Neural Networks</h2>
<p>This seems like a question where neural networks could be helpful. In <a href="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-07-24-neural-nets/">part 2</a>, we discussed several different architectures (sequences of math operations) that we could choose between. One consideration is whether the input to a problem is fixed length or variable length. Are we identifying pictures of dogs, or reading Anna Karenina? The problem of T cell binding can be (and is!) framed both ways, depending on the team and the approach they choose to take. In general, sequences of amino acids can have a huge variety of lengths. However, T cell receptors and the peptides held out by MHC have lengths within a narrow range. As a result, we could use neural net architectures that have developed for fixed length problems. Or we could take advantage of the engineering and large training sets that already went into creating neural networks for variable length proteins. Strong research is being published of both types, and I am curious to see if there will be a consensus 5 years from now on the best approach.</p>
</section>
<section id="to-use-alphafold-or-not" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="to-use-alphafold-or-not">To Use AlphaFold or Not?</h2>
<p>As discussed in <a href="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-07-09-t-cells/">part 1</a>, the computer program <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=pB0RxG1NdtA&amp;list=PLtmWHNX-gukLirebdPH8lla41SS78kjLD&amp;index=2">AlphaFold</a> made headlines in 2020 for its incredible accuracy in taking a 1D sequence of amino acids as input and producing a 3D protein structure as output. It won an international competition for this task by a huge margin, smashing all previous records. Since T cell receptors (TCRs), MHC molecules, and peptides are all proteins, it makes sense that we could modify it for the T cell problem.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-08-01-ai-t-cells/insulin-2ways.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:80.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Two different ways of representing the protein insulin: a string of letters, or its 3D structure</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>AlphaFold (and similar models, such as RosettaFold and ESMFold) are excellent at what they do, which is to take a sequence of amino acids and predict the 3D structure of a protein. However, it is possible that these models are simultaneously both overkill and underkill for our T cell question. AlphaFold can handle much longer amino acid sequences than are found in the T cell binding problem, yet it doesn’t account for T cells having not just one, but a <a href="https://elifesciences.org/articles/82813">pair of TWO sequences</a> of amino acids (known as the alpha and beta chains). AlphaFold was trained on a massive data set, yet that dataset did not include much in the way of T cell or MHC specific data. Some researchers have chosen to modify AlphaFold, adding additional layers for prediction, or fine-tuning on a more relevant dataset, whereas other teams have chosen to design neural networks that are more directly suited to the task at hand.</p>
<p>Which approach is better? It’s tough to tell. Reading papers within the field can be confusing, as many boast of great results. Since there is an absence of consistent benchmarks and models are often not evaluated for accuracy on new peptides, it can be tough to compare different models.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-need-for-a-grand-challenge" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-need-for-a-grand-challenge">The Need for a Grand Challenge</h2>
<p>You may wonder why we can’t clearly see which neural network for T cell binding is definitively the best. The ImageNet competition produced a clear winner for recognizing objects in images in 2012: AlexNet, a neural net that was head and shoulders better than the other entries. Similarly, AlphaFold dominated the CASP competition in 2020. However, several factors are necessary to create competitions such as ImageNet or CASP, and these factors do not yet exist for the T cell problem.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-08-01-ai-t-cells/lasker-statues2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:60.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">AlphaFold won the 2023 Lasker Award, “America’s Nobel Prize”. The trophies are based on The Winged Victory of Samothrace statue.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>You need a large, well-curated, and representative dataset. This can fail in numerous ways. While data is central to any machine learning project, all too often, data work has been undervalued and neglected. The paper <a href="https://research.google/pubs/everyone-wants-to-do-the-model-work-not-the-data-work-data-cascades-in-high-stakes-ai/">“Everyone wants to do the model work, not the data work”</a> drew on interviews with 53 machine learning practitioners across multiple countries. Building fancy math models is rewarded with career advancement, not the arduous labor of collecting and curating the underlying datasets that make those models possible. In many cases, those tasked with collecting data had it piled on top of already demanding jobs, with inadequate communication, training, or compensation. This led to erroneous measurements, miscommunications, and failed projects. To give one example, when machines in a robotic medical AI project were recalibrated, the change was not documented, leading to inconsistent data that was impossible to interpret.</p>
<p>Data work is particularly challenging in the area of T cell receptors (TCRs). Current datasets cover just a <a href="https://elifesciences.org/articles/82813">tiny fraction</a> of all possible TCRs. It is difficult to scale experimental methods, so less than 1 million unique TCR-peptide pairs have been found experimentally. Of the data that exists, the vast majority just contains one of the two amino acid sequences which make up a TCR, even though both sequences are significant.</p>
<p>You also need everyone to agree on what numerical metrics to use in evaluating success, and for those metrics to closely correspond to the value you care about. Great harm can result <a href="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2019-09-24-metrics/">when those metrics are a poor proxy</a> for the underlying goal. Providing a meaningful numeric score and declaring a winner require the right setup and a lot of effort behind the scenes.</p>
<p>Some researchers have called for a <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41577-023-00835-3">“grand challenge”</a> of inferring T cell receptor binding, similar to the grand challenge in prediction protein folding which led to AlphaFold. Standardizing datasets and setting clear metrics for comparisons could motivate innovation. This is a high-impact area within immunology and medicine and I hope that it is a continued focus of research!</p>
<p><em>This post is part 3 in a series on using AI to predict T cell binding. Here are <a href="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-07-09-t-cells/">part 1</a> and <a href="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-07-24-neural-nets/">part 2</a>.</em></p>
<p><em>Thank you to Jeremy Howard for feedback on an earlier draft of this post.</em></p>
<p>You can subscribe to be notified of new blog posts by submitting your email below:</p>
<script type="text/javascript" src="https://campaigns.zoho.com.au/js/zc.iframe.js"></script>
<iframe scrolling="no" frameborder="0" id="iframewin" width="100%" height="100%" src="https://zcmp-pd.maillist-manage.com.au/ua/Optin?od=11d0c075b7ed49&amp;zx=11a17553b1&amp;tD=156971d471c7b09&amp;sD=156971d471c7cb3">
</iframe>


</section>

<p><br><br><i>I look forward to reading your responses. Create a free GitHub account to comment below.</i></p> ]]></description>
  <category>machine learning</category>
  <category>science</category>
  <guid>https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-08-01-ai-t-cells/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 31 Jul 2024 14:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-08-01-ai-t-cells/wanted-rectangle2.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Most Common and Useful Neural Nets</title>
  <dc:creator>Rachel Thomas</dc:creator>
  <link>https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-07-24-neural-nets/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><em>This post can stand alone as a friendly introduction to neural nets, no background required. It is part 2 in my series on using AI to figure out what T cells can bind to. Here are <a href="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-07-09-t-cells/">part 1</a> and <a href="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-08-01-ai-t-cells/">part 3</a>.</em></p>
<section id="what-are-neural-networks" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-are-neural-networks">What are Neural Networks?</h2>
<p>Neural networks are a type of machine learning algorithm that are currently in the limelight, powering chatbots like ChatGPT and image generators like Midjourney. Neural networks are just math equations, written in computer code. When people hear the terms “neural networks” or “artificial intelligence,” they may picture humanoid robots, but it is more accurate to imagine a scaled-up version of 10th grade math class.</p>
<p>When considering an AI system, two major categories of tasks are:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Classifying things</strong>: These are not predictions in the sense of predicting the future, but rather, guessing the answer to a question. Is this a picture of a chihuahua or a blueberry muffin? Which of these potential drugs would be most likely to target antibiotic resistant bacteria?</li>
<li><strong>Generating things</strong>: Create a picture of <a href="https://medium.com/hackernoon/non-artistic-style-transfer-or-how-to-draw-kanye-using-captain-picards-face-c4a50256b814">Kanye West made out of tiny Captain Picard faces</a>. Generate a new molecule that may work as an antibiotic.</li>
</ul>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-07-24-neural-nets/chihuahua-kanye.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:65.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Classification: muffin or chihuahua? (pic from Karen Zack, <span class="citation" data-cites="teenybiscuit">@teenybiscuit</span>, 2016) // Generation: Kanye out of Picard faces (pic from fast.ai intern Brad Kenstler, 2017)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Some problems in medicine and immunology can be framed either as a classification problem OR as a generative problem. For instance, suppose your goal is to produce a <a href="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-04-03-ai-antibiotics/">new antibiotic to address antimicrobial resistance</a>. Some scientists are trying to classify which compounds, out of hundreds of millions of existing ones, may have the desired properties, whereas others are trying to generate new compounds. Both approaches are useful.</p>
</section>
<section id="language-models" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="language-models">Language Models</h2>
<p>You may have heard the term “language model” describing chatbots (such as Chat-GPT or Claude) and automated language translation (such as Google Translate and Skype Translator). One approach to developing sophisticated language capabilities is to write a computer program that predicts the next word in a sentence. Predict the next word and then the next, and you can generate strings of text. This is a language model. Both prediction and generation are used to build language models.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-07-24-neural-nets/google-translate.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:65.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Google Translate relies on language models. The gender bias shown here has since been corrected, although bias remains an issue.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Along the way, the model has learned a number of patterns regarding context, vocabulary, and relationships. Fine tuning lets us use these capabilities for specific problems. For instance, a <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC10338337/">language model trained on medical chart notes</a> was used to make predictions about which patients were most likely to be readmitted to the hospital. While the model was trained on a prediction task (predicting the next word in a sentence), it can now be used for generation as well when combined with some additional techniques when it is given additional instructions and training from humans.</p>
<p>When language models are trained, they are not always just tasked with predicting the next word. In a sentence, sometimes random words are covered up, and the computer must predict what goes in that spot. It is a fill-in-the-blank assignment.</p>
<p>Through predicting words, the model can learn which other words to focus on. Suppose I told you, “I am so tired that I can barely keep my XXXX open”. You could likely guess that the missing word is “eyes”. To do so, you may have focused on “tired” and “open”. Some of the word positions add little, if anything, to your efforts of deduction. In a similar way, attention-based neural networks learn what to pay attention to, where to focus.</p>
<p>Like the sequence of words in a novel, a sequence of amino acids is its own language, telling the story of a protein. The same techniques and approaches that were developed for natural languages (such as translating between English and French) can also be applied to the biological language of protein creation.</p>
</section>
<section id="popular-architectures" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="popular-architectures">Popular architectures</h2>
<p>Neural networks are often created from a few popular architectures, which are particular combinations of mathematical operations. Something that can be confusing is that different architectures can often be combined with one another. Also, most of these architectures can be used for both predictive and generative problems. Here are a few particularly popular ones:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Multi-Layer Perceptrons (MLPs)</strong>: the oldest example of a neural network was developed in the 1960s! It is the basis of many systems used today (<a href="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/mdp.39015039846566?urlappend=%3Bseq=13">Rosenblatt 1962</a>).</li>
<li><strong>Convolutional Neural Networks (CNNs)</strong>: are like a filter that you scan across a picture, inch by inch, to recognize what is in it. This is useful for programs such as those bird-watcher apps that will tell you what type of bird you spotted, based on the photo you upload (<a href="https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/726791">Lecun et al.&nbsp;1998</a>; <a href="https://papers.nips.cc/paper_files/paper/2012/hash/c399862d3b9d6b76c8436e924a68c45b-Abstract.html">Krizhevsky et al.&nbsp;2012</a>).</li>
<li><strong>Recursive Neural Networks (RNNs)</strong>: can take variable-length input (that is, sequences) and store state. Google began using these for translating between languages in 2016 (<a href="https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/abstract/document/6795963">Hochreiter and Schmidhuber 1997</a>; <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1609.08144">Wu et al.&nbsp;2016</a>).</li>
<li><strong>Transformers</strong>: offer a more efficient approach for sequences, which can be any length. These are based on <strong>attention</strong>, as explained above. These have now replaced RNNs in many applications, including Google Translate, which lets a user enter a word or phrase, or even entire paragraphs, and get back the response in another language (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1706.03762">Vaswani et al.&nbsp;2017</a>).</li>
<li><strong>Graph Neural Network (GNNs)</strong>: Allow for geometric relationships in the input to be captured. For example, GNNs can help represent the spatial relationships between different amino acids in a sequence. Principles of GNNs are typically combined with other options in the list above (<a href="https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/4700287">Scarselli et al.&nbsp;2009</a>; <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/19193509/">Micheli 2009</a>).</li>
</ul>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-07-24-neural-nets/convolution2.gif" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:65.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">How a convolution works, from deeplearning.net, 2018</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>How do you choose a neural network for your problem? One key consideration is how much the size of your input varies. Suppose you have a collection of photos and are trying to determine which are of cats and which are of dogs. Your photos are likely of similar sizes, and you can make them the same by adding a frame around the smaller ones. Whole families of neural networks have been developed for such problems with fixed-size input.</p>
<p>Now suppose you are developing a neural network that can read books and predict which word will come next. The difference in length between The Hungry Hungry Caterpillar and Les Miserables is huge. For this problem, we need a network that allows variable-size input. RNNs and Transformers allow variable-length input, whereas CNNs take fixed-size input.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-innovation-of-alphafold" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-innovation-of-alphafold">The Innovation of AlphaFold</h2>
<p>Recall from <a href="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-07-09-t-cells/">Part 1 of this series</a> that the computer program AlphaFold revolutionized the task of taking a 1D sequence of amino acids (shown on the left), and transforming it into a 3D molecule (shown on the right).</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-07-24-neural-nets/insulin-2ways.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:80.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Two different ways of representing the protein insulin: a string of letters, or its 3D structure</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The text of a book is 1-dimensional. It could be written on a single long ribbon, stretched out, and read as such. However, best making sense of amino acid sequences requires an additional dimension. We want to know not just the long ribbon of a single sequence, but the evolutionary relationships of related sequences it is similar to.</p>
<p>A crucial innovation of <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-021-03819-2">AlphaFold</a> is that it expanded attention to 2 dimensions. The 2 dimensions are the sequence of the amino acids, as well as a block of sequences of similar sequences. These similar sequences provide important evolutionary clues of what our protein of interest may be like. Like distant cousins in a family tree, they can give us insights of what may be some common features. This set of related sequences is known as a Multiple Sequence Alignment (MSA) and is a key component in bioinformatics. AlphaFold applies attention to the MSA, learning which parts of related sequences to focus on in trying to decode a protein structure.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-07-24-neural-nets/alphafold-2reps.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:65.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">AlphaFold represents sequences 2 ways. The MSA representation requires 2D attention. Image from Jumper, et al, 2021</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Returning to our list of popular architectures, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=pB0RxG1NdtA&amp;t=2s">AlphaFold</a> combines aspects of Transformers (in a new form, named the Evoformer, which has 2D attention) and Graph Neural Networks (to represent the spatial relationships between amino acids). Now that we have covered some of the types of neural networks and the structure of AlphaFold, we are ready to combine this with the information about T cells from <a href="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-07-09-t-cells/">part 1</a>. <strong>Check out <a href="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-08-01-ai-t-cells/">part 3</a> to see how AI is being used to predict T cell binding.</strong></p>
<p>And for understanding the ethical risks of AI systems, you may be interested in reading my previous posts:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-02-20-ai-medicine/">“AI will cure cancer” misunderstands both AI and medicine</a></li>
<li><a href="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2023-05-16-ai-centralizes-power/">AI and Power: The Ethical Challenges of Automation, Centralization, and Scale</a></li>
<li><a href="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2021-08-17-eleven-ethics-videos/">11 Short Videos About AI Ethics</a></li>
</ul>
<p><em>Thank you to Jeremy Howard for feedback on earlier drafts of this post.</em></p>
<p>You can subscribe to be notified of new blog posts by submitting your email below:</p>
<script type="text/javascript" src="https://campaigns.zoho.com.au/js/zc.iframe.js"></script>
<iframe scrolling="no" frameborder="0" id="iframewin" width="100%" height="100%" src="https://zcmp-pd.maillist-manage.com.au/ua/Optin?od=11d0c075b7ed49&amp;zx=11a17553b1&amp;tD=156971d471c7b09&amp;sD=156971d471c7cb3">
</iframe>


</section>

<p><br><br><i>I look forward to reading your responses. Create a free GitHub account to comment below.</i></p> ]]></description>
  <category>machine learning</category>
  <category>science</category>
  <guid>https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-07-24-neural-nets/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 23 Jul 2024 14:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-07-24-neural-nets/chihuahua-kanye.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Decoding T cells with AI</title>
  <dc:creator>Rachel Thomas</dc:creator>
  <link>https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-07-09-t-cells/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><em>I’m studying the intersection of AI and immunology, two notoriously jargon-heavy fields – but it’s important that scientists share their work with a broader audience. This 3-part series is an experiment: an accessible introduction to AI immunology concepts. This post is part 1 in a series on using AI to predict T cell binding. Here are <a href="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-07-24-neural-nets/">part 2</a> and <a href="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-08-01-ai-t-cells/">part 3</a>.</em></p>
<p>T cells are one of the most important cell types of our immune systems, assassinating cells that have been infected by viruses or turned cancerous, and sending commands to other immune cells to organize responses against invaders. T cells can help mobilize against a wide range of threats due to their incredible diversity. They are able to rearrange their genes to recognize billions of different types of infected or rogue cells.</p>
<p>Figuring out how to predict what a T cell will bind to (meaning what cells it can recognize as bad and coordinate attacks against) would be a vital medical breakthrough. Some cancer therapies are based on teaching T cells to better recognize tumor cells. Knowing the answer could help us design new drugs. And not knowing can have disastrous consequences. A <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3743463/">therapy was trialed</a> in which patients were injected with T cells that would kill cells displaying a protein that is commonly found in cancer, but is not displayed by healthy cells. Tragically, it turns out that these T cells can also bind to a different and unrelated protein found in heart muscles, and two patients died of cardiac arrest.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-07-09-t-cells/tcell-niaid.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:65.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">The surface of a T cell, image from a scanning electron micrograph, credit: NIAID, creative commons license</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>In this 3-part series, I will explore efforts to use AI to predict what T cells will bind to, and why it matters.</p>
<section id="t-cells-our-multi-purpose-immune-heroes" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="t-cells-our-multi-purpose-immune-heroes">T cells, our multi-purpose immune heroes</h2>
<p>At their best, T cells destroy viral-infected cells and stop cancer before we ever develop symptoms. When things go awry, T cells can accidentally attack our own cells – for instance Type 1 Diabetes occurs when T cells mistakenly destroy insulin-producing cells in the pancreas and psoriasis is caused by T cells attacking the skin (<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6BYocBxOfsU">check out this 5 minute video I made for more information about confused T cells</a>). Or “exhausted” T cells can sit idly by as tumors rapidly grow.</p>
<p>T cell receptors (TCRs) are protein complexes on the outside of a T cell. The way a T cell recognizes a problematic cell is by binding to a small piece of protein, called a peptide. T cells can bind only to peptides that are presented to them on fancy platters– err, I mean on special molecules called MHC molecules, found on the outside of cells. The binding of TCR-peptide-MHC is like a secret handshake. The TCR is very specific about which peptides it can bind to. Most combinations will not work.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-07-09-t-cells/t-cell-markers.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:65.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Does this pair know the same secret handshake? Sketch I made with my daughter’s markers</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Since TCRs are made of protein, and they bind to small pieces of protein, it is helpful to consider some related questions about proteins before we tackle TCR binding in more detail.</p>
</section>
<section id="proteins-workhorses-of-the-cell" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="proteins-workhorses-of-the-cell">Proteins: workhorses of the cell</h2>
<p>Proteins make life as we know it possible; they are <a href="https://www.newscientist.com/article/mg21128251-300-first-life-the-search-for-the-first-replicator/">responsible for the hard work</a> that goes on within our cells. <a href="https://www.nature.com/scitable/topicpage/protein-function-14123348/">Proteins give our cells</a> shape and structure, and help them stay organized. Most biochemical reactions occur thanks to enzymes, which are entirely made of proteins. And hormones are proteins that send messages around the body.</p>
<p>The 3D shape of a protein is crucial to understanding how it functions within the body and what roles it plays. However, the information we often receive about proteins is not 3D. It is a list of letters – a sequence of amino acids, the building blocks of proteins. These lists can twist and fold, creating spirals, sheets, and other interesting sculptures.</p>
<p>For example, insulin is an important protein messenger that lets our cells know when they should absorb more sugar. Insulin consists of this sequence of 110 amino acids (there are 20 distinct amino acids, and each has a letter representing it):</p>
<p><code>MALWMRLLPLLALLALWGPDPAAAFVNQHLCGSHLVEALYLVCGERGFFYTPKTRREAEDLQVGQVELGGGPGAGSLQPLALEGSLQKRGIVEQCCTSICSLYQLENYCN</code></p>
<p>However, to really understand insulin, we need to know what it <a href="https://alphafold.ebi.ac.uk/entry/P01308">looks like as a 3D molecule</a>. Its shape and structure helps determine which other molecules will interact with it.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-07-09-t-cells/insulin-3.gif" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:70.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Insulin lets our cells know to take in sugar from the blood. Animation from the AlphaFold Protein Structure Database.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The insulin receptor (which is on the surface of cells and can bind to insulin, receiving the message and sending off an internal signal within the cell) is also a protein. It is a sequence of over 1,000 amino acids and has a <a href="https://alphafold.ebi.ac.uk/entry/P06213">far more complicated structure</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="a-new-champion-alphafold" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-new-champion-alphafold">A new champion: AlphaFold</h2>
<p>This question of converting amino acid sequences (on the left) to 3D structures (on the right) has wide-reaching implications within biology and medicine.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-07-09-t-cells/insulin-2ways.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:80.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Two different ways of representing the protein insulin: a string of letters, or its 3D structure</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>In 1994, a competition was established for researchers to go head-to-head in trying to best answer this question. Leading up to the competition, as scientists discovered new protein structures, using laboratory techniques such as X-ray crystallography or NMR spectroscopy, they kept some of the results secret. Later, these structures would be freely shared with other scientists, but for now, they must be held apart for the challenge. The somewhat dry name, <a href="https://predictioncenter.org/">Critical Assessment of Structure Prediction (CASP)</a>, belies the importance of this task.</p>
<p>In the competition, each team submits their guesses, generated by computer programs they created. The distance between the guesses and the actual structures is measured in Angstroms, with 1 Angstrom being one just ten-billionth of a meter.</p>
<p>CASP did not make international headlines until 2020. This is when an entry, titled <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-021-03819-2">AlphaFold</a> smashed all existing records, and all competitors, by a wide margin. AlphaFold was created by DeepMind, an AI company owned by Google.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-07-09-t-cells/headlines-2021.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:65.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">AlphaFold was named the innovation of the year by both Science and Nature Methods magazines for 2021</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="challenges-with-t-cell-data" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="challenges-with-t-cell-data">Challenges with T cell data</h2>
<p>At first glance, it may seem like AlphaFold would give us a solution to our T cell problem. After all, T cell receptors are made of proteins, and they bind to other proteins. Aren’t protein structures a solved problem? Not so fast. The T cell receptor problem poses many different and additional challenges.</p>
<p>There are a few factors that make the question of what a T cell will bind to– known as <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41577-023-00835-3">T cell receptor specificity</a>– distinctive and more complicated than the problem AlphaFold solves. First of all, AlphaFold was created to predict protein structures from a single chain of amino acids. However, TCRs have 2 key chains of amino acids: alpha and beta. Both are important. These alpha and beta chains can be <a href="https://elifesciences.org/articles/82813">mixed and matched</a> willy-nilly.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-07-09-t-cells/hudson-1bc.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:70.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Here, MHC is represented in black &amp; grey and the TCR is represented in light &amp; dark turquoise. The peptide is in purple. Like a puzzle, we are interested in knowing which pieces fit together. Figure 1bc from Hudson, et al, 2023</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Another issue is that we have far less data on TCRs than we do on general proteins. The genes that code for the TCR vary greatly across the population. They are some of the most diverse genes in the entire human genome! This means that the (relatively small) dataset we do have is only a fraction of what exists. AlphaFold is based on machine learning, and machine learning models are highly dependent on the quality, quantity, and nature of the data used to train them.</p>
<p><em>This post is part 1 in a series on using AI to predict T cell binding. Here are <a href="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-07-24-neural-nets/">part 2</a> and <a href="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-08-01-ai-t-cells/">part 3</a>.</em></p>
<p><em>Thank you to Jeremy Howard for feedback on earlier drafts of this post.</em></p>
<p>You can subscribe to be notified of new blog posts by submitting your email below:</p>
<script type="text/javascript" src="https://campaigns.zoho.com.au/js/zc.iframe.js"></script>
<iframe scrolling="no" frameborder="0" id="iframewin" width="100%" height="100%" src="https://zcmp-pd.maillist-manage.com.au/ua/Optin?od=11d0c075b7ed49&amp;zx=11a17553b1&amp;tD=156971d471c7b09&amp;sD=156971d471c7cb3">
</iframe>


</section>

<p><br><br><i>I look forward to reading your responses. Create a free GitHub account to comment below.</i></p> ]]></description>
  <category>machine learning</category>
  <category>science</category>
  <guid>https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-07-09-t-cells/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jul 2024 14:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-07-09-t-cells/tcell-niaid-fingernail.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The microbiomes of wildfires, nanoplastics, and roller derby</title>
  <dc:creator>Rachel Thomas</dc:creator>
  <link>https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-05-07-microbiome-2/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>This is part 2 in a series covering surprising facts about the microbiome. Be sure to check out <a href="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-04-25-microbiome-1/">part 1 here</a>. A microbiome is the community of microorganisms found living together in a given habitat. The microbiome of the human gut can contribute to <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6BYocBxOfsU&amp;list=PLtmWHNX-gukLirebdPH8lla41SS78kjLD">development of autoimmune disease</a>. The microbiome of plant roots can include bacteria traveling on <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WpgAA1mh7Io">fungal super-highways</a>. Scientists also study the microbiome of nanoplastics floating in the ocean and the tiny microbes throughout our atmosphere that catalyze precipitation. Microbiomes influence food chains, weather patterns, and the human immune system.</p>
<section id="microbes-are-everywhere" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="microbes-are-everywhere">Microbes are everywhere</h2>
<p>When I lived in California there were several years in which we had widespread wildfire smoke that was harmful to breathe, polluted the air, and created an eerie yellow hue. I knew that smoke contains toxins, and I incorrectly assumed that it wouldn’t be a suitable habitat for anything living. Counter-intuitively, <a href="https://sci-hub.se/https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.abe8116">smoke is a good habitat for some microbes</a>, as the particulate matter helps block UV rays that might otherwise kill them. Water vapor produced by the combustion of biomass can help prevent microbes from drying out. And convective columns and updraft winds can draw in microbes from long distances.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-05-07-microbiome-2/wildfire-microbiome.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:70.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Microbes in wildfire smoke</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p><a href="https://www.thelancet.com/journals/lanplh/article/PIIS2542-5196(23)00046-3/fulltext">One study on the California wildfires</a> found that hospitalizations for coccidioidomycosis, a dangerous fungal infection, increased by 20% in the month following smoke exposure. This is a worrying threat given that the climate crisis has led to increasing frequency and intensity of wildfires. There is even a nascent field of <strong>pyroaerobiology</strong>, studying the aerosolization and transport of <a href="https://esajournals.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1002/ecs2.2507">microbes by wildfires</a>.</p>
<p>An estimated 5-13 million tons of plastic enter the oceans each year, including run-off from polluted rivers. Floating “islands” of plastic debris, including microplastics less than 5 mm in size, are found in the oceans. These plastics impact <a href="https://journals.asm.org/doi/10.1128/msystems.01112-20">over 700 different species of aquatic life</a>, ranging from microscopic phytoplankton to large whales. There are microbes that thrive on microplastics, <a href="https://esajournals.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1890/150017">forming the Plastisphere</a>. Unfortunately, this thin film of bacteria and fungi living on microplastics may make them more appealing to some sea animals, such as loggerhead turtles, to eat. Researchers have found that the Atlantic and Pacific oceans have distinct Plastisphere communities, and that these differences may necessitate different remediation approaches.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-05-07-microbiome-2/microplastics-chesapeake.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:70.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Microplastics from the Patapsco River, pictured at the laboratory of Dr.&nbsp;Lance Yonk, Photo by Will Parson/Chesapeake Bay Program</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Researchers are also investigating how microbes can be used to break down these dangerous plastics. One interesting research study collated data on <a href="https://journals.asm.org/doi/10.1128/msystems.01112-20">over 16,000 genes involved in plastic degradation</a>. These genes came from 6,000 microbial species, showing that there are numerous possibilities of potential microbes that may be used for bioremediation. Researchers have even found some microbes can be used <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-023-01697-4">to help break down PFAS</a>, often called “forever chemicals”, which are polluting aquatic environments. While it is very difficult to break down the fluorine-carbon bonds found in PFAS, microbes can instead first break chlorine-carbon bonds in the chemicals, which then makes it easier to remove the fluorine atoms.</p>
</section>
<section id="there-is-no-clear-good-vs.-bad-for-microbes" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="there-is-no-clear-good-vs.-bad-for-microbes">There is no clear “good” vs.&nbsp;“bad” for microbes</h2>
<p><em>Pseudomonas syringae</em> is a plant pathogen that is a scourge of agricultural crops. It infects almost all economically valuable species of crops and <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC5972017/">threatens global agriculture production</a>.</p>
<p>But actually it’s not all bad – this same species of bacteria is important to weather precipitation cycles. For temperatures above -40 degrees C, ice formation requires a catalyst, called an ice nucleator. Researchers have discovered that <a href="https://www.pnas.org/doi/full/10.1073/pnas.0809816105">most ice nucleators are biological</a>: tiny microbes that are widely dispersed throughout the atmosphere all over the world, even in Antarctica! And it turns out that <a href="https://www.activeremedy.org/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/brent-christner_2012_cloudy-with-a-chance-of-microbes.pdf"><em>Pseudomonas syringae</em> is a common nucleator for catalyzing precipitation</a>. This example highlights the complexity of microbial ecosystems. Efforts to protect plants from this pathogen must take into account the interrelated impact on precipitation.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-05-07-microbiome-2/p-syringae.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:70.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Left and center: Infected tomato plants and an infected leaf (images from Wikimedia). On the right: the life cycle of P. syringae, from the paper “Cloudy with a Chance of Microbes”</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Another example of a microbe that can’t be clearly classified as “good” or “bad” is <em>Prevotella Copri</em>, found in the human gut microbiome. An aptly titled paper, “The curious case of Prevotella copri” describes “puzzling discrepancies” in how various research studies have associated this species with a <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC10478744/">range of positive and negative impacts on disease</a>.</p>
<p>The authors share that high abundance of P. copri is associated with non-Western diets, rheumatoid arthritis, Ankylosing spondylitis (a type of inflammatory arthritis), Graves’ orbitopathy (autoimmune condition that can damage vision vision), diabetes mellitus, and cancer. This is particularly surprising, because several of the inflammatory and autoimmune conditions listed are more strongly associated with Western diets. Low abundance of P. copri is associated with Western diets, glucose intolerance, chronic hives, Parkinson’s disease, and food allergies.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-05-07-microbiome-2/p-copri.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:70.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">From the paper “The curious case of Prevotella copri”</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>It is unclear whether abundant <em>Prevotella copri</em> in the gut is good or bad. The paper notes that <em>P. copri</em> has a diverse set of strains, which differ from the reference strain, and may partly explain the discrepancies. The ways that gut microbes interact with each other, our immune systems, and our genetics can be quite complex, and these factors may mediate how P. copri influences a person’s health.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-social-microbiome" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-social-microbiome">The Social Microbiome</h2>
<p>We often talk about microbiomes at an individual level: the microbes inside the guts of a person (or insect) or the microbes on their skin or in their mouth. However, researchers also study the <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41559-020-1220-8"><strong>social microbiome</strong></a>: the metacommunity of all the microbiomes of animals in a social community. Members of a community can influence each other’s microbiomes through their social bonds.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-05-07-microbiome-2/roller-derby-fingernail.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:70.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Roller derby can change your skin’s microbiome, Image: Oklarsson, CC BY-SA 3.0, Wikimedia</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>One study sampled the <a href="https://peerj.com/articles/53/">skin microbiome of roller derby players</a> before and after games. The three teams in the study each came from a different city and state. They found that prior to a game, the microbiomes were more similar within a team, and different across teams. However, after competing in a game, which involves a fair amount of physical contact, all of the players’ skin microbiomes were more similar to one another.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-05-07-microbiome-2/roller-derby-fig1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:70.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Red, blue, and green represent the microbiomes of teams from San Jose, CA, Eugene, OR, and DC, respectively. There is much more overlap after games. Figure 1 from Meadow, et al, 2013</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Much of the research on the social microbiome has been done on nonhuman primates, where grooming, mating, feeding, and other close contact have been shown to impact the microbiome. Social networks and group membership were found to <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4379495/">determine the microbiomes of baboons</a>, and were more predictive than age or gender.</p>
<p>For some animals, microbiomes inside of scent glands are used to communicate group membership. Hyenas typically live in social clans of 40-80 individuals, and these clans are often overlapping in their territories. They secrete fermentative bacteria from their scent glands. This allows for group-specific odors, making it easier for the hyenas to communicate if they are in the same group as one another. <a href="">One study found</a> that the relative abundance of different types of bacteria was distinctive for different hyena clans.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-05-07-microbiome-2/spotted-hyenas.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:70.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">A group of hyenas may have a distinctive composition of microbes, giving them an identifying scent. Photo by Charles Peterson, CC BY-NC-ND 2.0</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="more-to-learn" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="more-to-learn">More to learn</h2>
<p>Understanding the microbiome is a crucial piece of better understanding the health of plants, humans, and other animals, as well as our environment. Microbes synthesize vitamins, catalyze precipitation, spread disease or protect from it, can remediate or exacerbate the impacts of pollution, and influence food chains. Only with relatively recent advances in genomic sequencing have we been able to better study and compare the balance of species composing different microbiomes. This is a fascinating and growing area of research.</p>


</section>

<p><br><br><i>I look forward to reading your responses. Create a free GitHub account to comment below.</i></p> ]]></description>
  <category>science</category>
  <guid>https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-05-07-microbiome-2/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 06 May 2024 14:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-05-07-microbiome-2/roller-derby-fingernail.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Surprises of the Microbiome</title>
  <dc:creator>Rachel Thomas</dc:creator>
  <link>https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-04-25-microbiome-1/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><em>This is part 1 in a series. You can <a href="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-05-07-microbiome-2/">read part 2 here</a>.</em></p>
<p>Humans <a href="https://microbiomejournal.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s40168-020-00875-0">co-evolved together</a> with our microbiomes, the bacteria and fungi that colonize our intestines, coat our skin, and inhabit our mouths, throats, and numerous other body locations. Microbiomes are significant because they influence how we process nutrients, fight pathogens, and what diseases we are susceptible to. This is not just true of humans, but plants and insects also have microbiomes that influence their metabolism and immune systems.</p>
<p>A microbiome is the community of microorganisms found living together in a given habitat– this does not just include living on a host. Scientists study the microbiomes of nanoplastics floating in the ocean, covered in bacteria and fungi, and of the tiny microbes throughout the atmosphere that catalyze precipitation. Even wildfire smoke has a microbiome. These environmental microbiomes influence food chains, weather patterns, and the spread of disease. We can’t fully understand the impacts of pollution and climate change without studying them.</p>
<p>Studying the microbiome is crucial for better understanding the health and disease of humans, other animals, plants, and our environment. In this 2-part series, I will cover a grab bag of surprising and fascinating facts about the microbiome.</p>
<section id="when-the-immune-system-attacks-friendly-bacteria" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="when-the-immune-system-attacks-friendly-bacteria">When the immune system attacks friendly bacteria…</h2>
<p>Commensal bacteria, often referred to as “friendly”, are bacteria that live on human skin or in the gut and help us. The human gut microbiome can help synthesize vitamins we need, regulate dopamine, and protect us from infection. However, so-called friendly bacteria can cause grave problems when they cross out of the gut into the bloodstream. Microbes can’t necessarily be classified as “good” or “bad”, and this impact of what happens when microbes cross from the gut to the blood is an example of this.</p>
<p>I created a short 5 minute video to explain these ideas, geared for a general audience:</p>
<center>
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/6BYocBxOfsU?si=aSkr2Zmp5HRGwg0Q" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen="">
</iframe>
</center>
<p>If “friendly” microbes stray into the bloodstream, our immune system may mount an attack against them by producing antibodies and activating T cells (the two primary approaches of our adaptive immune systems). The small regions on a bacteria recognized by T cells or antibodies are known as <strong>epitopes</strong>. All bacteria have many epitopes, and genetics helps determine which particular epitopes your immune system is able to recognize. Two different people will likely produce T cells recognizing different epitopes for the same bacteria.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-04-25-microbiome-1/delcherico.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:60.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Bacteria can leak between the cells lining the intestines into the bloodstream, where they may trigger an immune reaction (Fig 1, Del Cherico, et al, 2022</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>If the epitopes our immune system attacks are too similar to regions on our own cells, autoimmune disease can develop. This means that the <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC9737253/">friendly bacteria that has leaked into the bloodstream</a> (where it does not belong) “looks” too similar to some of your own cells. For instance, if the bacteria “looks” like your pancreatic cells (which produce insulin), your T cells may begin mistakenly attacking these insulin-producing cells, leading to Type 1 Diabetes.</p>
<p>The microbiome can also play a role in how likely microbes are to leak out of a person’s gut in the first place! Low levels of certain commensal bacteria increases gut permeability. This heightened permeability allowing the microbes to leave the intestines. This process has been <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC9737253/">linked to progression of Type 1 Diabetes</a> to more advanced stages. Note that commensal bacteria are just one potential trigger for the development of autoimmune diseases. As I discussed in a <a href="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2023-03-22-viruses2/">previous post</a>, viral infections can also trigger Type 1 Diabetes and other autoimmune diseases.</p>
</section>
<section id="bacteria-travel-on-fungal-highways-in-the-plant-microbiome" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="bacteria-travel-on-fungal-highways-in-the-plant-microbiome">Bacteria travel on fungal highways in the plant microbiome</h2>
<p>Plants also have microbiomes. One component of the plant microbiome are fungi that surround the plant roots and the bacteria that travel along these “fungal highways.” The fungi exude sugars that the bacteria use as an energy source along their journeys. The bacteria are able to mineralize organic phosphate, which is beneficial to the fungus and to the plant. Together, the fungus, plant, and bacteria are in symbiotic relationships.</p>
<p>Watch <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=AnsYh6511Ic">this short 90 second video</a> to see bacteria traveling along a fungal highway in real-time. You won’t believe how fast they are!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-04-25-microbiome-1/fungal-highway-3.gif" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:70.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">From the Science Friday video on fungal highways</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>For more on fungal highways, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WpgAA1mh7Io">here is a 3 minute Science Fridays video</a> which discusess how fungal networks optimize traffic to avoid traffic jams. It’s created by Christian Baker, who does a great job of explaining science in a succinct and engaging way. In this video, he interviews math professor Dr.&nbsp;Marcus Roper of UCLA who studies the fluid dynamics of bacterial travel.</p>
<p>Other researchers are looking at the use of fungal highways to allow <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/16047804/">pollutant-degrading bacteria to travel</a>, which could help remove pollutants in a broader area as part of bioremediation efforts.</p>
<p>Plant microbiomes have a strong influence on their immune function. They help prevent the colonization and growth of pathogens. Unfortunately, <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41579-023-00900-7">climate change is altering the microbiomes of plants</a>, which can make them more susceptible to disease. There are several mechanisms by which this can happen. Climate change alters the composition of microbes found in soil, which is the first line of defense for plants against pathogens. Plants release chemicals and metabolites into the soil, which are useful for attracting beneficial microbiomes, and climate change can harm plants’ capacity to do this (at least in the same quantities as before). Both plants and microbes may migrate into new areas due to changes in climate, further disrupting previous equilibriums.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-04-25-microbiome-1/climate-change-3ab.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:80.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Some of the ways that climate change can impact plant microbiomes, Fig 3 from Singh, et al, 2023</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="study-of-the-microbiome-is-both-old-and-very-new" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="study-of-the-microbiome-is-both-old-and-very-new">Study of the microbiome is both old and very new</h2>
<p>My microbiome course began with an in-depth unit covering different methods for sequencing genomes. There have been <a href="">multiple revolutions</a> in gene sequencing technology in recent decades, and new machines for gene sequencing are released regularly. Our growing understanding of the microbiome would not be possible without this technology to sequence numerous bacterial species in a sample, and in many ways the field is very young, with lots of open questions remaining.</p>
<p>Even though microbiome research has only taken off in the last 20 years with the advent of new sequencing technologies, ideas about the microbiome and its role in health have been around for a long time. <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3426293/">Antonie van Leewenhoek used a microscope</a> to compare the microbes in his oral and fecal microbiota in the 1680s.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-04-25-microbiome-1/metchkinoff-pacbio.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:70.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Left: Élie Metchnikoff, Right: a modern PacBio sequencing machine, which costs half a million dollars</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Élie Metchnikoff, who won the Nobel Prize in Medicine 1908, is best known as the father of cellular immunity. He discovered that there are immune cells that can ingest pathogens. He named them “eating cells” (phagocytes), and we now refer to these immune cells as “big eaters” (macrophages). In addition to discovering cellular immunity, <a href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fpubh.2013.00052/full">Metchnikoff is considered</a> one of the founders of probiotics. He believed consuming sour milk (yogurt) would be beneficial for the microbiome and he laid the conceptual framework for fecal transplantation to modify the microbiome, over 100 years ago. Questions about whether and how we can alter our microbiomes are still being <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC5374383/">studied and debated</a> today, as are the roles of genetics, lifestyle, and environment in influencing the microbiome.</p>
</section>
<section id="stay-tuned" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="stay-tuned">Stay tuned…</h2>
<p>Please subscribe to my blog to be notified of Part 2, which will describe the microbiomes of nanoplastics and wildfire smoke, as well as some puzzling examples of microbes that are both good and bad.</p>
<p>In the meantime, you may be interested in a previous post of mine that discussed the microbiomes of insects, which can help produce both essential nutrients and defensive toxins to use against predators. Read more in <a href="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-01-09-insects/">4 Things I Learned About Bugs</a>.</p>
<p>Submit your email below to be notified of new posts:</p>
<script type="text/javascript" src="https://campaigns.zoho.com.au/js/zc.iframe.js"></script>
<iframe scrolling="no" frameborder="0" id="iframewin" width="100%" height="100%" src="https://zcmp-pd.maillist-manage.com.au/ua/Optin?od=11d0c075b7ed49&amp;zx=11a17553b1&amp;tD=156971d471c7b09&amp;sD=156971d471c7cb3">
</iframe>


</section>

<p><br><br><i>I look forward to reading your responses. Create a free GitHub account to comment below.</i></p> ]]></description>
  <category>science</category>
  <guid>https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-04-25-microbiome-1/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 24 Apr 2024 14:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-04-25-microbiome-1/fungal-highway-fingernail.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Using AI to Discover New Antibiotics</title>
  <dc:creator>Rachel Thomas</dc:creator>
  <link>https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-04-03-ai-antibiotics/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="a-growing-threat" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-growing-threat">A Growing Threat</h2>
<p>The WHO estimates that antimicrobial resistance (AMR) contributed to approximately 5 million deaths worldwide in 2019 (<a href="https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/antimicrobial-resistance">“Antimicrobial Resistance” 2023</a>). In the USA, AMR results annually in 8 million additional days spent in the hospital and over $20 billion in healthcare costs (<a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4206945/">Bush et al.&nbsp;2011</a>). The problem will only grow in magnitude as antibiotic resistant genes in bacteria spread. AMR is compounded by the fact that development of new antibiotics has stalled over the past few decades. Historically, antibiotics were primarily discovered from natural products generated by soil microbes. This approach led to an initial burst of discoveries in the mid-20th century, but since then, soil screening has produced diminishing returns. Other antibiotics were created as derivatives of known antibiotics, but these have a limited ability to outpace antibiotic resistance (<a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC8463434/">Randall and Davies 2021</a>).</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-04-03-ai-antibiotics/drug-funnel.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:60.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">The narrow funnel of drug discovery (Figure from U Michigan Alzheimer’s Disease Center)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Developing new drugs is an expensive, time-consuming, and failure-prone process, with only a small percentage of potential drug candidates making it from discovery through clinical testing to regulatory approval. Antibiotic research has been particularly neglected due to unfavourable financial incentives. New antibiotics are typically only used if standard antibiotics fail, and antibiotics are given for a limited course. Thus, antibiotic research is not seen as profitable and pharmaceutical companies have largely avoided it (<a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4273861/">Durrant and Amaro 2015</a>). Artificial intelligence holds promise for accelerating research to address this threat, although there are also limitations and risks.</p>
</section>
<section id="possibilities-with-deep-learning" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="possibilities-with-deep-learning">Possibilities with Deep Learning</h2>
<p>Machine learning uses data to find patterns, as opposed to relying on manually coded rules. Deep learning is a powerful family of machine learning algorithms, responsible for the recent breakthroughs in artificial intelligence. The field of has seen massive improvements in accuracy and speed, and reductions in cost. Key reasons for this progress are the affordability of GPUs (processors used in video gaming which can quickly perform numerical computations in parallel), increases in available data, and research advances in the underlying algorithms (<a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/nature14539">LeCun, Bengio, and Hinton 2015</a>).</p>
<p>Deep learning-assisted approaches to drug discovery offer a potentially faster and cheaper way to identify new antibiotic candidates. It is estimated that there are 10<sup>30</sup>–10<sup>60</sup> potential drug-like chemicals; this scale means it is impossible to explore even a fraction of these (<a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC8429579/">Melo, Maasch, and de la Fuente-Nunez 2021</a>). Algorithms can help determine what compounds to prioritize.</p>
</section>
<section id="protein-folding-approaches-with-ai" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="protein-folding-approaches-with-ai">Protein Folding Approaches with AI</h2>
<p>AlphaFold has revolutionized protein structure prediction (<a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-021-03819-2">Jumper et al.&nbsp;2021</a>, my <a href="https://youtu.be/pB0RxG1NdtA">summary here</a>) and there has been interest in using it to aid in antibiotic discovery. Researchers applied AlphaFold to the essential proteins from <em>E. coli</em> (<a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC9446081/">Wong et al.&nbsp;2022</a>). They then used molecular docking programs to predict if these sites would be able to bind with over 300 different existing drug compounds. When they tested the predictions experimentally in the lab, they found that accuracy was relatively low. One limitation of the approach is that AlphaFold does not differentiate between active vs.&nbsp;inactive conformations. The researchers highlighted the need for better scoring functions to accurately rank the binding poses and for benchmarking datasets to evaluate performance (<a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC9446081/">Wong et al.&nbsp;2022</a>).</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-04-03-ai-antibiotics/lyu-2023-1a.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:70.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Comparisons between actual protein structures in turquoise versus AlphaFold predictions in yellow (Figure 1a from Lyu, et al, 2023)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>A more recent pre-print (not yet peer-reviewed) offered a potential explanation of AlphaFold’s poor performance on predicting existing drugs (<a href="https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2023.12.20.572662v1">Lyu et al.&nbsp;2023</a>, <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-024-00130-8">news coverage</a>). The authors proposed that minor differences in structure may cause AlphaFold to miss existing drugs, but that it may be identifying equally promising ones. Starting with 2 known protein structures, the researchers used AlphaFold to virtually screen millions of potential drugs and then synthesized a few hundred of the most promising candidates. For comparison, they also followed a more traditional process to screen and synthesize drug candidates. Even though AlphaFold and the traditional process yielded completely different drug candidates, they had similar success rates of how many of the candidates bound to the proteins of interest as predicted (<a href="https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2023.12.20.572662v1">Lyu et al.&nbsp;2023</a>).</p>
</section>
<section id="predicting-antibacterial-activity-with-ai" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="predicting-antibacterial-activity-with-ai">Predicting Antibacterial Activity with AI</h2>
<p>Other work has not relied on protein structure prediction software like AlphaFold, but instead created deep learning models directly for the underlying problem. Researchers used training sets of thousands of small molecule drugs to build models predicting which will have antibacterial activity (<a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC8349178/">Stokes et al.&nbsp;2020</a>; <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41589-023-01349-8">Liu et al.&nbsp;2023</a>). Message-passing neural networks, a type of deep learning model, allow for iteratively exchanging information between adjacent atoms and bonds. This captures some of the structural information of a protein, without explicitly predicting protein structure. A model was created using a dataset of thousands of repurposed drugs, and then applied to chemical libraries containing over 100 million molecules (<a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC8349178/">Stokes et al.&nbsp;2020</a>). The output was a ranking of the most promising drug candidates based on predicted antibacterial activity, chemical structure, and availability. This approach predicted that Halicin, which is structurally distinct form existing classes of antibiotics, would be an effective drug. When tested empirically, Halicin demonstrated a broad-spectrum impact against bacteria including M. tuberculosis, carbapenem-resistant <em>Enterobacteriaceae</em>, <em>C. difficile</em>, and multi-resistant <em>A. baumannii</em> (<a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC8349178/">Stokes et al.&nbsp;2020</a>).</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-04-03-ai-antibiotics/stokes-2020.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:75.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">The process used to discover Aubacin with a message-passing neural network (Figure 1 from Stokes, et al, 2020)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>A similar approach was used by the same lab to train a deep learning model to predict antibiotics that would be effective against multi-resistant <em>Acinetobacter baumannii</em> (<a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41589-023-01349-8">Liu et al.&nbsp;2023</a>). The WHO has designated drug resistant <em>A. baumannii</em> as one of the highest priorities for urgent development of new antibiotics. The model discovered a new antibiotic drug, Aubacin, which is structurally distinct from existing classes of antibiotics. In a lab experiment, Aubacin was effective at supressing <em>A. baumannii</em> in a mouse wound. It was also effective when tested against 41 different strains of resistant A. baumannii from the CDC Antibiotic Resistant Isolation bank (<a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41589-023-01349-8">Liu et al.&nbsp;2023</a>).</p>
</section>
<section id="data-sources-and-tools" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="data-sources-and-tools">Data Sources and Tools</h2>
<p>AI models are highly dependent on the data used to train them. Training data shapes the accuracy of a model, helps set what possibilities are considered, and determines the context in which it is appropriate to use. One useful data source is the <a href="https://www.broadinstitute.org/drug-repurposing-hub">Drug Repurposing Hub</a> (<a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/nm.4306">Corsello et al.&nbsp;2017</a>), which contains a hand-curated collection of thousands of existing drugs, including ones where safety was established in clinical trials, but that never obtained regulatory approval. Applying existing drugs to new diseases other than that which they were originally developed for is a pragmatic approach that can have a rapid and lower-cost impact. Another useful tool is the <a href="https://zinc15.docking.org/">ZINC15 database</a>, which includes data on small molecules, including their biological activity and chemical properties (<a href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/full/10.1021/acs.jcim.5b00559">Sterling and Irwin 2015</a>). Both the Drug Repurposing Hub and ZINC 15 databases have been used in neural network approaches (<a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC8349178/">Stokes et al.&nbsp;2020</a>; <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41589-023-01349-8">Liu et al.&nbsp;2023</a>).</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-04-03-ai-antibiotics/drug-repurposing-hub-S2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:75.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Diverse indications for drugs in the Drug Repurposing Hub, from 2017 launch. It has since grown in size to now include nearly 8,000 compounds (Figure S2 from Corsello, et al, 2017)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p><a href="https://www.rdkit.org/">RDKit</a> is an open-source library that can be used to compute molecular features. Some researchers use these computed features to augment the data gathered purely from existing structures and ligands, using one of the above databases together with RDKit-computed features as inputs to their models (<a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41589-023-01349-8">Liu et al.&nbsp;2023</a>).</p>
</section>
<section id="risks-and-limitations" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="risks-and-limitations">Risks and Limitations</h2>
<p>The research described above of antibiotics discovered through deep learning-assisted processes is still in preliminary stages, with none of those drugs having yet begun clinical trials, much less reached regulatory approval. In other fields, machine learning models have sometimes performed well in testing but failed to work as expected when deployed in the real world (<a href="https://research.google/pubs/everyone-wants-to-do-the-model-work-not-the-data-work-data-cascades-in-high-stakes-ai/">Sambasivan et al.&nbsp;2021</a>). Issues can arise when the context and quality of the training data is not fully understood (<a href="https://dl.acm.org/doi/10.1145/3458723">Gebru et al.&nbsp;2021</a>). ML systems are trained in clearly defined environments, while the physical world often has complex and volatile underlying phenomena, which are not fully accounted for during training. This can create a brittleness in ML-generated solutions. Moreover, there is a conflicting incentive system in which the creators of ML models are rewarded with prestige, but the arduous work used to gather and curate the data used to train those models is often neglected and taken for granted (<a href="https://research.google/pubs/everyone-wants-to-do-the-model-work-not-the-data-work-data-cascades-in-high-stakes-ai/">Sambasivan et al.&nbsp;2021</a>).</p>
<p>However, given the urgency of the antimicrobial resistance crisis, it is important that we consider a variety of innovative solutions for tackling it. Deep learning can be a powerful tool, and approaches to antibiotic discovery should continue to be pursued.</p>
<p><em>You can subscribe to be notified of new blog posts by submitting your email below:</em></p>
<script type="text/javascript" src="https://campaigns.zoho.com.au/js/zc.iframe.js"></script>
<iframe scrolling="no" frameborder="0" id="iframewin" width="100%" height="100%" src="https://zcmp-pd.maillist-manage.com.au/ua/Optin?od=11d0c075b7ed49&amp;zx=11a17553b1&amp;tD=156971d471c7b09&amp;sD=156971d471c7cb3">
</iframe>


</section>

<p><br><br><i>I look forward to reading your responses. Create a free GitHub account to comment below.</i></p> ]]></description>
  <category>machine learning</category>
  <category>science</category>
  <guid>https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-04-03-ai-antibiotics/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 02 Apr 2024 14:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-04-03-ai-antibiotics/thumbnail.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>“AI will cure cancer” misunderstands both AI and medicine</title>
  <dc:creator>Rachel Thomas</dc:creator>
  <link>https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-02-20-ai-medicine/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>AI has made remarkable strides in the medical field, with capabilities including the <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-023-06555-x">detection of Parkinson’s disease via retinal images</a>, <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41591-023-02361-0">identification of promising drug candidates</a>, and <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-023-06160-y">prediction of hospital readmissions</a>. While these advance are exciting, I’m wary of the practical impact AI will have on patients.</p>
<p>I recently watched a late-night talk show where skeptics and enthusiasts debated AI safety. Despite their conflicting views, there was one thing they could all agree upon. “AI will cure cancer,” one panelist declared, and everyone else confidently echoed their agreement. This collective optimism strikes me as overly idealistic and raises concerns about a failure to grapple with the realities of healthcare.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-02-20-ai-medicine/zhou-ext-fig-6.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:70.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">AI models can use retinal images to accurately detect Parkinson’s disease, stroke risk, and other medical issues (Extended Figure 6 from Zhou, et al, 2023)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>My reservations about AI in medicine stem from two core issues: First, the medical system often disregards patient perspectives, inherently limiting our comprehension of medical conditions. Second, AI is used to disproportionately benefit the privileged while worsening inequality. In many instances, claims like “AI will cure cancer” are being invoked as little more than superficial marketing slogans. To understand why, it is first necessary to understand how AI is used, and how the medical system operates.</p>
<section id="how-automated-decision-making-is-used" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-automated-decision-making-is-used">How Automated Decision Making is Used</h2>
<p>Automated computer systems, often involving AI, are increasingly being used to make decisions that have a big impact on people’s lives: determining who gets jobs, housing, or healthcare. Disturbing patterns are found across numerous countries and a range of systems: there is typically no way to surface or correct errors, and all too often the goal is to increase corporate and government revenues by denying poor people resources they need to survive.</p>
<p>A woman in France had her food benefits reduced by a computer program and can no longer afford enough to eat. She talked to a program officer, who said <a href="https://www.hrw.org/news/2021/11/10/how-eus-flawed-artificial-intelligence-regulation-endangers-social-safety-net">the cut was due to an error in the computer program</a>, but was unable to change it. She did not have her food benefits reinstated. The system was designed such that the computer is always considered correct, even when humans recognize an error. This woman was not alone; she was one of 60,000 people who went hungry due to these errors.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-02-20-ai-medicine/hrw.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:70.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">From the Human Rights Watch report on automated decision making in the EU, https://www.hrw.org/news/2021/11/10/how-eus-flawed-artificial-intelligence-regulation-endangers-social-safety-net</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>A man in Australia was told that he had been overpaid welfare benefits and that he was now in debt to the government. The debt was an error, based on an intentionally faulty calculation as part of the computational RoboDebt program. However, the man had no way to contest it. Despondent, <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/australia-news/2023/feb/20/platitudes-and-false-words-mother-of-robodebt-victim-who-took-own-life-tells-inquiry-of-government-stonewalling">he died by suicide</a>. This was not a one-off incident. The Australian government was later found to have wrongly created debts for hundreds of thousands of people.They were putting poor people into debt with a flawed calculation system, ruining lives efficiently at scale. The government had <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/australia-news/2020/may/29/robodebt-government-to-repay-470000-unlawful-centrelink-debts-worth-721m">increased the number of poor people it put into debt</a> each week by 50x, compared to before RoboDebt.</p>
<p>A woman in the USA with cerebral palsy needed a health aid to help her get out of bed in the morning, to get her meals, and to complete other basic tasks. Her care was drastically <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2018/3/21/17144260/healthcare-medicaid-algorithm-arkansas-cerebral-palsy">cut due to a computer bug</a>. She was given no explanation and no option for recourse as her quality of life drastically plummeted. Only through a lengthy court case was it finally revealed that many people with cerebral palsy had wrongly lost their care due to a computer error.</p>
</section>
<section id="patterns-in-automated-decision-making" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="patterns-in-automated-decision-making">Patterns in Automated Decision Making</h2>
<p>These examples always flow in the same direction. <a href="https://digitalrepository.unm.edu/nmlr/vol50/iss3/2/">Professor Alvaro Bedoya</a>, the founding director of the Center on Privacy and Technology at the Georgetown University Law Center, wrote “<em>It is a pattern throughout history that surveillance is used against those considered ‘less than’, against the poor man, the person of color, the immigrant, the heretic. It is used to try to stop marginalized people from achieving power.</em>” The same pattern is found in the role of technology in decision systems.</p>
<p>The goal of many automated decision systems is to increase revenues for governments and private companies. When this is applied to health and medicine, the goal is often achieved by denying poor people food or medical care. People often trust computers to be more accurate than humans, in a bias known as automation bias. A <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3240751/">systematic review of 74 research studies</a> found that automation bias exists across a range of fields, including healthcare, exerting a consistent influence. This bias can make it harder for people to recognize errors in automated decision-making. Moreover, implementing mechanisms to identify and correct errors is often seen as an unnecessary expense.</p>
<p>In all of the cases above, the people most impacted (those losing access to needed food or medical care, or unjustly being thrown into debt) recognized the errors in the system earliest. Yet the systems were built with no mechanism for recognizing mistakes, for allowing the participation of those impacted, nor for providing recourse to those harmed. Unfortunately, this can also be the case in medicine.</p>
</section>
<section id="how-the-medical-system-operates" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-the-medical-system-operates">How the Medical System Operates</h2>
<p>An AI algorithm that reads MRIs more accurately would not have helped neurologist Ilene Ruhoy, MD, PhD, when she developed a 7 cm brain tumor. The key obstacle to her treatment was getting fellow neurologists to believe her symptoms and even order an MRI in the first place. “<em>I was told I knew too much, that I was working too hard, that I was stressed out, that I was anxious</em>,” <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/wellness/interactive/2022/women-pain-gender-bias-doctors/">Dr.&nbsp;Ruhoy recounts</a>. Eventually, after her symptoms worsened further, she was able to get an MRI and <a href="https://www.webmd.com/women/features/women-doctors-symptoms-dismissed">urgently sent in for a 7 hour surgery</a>. Because of the delay in her diagnosis, her tumor was so large that it could not be completely removed, which has led to it growing back since her first surgery.</p>
<p>Dr.&nbsp;Ruhoy’s experience is sadly common. While Dr.&nbsp;Ruhoy lives in the USA, a study in the UK found that <a href="https://www.bbc.com/future/article/20180523-how-gender-bias-affects-your-healthcare">almost 1 in 3 patients with brain tumors</a> had to visit doctors at least 5 times before receiving an accurate diagnosis. Again, MRI-reading AI can not help these patients whose doctors won’t order an MRI in the first place. On average, it takes <a href="https://academic.oup.com/rheumap/article/4/1/rkaa006/5758274">Lupus patients 7 years</a> to receive a correct diagnosis, and 1 in 3 are initially misdiagnosed with doctors incorrectly claiming mental health issues are the root of their symptoms. Even healthcare workers are often shocked at how quickly they are dismissed and disbelieved once they become patients. For instance, <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/health/archive/2021/11/health-care-workers-long-covid-are-being-dismissed/620801/">interviews with a dozen healthcare workers</a> revealed that their colleagues shifted to discarding their expertise as soon as they developed Long Covid.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-02-20-ai-medicine/nothing-wrong-2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:70.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">‘Everybody was telling me there was nothing wrong’, a BBC article by Maya Dusenbery</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>This disregard of patient experience and patient expertise severely limits medical knowledge. It results in delayed diagnoses, misdiagnoses, missing data, and incorrect data. AI is great at finding patterns in existing data. However, AI will not be able to solve this problem of missing and erroneous underlying data. Furthermore, there is a negative feedback loop around lack of medical data for poorly understood diseases: doctors disbelieve patients and dismiss them as anxious or complaining too much, failing to gather data which could help illuminate the disease.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-wrong-data" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-wrong-data">The Wrong Data</h2>
<p>Even worse, often research problems are reformulated to shoe-horn inadequate data sources in. Analyzing electronic health record data is cheaper than searching for new causal mechanisms. Medical data is often limited by the categories of billing codes, by what doctors choose to note from a patient’s account, and what tests are ordered. The data are inherently incomplete.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.bbc.com/future/article/20180518-the-inequality-in-how-women-are-treated-for-pain">Medical bias</a> is widespread, with studies documenting that doctors give <a href="https://academic.oup.com/painmedicine/article/13/2/150/1935962">less pain medication to Black patients</a> than to white patients for the same conditions. On average, <a href="https://www.bbc.com/future/article/20180523-how-gender-bias-affects-your-healthcare">women have to wait months or years longer</a> than men to get an accurate diagnosis for the same conditions. This impacts the data that is collected and will be used for AI. <a href="https://aclanthology.org/D17-1323/">Multiple research studies</a> have shown that AI not only encodes existing biases, but <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1901.09451">can also amplify their magnitude</a>. At heart, these biases often pivot on not believing marginalized people about their experiences: not believing when they say that they are in pain nor how they report their symptoms.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-02-20-ai-medicine/hirsch2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:75.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">From Aubrey Hirsch’s powerful comic, “Medicine’s Women Problem”, https://thenib.com/medicine-s-women-problem/</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>On a deeper level, ignoring patient expertise limits what hypotheses are devised, and can slow research progress. These issues will propagate into AI, unless researchers seek ways to include meaningful patient participation. These problems are not unique to any one country or any one type of medical system. Patients across the USA, UK, Australia, and Canada (the 4 countries I am most familiar with) are all well-documented to experience these issues.</p>
</section>
<section id="being-honest-about-the-risks-and-opportunities" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="being-honest-about-the-risks-and-opportunities">Being Honest About the Risks and Opportunities</h2>
<p>While AI holds transformative possibilities for medicine, it is important that we are clear-eyed about both the risks and the opportunities. Many talks on Medical AI give the impression that the only thing holding medicine back is a lack of knowledge. The many other factors that influence medical care, including the systematic disregard for patients’ knowledge of their own experiences, are often ignored in these discussions. Ignoring these realities will lead people to design AI for an idealized medical system that does not exist. There is already a clear pattern in which AI is used to centralize power and harm the marginalized. In medicine, this could lead to patients, who are already disempowered and often disregarded, having even less autonomy or voice.</p>
<p>In my view, some of the most promising areas of research are participatory approaches to machine learning and patient-led medical research. The <a href="https://participatoryml.github.io/">Participatory Approaches to Machine Learning workshop at ICML</a> included a powerful collection of talks and papers on both the need and the opportunities for designing systems with greater participation of those impacted. AI ethics work on topics of contestability (building in ways for participants to contest outputs) and actionable recourse are necessary. For medical research more generally, the <a href="https://patientresearchcovid19.com/">Patient Led Research Collaborative</a> (focused on Long Covid) is an encouraging model. I hope that we can see more efforts within medical AI to center patient expertise.</p>
</section>
<section id="for-further-reading-watching" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="for-further-reading-watching">For further reading / watching:</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vVRWeGlMkGk&amp;list=PLtmWHNX-gukLQlMvtRJ19s7-8MrnRV6h6&amp;index=3">AI, Medicine, and Bias: Diversifying Your Dataset is Not Enough</a> - my keynote talk at the Stanford AI in Medical Imaging symposium</li>
<li><a href="https://www.bostonreview.net/articles/rachel-thomas-medicines-machine-learning-problem/">Medicine’s Machine Learning Problem</a> - my Boston Review article on medicine and AI</li>
<li><a href="https://www.bbc.com/future/article/20180523-how-gender-bias-affects-your-healthcare">‘Everybody was telling me there was nothing wrong’</a> - BBC article by Maya Dusenberry</li>
<li><a href="https://thenib.com/medicine-s-women-problem/">Medicine’s Women Problem</a> - comic by Aubrey Hirsch</li>
<li><a href="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2023-05-16-ai-centralizes-power/">AI and Power: The Ethical Challenges of Automation, Centralization, and Scale</a> - a deeper dive into how AI centralizes power</li>
<li><a href="https://www.hrw.org/news/2021/11/10/how-eus-flawed-artificial-intelligence-regulation-endangers-social-safety-net">How the EU’s Flawed Artificial Intelligence Regulation Endangers the Social Safety Net</a> - Human Rights Watch</li>
</ul>
<p><em>Thank you to Jeremy Howard and Krystal South for providing feedback on earlier drafts of this post.</em></p>
<p><br><br></p>
<p>You can subscribe to be notified of new blog posts by submitting your email below:</p>
<script type="text/javascript" src="https://campaigns.zoho.com.au/js/zc.iframe.js"></script>
<iframe scrolling="no" frameborder="0" id="iframewin" width="100%" height="100%" src="https://zcmp-pd.maillist-manage.com.au/ua/Optin?od=11d0c075b7ed49&amp;zx=11a17553b1&amp;tD=156971d471c7b09&amp;sD=156971d471c7cb3">
</iframe>


</section>

<p><br><br><i>I look forward to reading your responses. Create a free GitHub account to comment below.</i></p> ]]></description>
  <category>ethics</category>
  <category>machine learning</category>
  <category>science</category>
  <guid>https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-02-20-ai-medicine/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 19 Feb 2024 14:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-02-20-ai-medicine/zhou-cover-2.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>How Immune Cells Communicate</title>
  <dc:creator>Rachel Thomas</dc:creator>
  <link>https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-02-06-cytokines2/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><em>This post is part 2 in a series. Be sure to <a href="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-01-23-cytokines1/">read part 1 here</a>.</em></p>
<p>A key obstacle hindering medical research for a range of diseases is our lack of understanding of the immune system. <a href="https://www.freethink.com/health/human-immunome">Harvard Professor Wayne Koff described</a> his decades of HIV research, “<em>slowly, over time, we began to see that we understood a lot about HIV at the molecular level, but we didn’t know anything about ourselves. And the reason is that the immune system is incredibly complex</em>.”</p>
<p>Many diseases involve the immune system overreacting, underreacting, or having a mistargeted reaction. Deepening our understanding of the immune system is crucial for better understanding and treating a range of diseases. In <a href="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-01-23-cytokines1/">part 1 of this series</a>, I shared about the networks by which immune cells communicate and coordinate via the use of protein messengers called <em>cytokines</em>. These networks are complex and not fully mapped. Studying these networks is part of determining how and why the immune system reacts as it does. Here, I will share some more research on immune cell-cytokine networks.</p>
<section id="immune-cells-coordinate-like-a-social-network" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="immune-cells-coordinate-like-a-social-network">Immune Cells Coordinate Like a Social Network</h2>
<p>Immune cells and the cytokines they use to communicate can be analyzed using the same techniques as are used for social networks. Networks can be represented as matrices, in which each column/row represents a node, and the matrix values represent the presence or strength of connections between them. This type of representation underlies how the network of the internet is represented for search engines such as Google. Matrix math is everywhere! I covered many applications of it in the computational linear algebra course that Jeremy Howard and I designed and taught at University of San Francisco and fast.ai.</p>
<p>The <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/ni.3693">paper ImmProt</a> sampled immune cells from the bloodstream of humans and used proteomics (the large-scale analysis of proteins) to study immune communication networks. The researchers considered 28 cell types in both steady and activated states, and over 10,000 proteins. ImmProt used several classic math techniques to analyze the network, including principal component analysis, supervised clustering, and Lasso regression analysis.</p>
<p>Cytokines bind to receptors on the surface of the cell that is receiving them. Receptors for some cytokines are found on many different types of immune cells (these receptors are said to be “broadly expressed”), while receptors for other cytokines may be expressed on a very limited number of cell types. The researchers found that there were two types of cytokine communication patterns: there were either many types of cells sending and few types receiving for a given cytokine, or there were few types of cells sending and many receiving. This is a directed, asymmetric information exchange.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-02-06-cytokines2/rieckmann-6h.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:65.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">A single type of message (in this case, CCL5/3) can be sent to many different cells (figure 6h from ImmProt)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The authors looked at the number of in-going and out-going communication between various cell types, and determined how much cross-talk there is between different clusters of cell types. In the above diagram, the outer circle lists cell types and the middle circle lists receptor and cytokine gene names. This picture shows that eosinophils and basophils (two cell types that evolved primarily to address parasites) send the cytokine CCL5/3 to a variety of other cells that receive the message using the receptor CCR3. The color of the lines indicates the type of cell sending the cytokine.</p>
<p>While many of the relationships found were well established in existing scientific papers, they also discovered new relationships, and validated two of these new relationships experimentally: one in-going and one out-going. <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/ni.3693">The authors wrote</a>, “<em>The immune system displays an almost infinite diversity in cell types and activation states, and achieving completeness in both dimensions is particularly challenging for human cells</em>.”</p>
</section>
<section id="ai-does-not-replace-other-ways-of-knowing-about-the-world-benchtop-research-is-still-crucial" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="ai-does-not-replace-other-ways-of-knowing-about-the-world-benchtop-research-is-still-crucial">AI does not replace other ways of knowing about the world: benchtop research is still crucial</h2>
<p>AI is a powerful tool, but it does not replace other ways of knowing about the world, including <a href="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2022-06-01-qualitative/">qualitative research</a> (as I wrote about together with Louisa Bartolo) and benchtop quantitative experiments. Machine learning and AI techniques are great at learning patterns in existing data. However, they are limited by what types of data have been collected so far, and it is still crucial to continue running new laboratory-based experiments. For this reason, the recent <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-023-06816-9">Immune Dictionary paper</a> was a valuable contribution to the field. The researchers gathered direct measurements of over &gt;1,400 cytokine-cell type pairings in an in vivo experiment.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-02-06-cytokines2/immune-dictionary-1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:60.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Steps for creating a dictionary of immune gene expression signatures (Figure 1A from Immune Dictionary)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>This study was significant because it considered all major immune cell types and all major cytokines (studies typically look at only 5 immune cell types) and was conducted in vivo (not in a culture). The researchers injected 86 different cytokines into individual mice and measured the responses of 17 types of immune cells in the mouse lymph nodes. They used single-cell RNA sequencing, which is more direct than considering ligand and receptor expression association data. They released their findings as an “Immune Dictionary” and developed <a href="https://www.immune-dictionary.org/app/home">accompanying computer software</a>. This software was then used to identify cytokine networks in tumors after checkpoint blockade therapy (a cancer therapy that helps to reactivate exhausted immune cells).</p>
<p><a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-023-06816-9">One key finding</a> was that the responses induced by cytokines are highly cell-specific. Rarer types of immune cells expressed a greater number of cytokine types than more common cell types. One rare cell type, typically not even covered in immunology courses, was found to express the highest number of distinct cytokines, influencing nearly every other cell type. This result suggests that rare immune cell types are crucial for cell-to-cell communication.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-02-06-cytokines2/immune-dictionary-software.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:75.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Software for the dictionary of 17+ immune cell types responding to 86 cytokines in vivo</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Another important finding was that every immune cell type could be polarized into multiple states depending on the combination of cytokines that it received. The <a href="https://www.broadinstitute.org/news/new-dictionary-immune-responses-reveals-far-more-complexity-immune-system-previously-thought">two key researchers were surprised</a> at this level of plasticity and complexity in immune cell types, with even the most well-studied cytokines inducing more complex responses than previously expected.</p>
</section>
<section id="an-ongoing-area-of-research" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="an-ongoing-area-of-research">An Ongoing Area of Research</h2>
<p>This is an exciting area of research to follow. There is still much work to be done in more thoroughly understanding the intricate and complex ways immune cells coordinate with one another to respond to threats. Immune cell-cytokine networks are a great illustration of the power of interdisciplinary work, since NLP, mathematics, and bench top immunology research all provide important insights into the problem. And this is just one of several important problems in immunology where AI is being applied!</p>
<p>You can subscribe to be notified of new blog posts by submitting your email below:</p>
<script type="text/javascript" src="https://campaigns.zoho.com.au/js/zc.iframe.js"></script>
<iframe scrolling="no" frameborder="0" id="iframewin" width="100%" height="100%" src="https://zcmp-pd.maillist-manage.com.au/ua/Optin?od=11d0c075b7ed49&amp;zx=11a17553b1&amp;tD=156971d471c7b09&amp;sD=156971d471c7cb3">
</iframe>


</section>

<p><br><br><i>I look forward to reading your responses. Create a free GitHub account to comment below.</i></p> ]]></description>
  <category>machine learning</category>
  <category>science</category>
  <guid>https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-02-06-cytokines2/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 05 Feb 2024 14:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-02-06-cytokines2/rieckmann-network.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Applying AI to Immune Cell Networks</title>
  <dc:creator>Rachel Thomas</dc:creator>
  <link>https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-01-23-cytokines1/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="the-value-of-domain-expertise" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-value-of-domain-expertise">The value of domain expertise</h2>
<p>Back in 2016, Jeremy Howard and I founded the research lab <a href="https://www.fast.ai/posts/2016-10-07-fastai-launch.html">fast.ai</a>. At the time, deep learning (the technique behind recent advances in AI) was the purview of a small and homogeneous handful of practitioners. The standard approach was to have computer science PhDs tackle problems in domains they had little familiarity with.</p>
<p>Jeremy and I proposed an ambitious idea–we wanted to teach people from all domains and backgrounds to be able to use deep learning. We weren’t even sure if our goal was possible. However, <a href="https://course.fast.ai/">our online course</a> became one of the most popular deep learning courses in the world, and members of the fast.ai community went on to join top research labs and major tech companies, <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2018/5/7/17316010/fast-ai-speed-test-stanford-dawnbench-google-intel">win competitions against Google</a>, and launch their own startups.</p>
<p>A core part of our mission was the belief that the people closest to a topic best understand the problems in that area and are best equipped to address them. I’m now one of those people in another domain, as I have <a href="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2023-02-07-school-immunology/">immersed myself in the field of immunology</a>. I am particularly interested in studying the intersection of immunology and AI. In this 2-part series, I will share some exciting research at this intersection.</p>
</section>
<section id="a-most-complicated-system" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-most-complicated-system">A Most Complicated System</h2>
<p>The immune system is even “more complicated than the human genome,” <a href="https://www.freethink.com/health/human-immunome">says John Tsang</a>, a professor at Yale School of Medicine. One component of this complexity is the complicated network by which immune cells communicate with one another via protein messengers known as <em>cytokines</em>.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-01-23-cytokines1/biolegend.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:80.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Poster of immune cell interactions from <a href="https://www.biolegend.com/en-ie/immunologic-networks-2011">https://www.biolegend.com/en-ie/immunologic-networks-2011</a></figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Immune cell communication through cytokines is a key area for us to better understand medicine and disease. Various immune cell types must communicate to coordinate their response to threats. However, the immune system may end up over-reacting, under-reacting, or having a misplaced reaction, all of which can cause disease. Sepsis occurs when the immune system responds too vigorously, damaging our own organs. In cancer, the immune system may under-respond, failing to attack cancerous cells that it should. Several types of cancer therapies involve trying to activate or reactivate our own immune cells. In other cases, the immune system mistakenly attacks our own tissue, causing autoimmune diseases including Type 1 diabetes, rheumatoid arthritis, multiple sclerosis, and psoriasis.</p>
<p>Recent research, drawing on a blend of immunology, mathematics, and natural language processing (NLP) AI, is helping us better understand immune cell-cytokine networks. I have a PhD in math, taught a <a href="https://www.fast.ai/posts/2019-07-08-fastai-nlp.html">masters course in NLP</a>, and <a href="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2023-02-07-school-immunology/">now study immunology</a>, so I have a particular interest in this work. Understanding how the immune system is communicating and coordinating is necessary for knowing why and how the immune response can go awry.</p>
</section>
<section id="how-immune-cells-communicate" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-immune-cells-communicate">How Immune Cells Communicate</h2>
<p>There are dozens of types of immune cells. The main way that immune cells communicate and coordinate with each other is by sending small protein messengers known as cytokines. There are hundreds of types of cytokines. A single cytokine can have different effects on different cell types. The impact of a cytokine depends on the type of cell sending it, the type of cell receiving it, and the state of the cell. This makes interpreting immune responses challenging!</p>
<p>Cytokine-based therapies are used to treat some diseases, including cancer and autoimmune disorders. The interactions between cells and cytokines form complex networks, which are not fully mapped.</p>
<p><em>Note: You may have heard the term “cytokine storm” in <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2020/04/01/health/coronavirus-cytokine-storm-immune-system.html">the news</a> during early coverage of covid (other diseases and some medical treatments can lead to cytokine storms as well). A cytokine storm occurs when the immune system reacts too vigorously, sending tons of messages and ramping up its inflammatory response to a level that is dangerous to the patient. The double-edged nature of the immune system is part of what piqued my interest about the topic.</em></p>
</section>
<section id="nlp-for-cell-cytokine-interactions" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="nlp-for-cell-cytokine-interactions">NLP for Cell-Cytokine Interactions</h2>
<p>Language models such as ChatGPT are part of the active field Natural Language Processing (NLP). NLP applies data science and machine learning to collections of text documents. At fast.ai, Jeremy Howard, Sylvain Gugger, and I developed a <a href="https://www.fast.ai/posts/2019-07-08-fastai-nlp.html">course on NLP in 2019</a>, teaching cutting edge techniques like transformers, which are now used in ChatGPT and other popular models.</p>
<p>One paper in immunology is published every 30 minutes! That is a lot of immunology papers, and NLP techniques can be used to help synthesize this huge quantity of information. While models like ChatGPT are trained using a huge variety of texts scraped from the internet, immune-focused work may focus on a more specific group of documents, such as PubMed abstracts. <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/nbt.4152">A computer program called ImmuneXpresso</a> was developed to text-mine the 16 million abstracts available on PubMed and create triples containing a cell type, cytokine, and whether the relationship was in-coming or out-going (i.e.&nbsp;if the cell was sending or receiving the cytokine).</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-01-23-cytokines1/immunexpresso.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:75.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Information flow of families of cytokines between families of cells (Figure 2A from ImmuneXpresso)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The above figure from the <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/nbt.4152">ImmuneXpresso paper</a> shows some of the information flow. Each family of cytokines shown contains multiple cytokines, and each family of cells contains multiple sub-types. The researchers relied on sentence syntax to parse these relationships, and captured associations with 188 diseases. A machine learning classifier was used to predict whether the data captured were related to cell-cytokine relationships. Over 4,000 directional cell–cytokine interactions were documented via this process. The authors experimentally tested two interactions that were predicted, but are not well-established in the literature, and validated that they hold true.</p>
</section>
<section id="a-famous-data-scientist-turns-to-immunology" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-famous-data-scientist-turns-to-immunology">A famous data scientist turns to immunology</h2>
<p>Jeff Hammerbacher created and led the data team at Facebook in 2006-2008 and was a founder of the successful cloud computing company Cloudera. A decade ago he made a similar pivot to the one I am currently attempting, starting <a href="https://www.hammerlab.org/">his own immunology lab</a> at Mt. Sinai and later the Medical University of South Carolina. He has applied machine learning to a variety of immunology problems, including <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/26856372/">predicting surgery outcomes</a>, <a href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fimmu.2017.01807/full">designing cancer vaccines</a>, and starting a <a href="https://www.related.vc/">data science focused drug-discovery firm</a>.</p>
<p>Hammerbacher, together with Ed Czech, tackled the problem of <a href="https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/643767v2">using NLP to extract cell type-cytokine relationships</a>. To give an example of the type of problems that must be addressed in NLP, “<em>Th1 (CD4+IL-17-IFN-γhi) cells</em>” is referring to the same cell type as “<em>helper CD4+IL-17-IFN-γhi type 1 cells</em>.” Expert knowledge must be encoded in how to properly parse and categorize cells, knowing when two different strings refer to the same cell type and when they are different.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-01-23-cytokines1/t-cells.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:85.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">A few different T-cells communicating. Source: biolegend.com</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>They compared two different deep learning models. In one case, they used a generative model with weak supervision, which allowed for them to begin with a smaller labeled dataset to generate labels for previously unlabeled data. In the other case, they used a language model (SciBERT) which had been pre-trained on scientific texts, and then they fine-tuned it for the specific PubMed immunology articles they were using. This is an example of <strong>transfer learning</strong>, a technique in which a machine learning model trained on a large dataset can be customized for use on a much smaller dataset. Transfer learning has been a central part of the fast.ai approach from the start, and was a key technique I featured in my <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=frc7FgheUj4&amp;list=PLtmWHNX-gukLQlMvtRJ19s7-8MrnRV6h6&amp;index=11">keynotes at JupyterCon 2017</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=KChtdexd5Jo&amp;list=PLtmWHNX-gukLQlMvtRJ19s7-8MrnRV6h6&amp;index=6">SciPy 2019</a>.</p>
<p>As part of Czech and Hammerbacher’s research, they created a database of T-cell specific cytokines and transcription factors, including relationships between 75 cell types, 262 cytokines, and 382 transcription factors. Their work was distinctive for having a tiny team (just 2 people, compared to 16 authors and 11 annotators for ImmuneXpresso), using 53k full-text documents (rather than solely abstracts), and focusing more narrowly on T-cells (as opposed to all immune cells). Techniques such as transfer learning are powerful in that they allow small teams of researchers to leverage previous models via fine-tuning. In addition to <a href="https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/643767v2">the paper</a>, Hammerbacher shared about this work in a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=pvj9tIdvOXQ">talk he gave at the Allen Institute for AI</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="stay-tuned" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="stay-tuned">Stay Tuned</h2>
<p>Stay tuned for part 2 of this series, which will cover more fascinating research about how immune cells communicate. You can subscribe to be notified of new blog posts by submitting your email below:</p>
<script type="text/javascript" src="https://campaigns.zoho.com.au/js/zc.iframe.js"></script>
<iframe scrolling="no" frameborder="0" id="iframewin" width="100%" height="100%" src="https://zcmp-pd.maillist-manage.com.au/ua/Optin?od=11d0c075b7ed49&amp;zx=11a17553b1&amp;tD=156971d471c7b09&amp;sD=156971d471c7cb3">
</iframe>


</section>

<p><br><br><i>I look forward to reading your responses. Create a free GitHub account to comment below.</i></p> ]]></description>
  <category>machine learning</category>
  <category>science</category>
  <guid>https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-01-23-cytokines1/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2024 14:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-01-23-cytokines1/biolegend-zoom.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>4 Things I Learned About Bugs</title>
  <dc:creator>Rachel Thomas</dc:creator>
  <link>https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-01-09-insects/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>I am currently halfway through my Masters of Microbiology &amp; Immunology. My goal is to apply my previous decade of experience as a data scientist and AI researcher to immunology. Even though my primary interest is on long-term impacts of viruses on humans, I wanted a broader and deeper understanding of microbiology in general. This past semester, I was pleasantly surprised to learn several fascinating facts about insects!</p>
<section id="insects-are-useful-for-making-medications-and-vaccines" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="insects-are-useful-for-making-medications-and-vaccines">Insects are useful for making medications and vaccines</h2>
<p>Proteins are a key component of many vaccines and medications. To create these proteins, scientists have come up with a range of <strong>protein expression systems</strong>. Bacteria, yeast, mammalian cells, and genetically modified animals can all be used to produce proteins for medications. And so can insects! For instance, <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/nbt1095">baculovirus is a virus</a> that mostly infects insects, and its genome can be modified to produce various cytokines (chemical messengers), antivirals (such as type 1 interferons), and vaccine components.</p>
<p>There are trade-offs with any choice of protein expression system. For example, <em>bacteria</em> are fast and cheap to use, but because they are quite dissimilar to humans, they are much worse for key steps such as protein folding or adding sugars to proteins (a process called glycosylation). And while <em>mammalian</em> cells or genetically modified animals will produce much more accurately folded proteins and glycosylation, they are expensive and slow for production. Baculoviruses from insects aren’t the worst in any of these categories, which makes them a widely useful workhorse for protein expression.</p>
<p>Insect cells are more similar to human cells than yeast or bacteria are, which means that the proteins they produce (when infected with <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC7159335/">modified baculoviruses</a>) are more likely to be folded correctly, and they make for cheaper and faster expression systems than mammalian cells do. A baculovirus expression system is used, for example, to produce Novavax, a popular protein-based covid vaccine (which may have fewer side-effects than mRNA-based covid vaccines such as Pfizer and Moderna).</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-01-09-insects/expression-systems.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:65.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Comparing Different Expression Systems, image from brainkart.com</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="insects-have-the-same-problems-humans-do-viral-bacterial-fungal-and-protozoan-infections" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="insects-have-the-same-problems-humans-do-viral-bacterial-fungal-and-protozoan-infections">Insects have the same problems humans do: viral, bacterial, fungal, and protozoan infections</h2>
<p>Insects can be infected with harmful viruses, bacteria, fungi, and protozoa. <strong>Entomopathogens</strong> is a fun vocabulary word for pathogens that infect arthropods (arthropods include insects, mites, ticks, spiders, and more). These are sometimes used as natural pesticides, in order to try to control insect pests that may be feeding on crops or spreading disease. <a href="https://ucanr.edu/blogs/blogcore/postdetail.cfm?postnum=24119">Entomopathogens may kill, limit reproduction, or shorten the life of arthropod pests</a>. They are generally less toxic to humans and other animals than other pesticides, although it is a risk that they could spread to related species.</p>
</section>
<section id="insects-really-need-the-bacteria-in-their-guts" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="insects-really-need-the-bacteria-in-their-guts">Insects really need the bacteria in their guts</h2>
<p>While some bacteria are harmful to insects, other bacteria are not only beneficial, but even essential. A diet consisting only of sap is not nutritionally complete. Neither is a diet just of blood. Some arthropods can’t produce all the vitamins they need, and instead rely on bacteria in their guts to help synthesize essential vitamins. These bacteria (known as obligate symbionts) rely on their hosts as well, in a mutually beneficial relationship. Bioinformatics and modern gene sequencing has revolutionized the study of these obligate symbionts by allowing for their genomes to be sequenced and studied. One paper calls them the <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/24995872/">“The Tiniest Tiny Genomes”</a>, and describes how through a long process of coevolution the bacteria lost the genes to manufacture cell membrane components. They are completely reliant on their hosts, while also producing B vitamins and essential amino acids.</p>
<p>While many types of bacteria help bugs synthesize nutrients, other types can help synthesize protective toxins to be used against predators. Diaphorina is an insect pest of citrus plants. Profftella, one of the bacterial obligate symbionts in its gut, is noteworthy for helping to <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/32797185/">synthesize both vitamins and protective toxins</a> for its host, whereas many symbionts provide either vitamins or toxins, but not both.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-01-09-insects/psyllid.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:80.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">A Diaphorina on a leaf– gut bacteria not pictured. Photo by David Hall, USDA ID d595-1.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="a-common-bacteria-in-insects-reduces-risk-of-dengue-virus-to-humans" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-common-bacteria-in-insects-reduces-risk-of-dengue-virus-to-humans">A common bacteria in insects reduces risk of Dengue Virus to humans</h2>
<p>An astonishing <a href="https://www.cdc.gov/mosquitoes/mosquito-control/community/emerging-methods/wolbachia.html">60% of insects</a> (including butterflies, bees, and beetles) around the world have the bacteria Wolbachia. This fascinating bacteria can have some surprising impacts, including reducing the ability of mosquitoes to carry or transmit dengue virus.</p>
<p><em>A. aegypti</em> mosquitoes are carriers of dengue virus. They do not naturally carry Wolbachia, but when mosquitoes with Wolbachia were <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41598-023-42336-2">released in North Queensland, Australia</a>, predicted transmission of dengue infections dropped by 95% over the following 2 years. <a href="https://www.nejm.org/doi/full/10.1056/nejmoa2030243">A randomized study in Indonesia</a> released Wolbachia-infected mosquitoes in some regions but not others, and found the regions with the Wolbachia-infected mosquitoes had 77% fewer dengue cases.</p>
<p>Another surprising effect of the bacteria is that a male mosquito with Wolbachia mates with a female mosquito that doesn’t have it, the fertilized eggs will not be viable. And two mosquitoes with different strains of Wolbachia can not produce viable eggs. Isn’t this weird??? This has been used in some efforts to reduce mosquito populations.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-01-09-insects/cytoplasmic-incompatibility.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:65.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Cytoplasmic incompatibility, figure from https://almob.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s13015-020-00174-1</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>


</section>

<p><br><br><i>I look forward to reading your responses. Create a free GitHub account to comment below.</i></p> ]]></description>
  <category>science</category>
  <guid>https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-01-09-insects/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 14:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2024-01-09-insects/psyllid.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>AI and Power: The Ethical Challenges of Automation, Centralization, and Scale</title>
  <dc:creator>Rachel Thomas</dc:creator>
  <link>https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2023-05-16-ai-centralizes-power/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Friends with no previous interest in AI ethics have begun asking me questions in the wake of the release of ChatGPT4, Bard, and Bing Chat. This new generation of large language models <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/12/10/technology/ai-chat-bot-chatgpt.html">has made headlines</a> and sparked widespread debate. To consider the risks posed by new AI applications, it is useful to first understand several underlying concepts. <a href="https://rachel.fast.ai/about.html">I spent years</a> researching the mechanisms by which algorithmic systems can cause harm, and in late 2021, I gave a 20-minute talk on what I consider key ideas at the heart of AI ethics. With the advent of the newest generation of language models, these concepts are more relevant than ever.</p>
<p>Over the past decade, topics such as <em>explainability</em> (having computers generate an explanation of why they compute the outputs they do) and <em>fairness/bias</em> (addressing when algorithms have worse accuracy on some groups of people than others) have gained more attention within the field of AI and in the media. Some computer scientists and journalists have stopped there: assuming that a computer program that can explain the logic behind its decision making, or a program that has the same accuracy on light-skinned men as on dark-skinned women, must now be ethical. While these principles are important, on their own they are not enough to address nor prevent harms of AI systems.</p>
<center>
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/spHB7IEFXbg" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="">
</iframe>
</center>
<p>Below is an edited transcript of this talk.</p>
<section id="actionable-recourse" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="actionable-recourse">Actionable Recourse</h2>
<p><em>Explainability</em> on its own is insufficient. Consider an algorithmic system that is making decisions about whether or not someone should get a loan. Often a question will be “why was my loan denied?”, but really the underlying question is “what can I change about my situation to get a loan in the future?”</p>
<p>An explanation should be <em>actionable</em>. For example, it’s not okay to deny a loan because of ethnicity. That’s discrimination and it would not make for a satisfying explanation. For decisions impacting people’s lives, there also needs to be a mechanism for <em>recourse</em>, so that decisions can be changed. This is <em>actionable recourse</em>, as <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1809.06514">described by Berk Ustun</a>.</p>
<p>This underlying idea of actionable recourse shows up in many applications. There is an example I return to often, since it’s a pattern that we see across many countries. In the USA there is an algorithm to determine poor people’s health care benefits. When it was implemented in one state there was a <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2018/3/21/17144260/healthcare-medicaid-algorithm-arkansas-cerebral-palsy">bug in the code that incorrectly cut care</a> for people with cerebral palsy. Tammy Dobbs was one of the many people that lost care due to a software bug. She needed this care for very basic life functions: to help her get out of bed in the morning, to get her breakfast, and so on. She asked for an explanation and they didn’t give her one; they just said this is what the algorithm determined. At the root, what she needed was not just an explanation, but a mechanism for recourse to get the decision changed. Eventually the error was revealed through a lengthy court case, but that is a terrible setup.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2023-05-16-ai-centralizes-power/cuts-healthcare2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:60.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">When an algorithm cuts your health care</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>This illustrates a common issue that shows up again and again: <strong>automated systems are often implemented with no way to identify and address mistakes</strong>.</p>
<p>There are a few reasons why there is no mechanism for catching mistakes. Often automation is being used as a cost cutting measure and having robust error checking in place and ways to surface mistakes would cost more. There can also be biases of people mistakenly believing that computers are perfectly accurate.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.hrw.org/news/2021/11/10/how-eus-flawed-artificial-intelligence-regulation-endangers-social-safety-net">Human Rights Watch put out a report</a> on automated system use in the EU for social benefits. Country after country had alarming examples where there were errors, yet no clear way to identify, much less address, them. There was a case in France where an algorithm to determine food benefits made errors in at least 60,000 cases. One woman said her case manager even agreed this was a bug and that she deserved to receive benefits, but the case manager didn’t have the power to reinstate them!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2023-05-16-ai-centralizes-power/hrw-eu.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:75.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Human Rights Watch report</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Another domain to consider is content moderation. The <a href="https://santaclaraprinciples.org/">Santa Clara Principles for content moderation</a> were developed by a group of ethicists, although these principles are not observed by the major platforms. I want to share Principle 3, because I love the wording, which is that companies should provide a <em>meaningful opportunity for timely appeal</em>. I really like this idea of appeal being <em>meaningful</em> and <em>timely</em>. I think this is relevant far, far beyond content moderation. Too often, even when there is a way to try to report a mistake, you just get an automated response that clearly hasn’t been read or you have to wait months for an answer. It is important that appeals are not just available, but also that they are meaningful and timely.</p>
</section>
<section id="contestability" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="contestability">Contestability</h2>
<p><a href="https://dl.acm.org/doi/abs/10.1145/3311957.3359435"><em>Contestability</em></a> is the idea of building an algorithmic system to include mechanisms for questioning and disagreeing with results as part of the system, rather than as an external add-on. Too often we build computational systems assuming okay this is going to work great, and then when there are errors, we tack on something extra at the end. I found this provocative to think about how we <strong>include disagreement into the core of the system</strong>.</p>
<p>I had considered this from a slightly different angle in my work with fast.ai, where we have a concept of what we call <em>augmented machine learning</em>. This is in contrast to auto machine learning, which is often about automating a process end to end. With <a href="https://slideslive.com/38917533/lessons-learned-from-helping-200000-nonml-experts-use-ml">augmented machine learning</a> we really wanted to think about what are the things that humans are really good at and how can we take advantage of human strengths as opposed to simply trying to automate everything and then being left with weird gaps of stuff that computers are not doing well. How can humans and computers best work together? This is important to keep in mind with system design.</p>
</section>
<section id="fairness-and-bias" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="fairness-and-bias">Fairness and Bias</h2>
<p>It is important to consider fairness and bias, but that alone is insufficient. I imagine many of you are familiar with the <a href="http://gendershades.org/overview.html">Gender Shades research</a> on facial recognition by Joy Boulamwini, Timnit Gebru, and Deborah Raji. They evaluated commercial computer vision products that had been released from a number of big name companies including Microsoft, IBM, and <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2019/01/24/technology/amazon-facial-technology-study.html">Amazon</a>. They found that the products performed worse on women than on men and worse on people with dark skin than on people with light skin, leading to terrible results for dark-skinned women. For instance, IBM’s product had 99.7% accuracy on light skinned men, but just 65% accuracy on dark-skinned women. That is a huge discrepancy in a product that had been commercially released. This research was ground-breaking in bringing attention to a pernicious issue.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2023-05-16-ai-centralizes-power/gendershades.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:65.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Results from one of the GenderShades studies</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Some people have reacted with a superficial response, which is not consistent what the researchers wrote, concluding that the solution is solely to get more pictures of dark-skinned women and then call it a day. While issues of representation in underlying training datasets need to be addressed, this is only one part of the problem. We have to look at how these systems are used, which poses many other significant harms.</p>
</section>
<section id="harmful-if-it-doesnt-work-harmful-if-it-works" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="harmful-if-it-doesnt-work-harmful-if-it-works">Harmful if it doesn’t work; Harmful if it works</h2>
<p>In several USA cities, <a href="https://www.nbcmiami.com/investigations/miami-police-used-facial-recognition-technology-in-protesters-arrest/2278848/">police have</a> used <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2020/8/18/21373316/nypd-facial-recognition-black-lives-matter-activist-derrick-ingram">facial recognition</a> to <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2016/10/11/13243890/facebook-twitter-instagram-police-surveillance-geofeedia-api">identify Black people</a> protesting police racism and police murders of unarmed civilians. There’s a huge power issue when you look at this type of use of technology. I believe this is unethical whether or not it works. It is certainly terrible to misidentify people and arrest the wrong person, but it’s a threat to civil rights to identify protesters.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2023-05-16-ai-centralizes-power/police-facial-rec.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:75.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Headlines about police use of facial recognition to identify protesters in Miami, NYC, and Baltimore</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p><a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2019/11/19/technology/artificial-intelligence-bias.html">Dr.&nbsp;Timnit Gebru wrote</a>, <em>“A lot of times, people are talking about bias in the sense of equalizing performance across groups. They’re not thinking about the underlying foundation, whether a task should exist in the first place, who creates it, who will deploy it on which population, who owns the data, and how is it used?”</em> These are all crucial questions to ask. They are questions of power. Yes, you should check the error rates on different subgroups, but that alone is insufficient, and doesn’t address questions of power.</p>
<p>While the policing examples are from the USA, this is a pattern throughout history and throughout the world. <a href="https://digitalrepository.unm.edu/nmlr/vol50/iss3/2/">Professor Alvaro Bedoya wrote</a>, <em>“It is a pattern throughout history that surveillance is used against those considered ‘less than’, against the poor man, the person of color, the immigrant, the heretic. It is used to try to stop marginalized people from achieving power.”</em> The history of surveillance as a weapon used against the marginalised stretches back centuries and predates computers, but <strong>AI has now turbocharged this dynamic</strong>.</p>
</section>
<section id="operating-at-scale" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="operating-at-scale">Operating at scale</h2>
<p>Robodebt was a program where the Australian government created unlawful debts for hundreds of thousands of people through an automated system. People would be notified that they had been overpaid on welfare (often, this was false, but contesting it required documentation most people didn’t have) and that they now owed the government significant amounts of money. This destroyed many lives, even driving some <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/australia-news/2023/feb/20/platitudes-and-false-words-mother-of-robodebt-victim-who-took-own-life-tells-inquiry-of-government-stonewalling">victims to suicide</a>. A <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/australia-news/2020/may/29/robodebt-government-to-repay-470000-unlawful-centrelink-debts-worth-721m">detail that struck me</a> is that the number of debts issued went from 20,000 <em>per year</em>, back when it was a more manual process, to 20,000 <em>per week</em> with automation. That is a 50x scale up! <strong>Automation was used to drastically scale putting poor people into debt</strong>. This is another disturbing pattern in machine learning.</p>
</section>
<section id="centralizing-power" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="centralizing-power">Centralizing Power</h2>
<p>Machine learning often has the effect of centralizing power. It can be implemented with no system for recourse and no way to identify mistakes, as we saw earlier with people whose <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2018/3/21/17144260/healthcare-medicaid-algorithm-arkansas-cerebral-palsy">healthcare was wrongly cut due to a bug</a>. It can be used cheaply at massive scale, as shown with Robodebt. It can also replicate identical biases or errors at scale.</p>
<p>Often when I teach about how automated systems can cause harm, <a href="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2018-08-07-hbr-bias-algorithms/">people will point out</a> how humans make mistakes and are biased too. However, there are key differences in automated systems. It is not just plug-and-play interchangeable when you switch from a human decision maker to an automated decision maker.</p>
<p>Automated systems can also be used to evade responsibility. This is true of bureaucracy in general. While in non-automated bureaucracies you also get a passing of the buck (“I was just following orders” or ”it’s this other person’s fault”); however, as dana boyd has pointed out, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NTl0yyPqf3E">automated systems are often being used to extend bureaucracy</a> (as explained by danah boyd), adding additional places to deflect responsibility.</p>
<p>In the example health care software bug example that I shared, a journalist interviewed the creator of that algorithm. He is earning royalties through a private company, and he said it’s not the company’s responsibility to offer an explanation. He blamed policymakers for the errors. The policymakers could blame the particular people that implemented this software. Everyone can point to somebody else or even to the software itself. Systems where nobody takes responsibility do not lead to good outcomes.</p>
</section>
<section id="feedback-loops" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="feedback-loops">Feedback loops</h2>
<p>Feedback loops occur when you create the outcome that you were trying to predict. Data can become tainted from the output of the model. Furthermore, machine learning models can amplify bias, not just encode it. There have been <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1901.09451">multiple papers</a> showing that if <a href="https://www.wired.com/story/machines-taught-by-photos-learn-a-sexist-view-of-women/">you start</a> with <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1706.09847">a biased dataset</a> you can actually train a model that is even <strong>more</strong> biased than the training dataset.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2023-05-16-ai-centralizes-power/talk-power.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:75.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Screenshot from my talk at QUT, on ways that AI can centralize power</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>In summary, these are several reasons why machine learning can end up centralising power and why automated systems are different from human decision makers. AI researcher Pratyusha Kalluri advises us that rather than ask whether an AI application is fair to instead <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-020-02003-2">ask how it shifts power</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-people-impacted" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-people-impacted">The People Impacted</h2>
<p>Another thing I want to highlight about the healthcare example is that the people whose healthcare was incorrectly cut saw the problem right away, but there was no way to get that mistake acknowledged or addressed.</p>
<p>Another tragic example of people recognizing an issue but not being able to get it addressed is Facebook’s role in the genocide in Myanmar. In 2018, the UN found that Facebook had <a href="https://www.reuters.com/article/us-myanmar-rohingya-facebook-idUSKCN1GO2PN">played a “determining role”</a> in the genocide; however that was not not a surprise to anyone who had been following the events. A tech entepreneur <a href="https://www.wired.com/story/how-facebooks-rise-fueled-chaos-and-confusion-in-myanmar/">based in Myanmar said</a>, “That’s not 20/20 hindsight. The scale of this problem was significant. It was already apparent [going back to 2013].”</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2023-05-16-ai-centralizes-power/myanmar.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:75.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Articles about the role of Facebook in the Myanmar genocide</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>It’s important to understand that genocide does not come out of nowhere. It gradually escalates. From 2013, people warned executives about how Facebook was being used in Myanmar to incite violence and to dehumanize an ethnic minority. In 2013, 2014, and 2015, people raised warnings and they were not listened to.</p>
<p>An indication of how little Facebook did to address the issues is that the start of 2015 they only had two contractors who spoke Burmese, and they only hired 2 more that year. Compared to the number of Burmese-speaking users in Myanmar, it was a tiny number. Facebook invested very few resources in this (contrast the situation with when <a href="https://www.fast.ai/posts/2018-04-19-facebook.html#myanmar">Facebook rapidly hired over a thousand content moderators</a> in Germany to avoid a fine).</p>
<p>This is a pattern that we see over and over, that often the people most impacted by a system recognize the issues earliest, but they are not listened to and don’t have effective ways to raise an alarm. They also best understand the needed interventions for addressing the ethical risk. It is crucial that the people most impacted have avenues for participation and power.</p>
</section>
<section id="practical-resources" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="practical-resources">Practical Resources</h2>
<p>The <a href="https://icml.cc/virtual/2020/workshop/5720">participatory approaches to machine learning</a> workshop at ICML 2020 was fantastic. The organizers of the workshop highlighted that the designers of a machine learning system have far more power over the system than the individuals impacted. Even within algorithmic fairness or human-centered ML, <strong>ethics work is often focused on centralized solutions, which can further increase the power of system creators</strong>. The workshop organizers called for more democratic, cooperative, and participatory approaches.</p>
<p>I want to share some practical resources with you. The Markkula Center for Applied Ethics at Santa Clara University has a packet of resources online for ethics and technology practice and in particular I love their <a href="https://www.scu.edu/ethics-in-technology-practice/ethical-toolkit/">Tech Ethics Toolkit</a>. This is a set of practices that you could implement within your organization. As an example, tool 3 is “expanding the ethical circle”, which involves setting a regular time aside to make sure you are going through who all the stakeholders are that will be directly affected by a system, as well as who will be indirectly affected in significant ways. It involves asking whose skills, experiences, and values have we simply assumed rather than actually consulted. The toolkit goes into more detail about this on questions to ask and things to look for.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2023-05-16-ai-centralizes-power/diverse-voices.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:80.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Diverse Voices Guide</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Another useful resource on this is the <a href="https://techpolicylab.uw.edu/news/diverse-voices-guide/">Diverse Voices guide</a> from the University of Washington Tech Policy Lab. In addition to an academic paper, they have a practical how-to guide on assembling panels of groups who are not be well-represented and whose input you need. They include examples, such as panels of people who are formerly incarcerated, people who don’t drive cars, and extremely low income people.</p>
</section>
<section id="data-are-not-bricks-to-be-stacked-oil-to-be-drilled" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="data-are-not-bricks-to-be-stacked-oil-to-be-drilled">Data are not bricks to be stacked, oil to be drilled</h2>
<p>In conclusion, explainability on its own is insufficient; we need actionable recourse and contestability. Fairness is insufficient; we need justice. The people most impacted by a system need avenues for participation and power.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2023-05-16-ai-centralizes-power/talk-end.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:75.0%"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Screenshot from my talk at QUT</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>These are very difficult problems but some steps towards solutions are:</p>
<ul>
<li>making sure you have ways to identify, report, and address errors quickly</li>
<li>offering timely meaningful appeals</li>
<li>include consultation with voices that are often overlooked (and not just in a tokenistic way</li>
<li>designing products processes processes and technology with contestability in mind</li>
<li>diversity in hiring retention and promotions (diversity including nationality and language)</li>
</ul>
<p>I’ll close with a quote that I love from <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC7296309/">AI researcher Inioluwa Deborah Raji</a>, <em>“But data are not bricks to be stacked, oil to be drilled, gold to be mined, opportunities to be harvested. Data are humans to be seen, maybe loved, hopefully taken care of.”</em></p>
<p>The video version of my talk is <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=spHB7IEFXbg&amp;list=PLtmWHNX-gukLQlMvtRJ19s7-8MrnRV6h6&amp;index=6">available here</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="further-reading-watching" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="further-reading-watching">Further reading / watching</h2>
<p>You may also be intersted in:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=KChtdexd5Jo&amp;list=PLtmWHNX-gukLQlMvtRJ19s7-8MrnRV6h6&amp;index=6">The New Era in NLP | SciPy 2019 | Rachel Thomas</a>: keynote talk I gave at SciPy 2019, just after the release of GPT-2, about the technical advances and ethical risks of language models</li>
<li><a href="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2021-08-17-eleven-ethics-videos/">11 Short Videos About AI Ethics</a>: short videos about machine learning ethics, which I created for the fast.ai deep learning course</li>
<li><a href="https://www.cell.com/patterns/fulltext/S2666-3899(22)00056-3">Reliance on metrics is a fundamental challenge for AI</a>: academic paper David Uminsky and I wrote about how AI is perhaps too good at optimizing metrics, and the problems this can create</li>
</ul>


</section>

<p><br><br><i>I look forward to reading your responses. Create a free GitHub account to comment below.</i></p> ]]></description>
  <category>ethics</category>
  <category>machine learning</category>
  <guid>https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2023-05-16-ai-centralizes-power/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 15 May 2023 14:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://rachel.fast.ai/posts/2023-05-16-ai-centralizes-power/cuts-healthcare.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
